>>Paula Sherriff (Dewsbury) (Lab): If she
will list her official engagements for Wednesday
12 October.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): This
morning, I had meetings with ministerial colleagues
and others. In addition to my duties in this
House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Paula Sherriff: Previously, I worked in
an NHS service that the coalition Government
gifted to Virgin Care, which is now seeking
another contract covering my constituency.
Among many unethical practices that I witnessed,
Virgin imposed a system of double appointments,
forcing patients to have unnecessary extra
consultations before surgery, boosting its
profits at the expense of the taxpayer and
patient safety. Is that acceptable? If not,
what is the Prime Minister prepared to do
about it?
>>The Prime Minister: Of course, what we want
to see in the provision of local services
are the best services possible for local people.
The hon. Lady talks about outsourcing of services
in the NHS; I have to say to her that the
party that put greater privatisation into
the NHS was not my party but the Labour party.
>>Michael Fabricant (Lichfield) (Con): What
recent assessment she has made of (a) the
performance of the economy and (b) the adequacy
of provision of public services in the west
midlands; and if she will make a statement.
>>The Prime Minister: The west midlands economy,
I have to say, is in a very positive position
at the moment. I am very pleased to say that
since 2010 nearly 200,000 more people are
at work there, and there are 42,000 new businesses.
I saw the strength of the economy when I was
in Birmingham last week. Of course, we are
giving the west midlands new powers with the
devolution deal and the election of a Mayor.
Andy Street, with his business and local experience,
would be a very good Mayor for the west midlands.
>>Michael Fabricant: On the subject of the
NHS, 18 months ago my wonderful doctor, Helen
Stokes-Lampard, suggested that I have a general
“well man” check-up. It is just as well
that I did: the blood test revealed a problem
with my prostate, despite the fact that I
was symptom-free. I was immediately referred
to the Queen Elizabeth hospital in Birmingham,
whose staff were simply wonderful. After a
period of surveillance, I had a prostatectomy
back in June.
But hey—I’m now fine! [Hon. Members: “Hooray!”]
I want to thank the whole team at the QE,
including my surgeon Alan Doherty and my excellent
specialist prostate nurse Richard Gledhill,
who gave me practical advice. But, in the
next 10 years, there will be a real shortage
of specialist prostate and urology nurses,
as many are due for retirement. May I ask
the Prime Minister what the Government can
do to avert a shortage of these much needed
specialist nurses?
>>The Prime Minister: May I say to my hon.
Friend that the whole House is pleased to
see him back in his position as his normal
exuberant self? He raises a very serious issue.
I join him in commending not only those doctors,
nurses and other health service staff who
treated him for his prostate cancer, but those
doctors and nurses who, day in, day out, are
ensuring that, as we see, cancer survival
rates are at a record high.
The Government are putting more money into
awareness of cancer problems. We will look
at the training of nurses—50,000 nurses
are in training—and continue to make sure
that the specialisms are available to do the
work that is necessary in the health service.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): I,
too, join the Prime Minister in wishing the
hon. Member for Lichfield (Michael Fabricant)
well and obviously hope the treatment he got
is the same treatment that everybody else
gets, because we want good treatment for everybody
in our society. [Interruption.] It is not
controversial—I am just wishing him well.
Is that okay? I am sorry to start on such
a controversial note, Mr Speaker. I do apologise.
At the Conservative party conference, the
Prime Minister said she wants Britain to be
“a country where it doesn’t matter where
you were born”, but the Home Secretary’s
flagship announcement was to name and shame
companies that employ foreign workers. Could
the Prime Minister explain why where someone
was born clearly does matter to members of
her Cabinet?
>>The Prime Minister: First, may I congratulate
the right hon. Gentleman on winning the Labour
leadership election? [Interruption.] I welcome
him back to his place in this House as his
normal self. The policy that he has just described
was never the policy that the Home Secretary
announced? There was no naming and shaming,
no published list of foreign workers, no published
data. What we are going to consult on is whether
we should bring ourselves in line with countries
such as the United States of America, which
collect data in order to be able to ensure
that they are getting the right skills training
for workers in their economy.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I am most grateful to the
over 300,000 people that voted for me to become
the leader of my party, which is rather more
than voted for the Prime Minister to become
the leader of her party. She seems to be slightly
unaware of what is going on: first, the Home
Secretary briefed that companies would be
named and shamed; the Education Secretary
clarified that data would only be kept by
Government; yesterday, No. 10 said the proposal
was for consultation; and the Home Secretary
clarified the whole matter by saying, “it’s
one of the tools we are going to use”. This
Government have no answers, just gimmicks
and scapegoats. Yesterday, we learned that
pregnant women will be forced to hand over
their passports at NHS hospitals. No ultrasound
without photographic ID—heavily pregnant
women sent home on icy roads to get a passport.
Are these really the actions of “a country
where it doesn’t matter where you were born”?
>>The Prime Minister: I have made absolutely
clear the policy that the Home Secretary set
out. The right hon. Gentleman raises issues
around the health service. I think it is right
that we should say that we ensure, when we
are providing health services to people, that
they are free at the point of delivery; that
people are eligible to have those services;
that where there are people who come to this
country to use our health service, and who
should be paying for it, the health service
actually identifies them and makes sure that
it gets the money from them. I would have
thought that that would be an uncontroversial
view. Of course, emergency care will be provided,
when necessary, absolutely without those questions,
but what is important is that we ensure that
where people should be paying, because they
do not have the right to access free care
in the health service, they do so.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Some of the Prime Minister’s
colleagues on the leave side promised £350
million a week extra for the NHS. She does
not seem to have answers to the big questions
facing Britain. On Monday, the Secretary for
Brexit, when questioned about the Government’s
approach to single market access, replied:
“We…need hard data about the size of the
problem in terms of both money and jobs”
It would have been much easier if he had simply
asked his colleague, the Chancellor of the
Exchequer, because he would have been able
to tell him that the Treasury forecast is
a £66 billion loss to the economy—7.5%
of the GDP. Can the Prime Minister now confirm
that access to the single market is a red
line for the Government, or is it not?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
has asked me this question before. [Interruption.].
He says it is a simple question, and I will
give him the simple answer: what we are going
to do is deliver on the vote of the British
people to leave the European Union; what we
are going to do is be ambitious in our negotiations,
to negotiate the best deal for the British
people, and that will include the maximum
possible access to the European market, for
firms to trade with, and operate within, the
European market. But I am also clear that
the vote of the British people said that we
should control the movement of people from
the EU into the UK, and, unlike the right
hon. Gentleman, we believe we should deliver
on what the British people want.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Someone once said that in
leaving the single market “we risk a loss
of investors and businesses…and we risk
going backwards when it comes to international
trade.” That person is now the Prime Minister,
and that was before the referendum.
The Japanese Government wrote to the Prime
Minister in September, worried about a shambolic
Brexit. Many Japanese companies are major
investors in Britain—such as Nissan in Sunderland,
which has already halted its investment—and
140,000 people in Britain work for Japanese-owned
companies. They have made it clear that those
jobs and that investment depend on single
market access. What reassurance can she give
workers today, desperately worried about their
future, their company and their jobs?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I would say to
the right hon. Gentleman that the biggest
vote of confidence that we had in Britain
after the referendum vote was the £24 billion
investment from a Japanese company, SoftBank,
in taking over Arm. Secondly, in relation
to what we are doing in our negotiations,
he does not seem to get what the future is
going to be about. The UK will be leaving
the European Union. We are not asking ourselves
what bits of membership we want to retain.
We are saying: what is the right relationship
for the UK to have for the maximum benefit
of our economy and of the citizens of this
country?
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The right hon. Member for
Broxtowe (Anna Soubry) has said that “there
is a danger that this Government appear to
be turning their back on the single market”.
Staying in the single market was, indeed,
a commitment in the Conservative party manifesto.
The reality is that, since the Brexit vote,
the trade deficit is widening, growth forecasts
have been downgraded, the value of the pound
is down 16%, and an alliance of the British
Chambers of Commerce, the Confederation of
British Industry, the British Retail Consortium
and the Trades Union Congress have all made
representations to the Prime Minister demanding
clarity. Is the Prime Minister really willing
to risk a shambolic Tory Brexit just to appease
the people behind her?
>>The Prime Minister: What the Conservative
party committed to in its manifesto was to
give the British people a referendum on whether
to stay in the European Union. We gave the
British people that vote, and they have given
their decision: we will be leaving the European
Union. In doing that, we will negotiate the
right deal for the UK, which means the right
deal in terms of operating within and trading
with the European market. That is what matters
to companies here in the UK, and that is what
we are going to be ambitious about delivering.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The right hon. and learned
Member for Rushcliffe (Mr Clarke) often has
a mot juste to help us in these debates. He
simply said—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I want to hear about
the right hon. and learned Member for Rushcliffe.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: In his own inimitable way,
the right hon. and learned Gentleman said:
“The reason the pound keeps zooming south
is that absolutely nobody has the faintest
idea what exactly we’re going to put in
place.” Those of us on the Labour Benches
do respect the decision of the British people
to leave the European Union, but this is a
Government that drew up no plans for Brexit;
that now has no strategy for negotiating Brexit;
and that offers no clarity, no transparency
and no chance of scrutiny of the process for
developing a strategy. The jobs and incomes
of millions of our people are at stake. The
pound is plummeting, business is worrying
and the Government have no answers. The Prime
Minister says she will not give a running
commentary, but is it not time the Government
stopped running away from the looming threat
to jobs and businesses in this country and
to the living standards of millions of people?
>>The Prime Minister: Unlike the right hon.
Gentleman, I am optimistic about the prospects
of this country once we leave the European
Union; I am optimistic about the trade deals
that other countries are now actively coming
to us to say they want to make with the United
Kingdom; and I am optimistic about how we
will be able to ensure that our economy grows
outside the European Union. But I have to
say to the right hon. Gentleman that Labour
did not want a referendum on this issue—we,
the Conservatives, gave the British people
a referendum; and Labour did not like the
result—we are listening to the British people
and delivering on that result. [Interruption.]
The shadow Foreign Secretary is shouting from
a sedentary position. The shadow Foreign Secretary
wants a second vote. I have to say to her
that I would have thought Labour MPs would
have learned this lesson: you can ask the
same question again; you still get the answer
you don’t want.
>>Steve Double (St Austell and Newquay) (Con):
Despite several rounds of European regional
development funding, the Cornish economy continues
to lag about 30% behind the UK average. Does
the Prime Minister agree that Brexit provides
us with the opportunity to develop our own
economic programme, which will be less bureaucratic
and more effectively targeted and will offer
better value for money for the taxpayer, and
will she confirm that her Government will
continue to invest in the poorer regions of
our country, such as Cornwall, once we leave
the EU?
>>The Prime Minister: I can give my hon. Friend
that assurance. What I said at our party conference,
and have been saying since I became Prime
Minister, is that we want an economy that
works for everyone; that means for every part
of our country, including areas such as Cornwall
and the Isles of Scilly. We have already negotiated
a devolution deal with Cornwall, which was
signed in 2015; that demonstrates that we
recognise the challenges that Cornwall faces.
We are open to further discussions on ways
in which we can improve Cornwall’s economy
for the future.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): The European
Commission against Racism and Intolerance
has found that there are “a number of areas
of concern” regarding political discourse
and hate speech in the UK, as well as violent
racial and religious attacks. Police statistics
show a sharp rise in Islamophobic, anti-Semitic
and xenophobic assaults over the past year.
Does the Prime Minister agree that all mainstream
Governments and mainstream political parties
should do everything they can to oppose xenophobia
and racism?
>>The Prime Minister: I have been very clear
from this Dispatch Box on a number of occasions
that there is absolutely no place in our society
for racism or hate crime. It is right that
the police investigate allegations of hate
crime where they occur. I am pleased to say
that as Home Secretary I was able to bring
in arrangements that improved the recording
of hate crime. We also improved the requirement
on police specifically to record hate crime
relating to faith, so that we can see when
Islamophobia is taking place, as well as anti-Semitism
and other types of hate crime. There is no
place for such crime in our society. With
one voice, from across this Chamber, we should
make that absolutely clear, and give our police
every support in dealing with it.
>>Angus Robertson: I remind the Prime Minister
that when she was Home Secretary she put advertising
vans on the streets of this country telling
foreigners to go home. At her party conference
we heard that her party wishes to register
foreigners working in the UK. The crackdown
and the rhetoric against foreigners from this
Government have led to even UKIP—UKIP—saying
that things have gone too far. Across the
length and breadth of this land people are
totally disgusted by the xenophobic language
of her Government. Will she now confirm that
her Government’s intention is still to go
ahead with the registration of foreign workers,
but that we apparently should not worry, because
her Government will keep it secret?
>>The Prime Minister: May I say very gently
to the right hon. Gentleman that I answered
two questions on that earlier? I suggest he
should have listened to the answers I gave
then.
>>Daniel Kawczynski (Shrewsbury and Atcham)
(Con): We have empowered local doctors to
take real leadership over important reconfiguration
proposals. In Shropshire, 300 doctors, surgeons
and clinicians have been working on a vital
reconfiguration of A&E services in Shropshire
and in Wales. When they make their decision
on that later this month, it is very important
that the Government back them and provide
the capital funding required for this vital
change to enhance patient safety.
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important point. The configuration of services
in his constituency and others is obviously
a significant issue across the House. I am
pleased to say that we are now seeing more
people being treated in A&E. We will look
at the proposals. The point about how this
is being done is that local people should
be able to have their voice heard and the
decisions taken should reflect the needs in
a particular local area. We all want to see
that. A&E services are vital, and I pay tribute
to all those who work in A&E in hospitals
across the country.
>>Meg Hillier (Hackney South and Shoreditch)
(Lab/Co-op): The Public Accounts Committee
and the Comptroller and Auditor General have
both warned that the NHS budget is not sustainable.
When will the Prime Minister’s Government
wake up to the reality of growing demand,
avoid the political rhetoric and set a sustainable
NHS budget for this year and the future?
>>The Prime Minister: The Government took
a very simple approach. We asked the NHS itself
to propose its five-year plan for the NHS.
We asked it how much money it required. It
said £8 billion; we are giving it £10 billion,
which is more than the NHS said. Funding in
the NHS is at record levels. The only place
where money for the NHS is being cut is under
a Labour Administration in Wales.
>>Mr David Burrowes (Enfield, Southgate) (Con):
A young man with Asperger’s syndrome awaits
extradition to the United States to face charges
of computer hacking, and is then likely to
kill himself. It sounds familiar, but he is
not Gary McKinnon, who was saved by the Prime
Minister, but Lauri Love, who faces in effect
a death sentence. When the Prime Minister
introduced the forum bar to, in her words,
“provide greater safeguards for individuals”,surely
she expected it to protect the vulnerable
like Gary McKinnon, like Lauri Love?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend campaigned
long and hard for Gary McKinnon, and I obviously
took that decision. At that time, it was for
the Home Secretary to decide whether there
was a human rights case for an individual
not to be extradited. We subsequently changed
the legal position on that, so this is now
a matter for the courts. There are certain
parameters that the courts look at in terms
of the extradition decision, and that is then
passed to the Home Secretary, but it is for
the courts to determine the human rights aspects
of any case that comes forward. It was right
to introduce the forum bar to ensure that
challenge on whether cases should be heard
here, but the legal process is very clear,
and the Home Secretary is part of it.
>>Vernon Coaker (Gedling) (Lab): What does
the Prime Minister say to British steelworkers
who have lost their jobs or whose jobs are
threatened, given the news that French steel
is to be used for the new replacement Trident
submarines? Is that what she means by being
a party of the workers?
>>The Prime Minister: We recognise the concerns
of British steelworkers. That is why the Government
have worked, under both my predecessor and
I, to ensure that we do what we can to promote,
encourage and retain a steel industry here
in the United Kingdom. A number of measures
have been taken. If the hon. Gentleman was
in the Chamber earlier for Scottish questions,
he will have heard my right hon. Friend the
Secretary of State for Scotland setting them
out.
>>Mr Philip Hollobone (Kettering) (Con): Doctors
and nurses at Kettering general hospital are
treating a record number of patients with
increasingly world-class treatments, yet despite
being located in an area of rapid population
and housing growth, due to an historical anomaly
the local clinical commissioning groups are
among the most relatively underfunded in the
whole country. What can my right hon. Friend
the Prime Minister do to help address the
situation?
>>The Prime Minister: As my hon. Friend says,
we want to ensure that patients experience
the same high-quality care regardless of where
they live and wherever they are. That is why,
as I understand it, the funding for my hon.
Friend’s local clinical commissioning group
is being corrected to reflect more accurately
the local health need. An investment of more
than £757 million will be going into his
local area, which shows the Government’s
intention to ensure that we see a health service
that is working for everyone across the country,
but we can do that only with the economy to
back up the NHS.
>>Dr Alasdair McDonnell (Belfast South) (SDLP):
The Prime Minister will be aware that the
soft border between Northern Ireland and the
Irish Republic was vital in boosting the economy
of Northern Ireland. Does she understand the
confusion that has set in, and that many of
us feel? On the one hand, the Government define
their intention tightly to control the free
movement of people and labour, yet on the
other they assure us that that border between
Northern Ireland and the Republic will continue
to be open. Does she see the contradiction
for many of those directly affected, and whose
jobs are affected?
>>The Prime Minister: I have been clear, the
Secretary of State for Northern Ireland has
been clear, and the Taoiseach has also said
that, on both sides of the border, we do not
want to see a return to the borders of the
past. It is worth reminding the House that
the common travel area has been in place since
the 1920s, so it was there well before we
were both members of the European Union. We
are working with the Government of the Republic,
and I have had discussions on this with the
First Minister and the Deputy First Minister
of Northern Ireland. We want to ensure that
we do not see a return to the borders of the
past.
>>Andrew Stephenson (Pendle) (Con): Thanks
to the Government’s growth deal, the £32
million transformation of Brierfield Mill
in my constituency gets under way this week,
giving a new lease of life to the largest
redundant mill complex in Lancashire. May
I thank the Prime Minister for her support
and commend Pendle’s other bits in the latest
round of the growth deal as a great way to
build a country that works for everyone?
>>The Prime Minister: I commend my hon. Friend
for taking his opportunity to support the
bids from Pendle. He is absolutely right that
the money put in has enabled growth in local
projects like Brierfield Mill to be unlocked.
We have seen £250 million committed to the
Lancashire local enterprise partnership, £2.8
billion to the northern powerhouse through
the local growth fund, and the latest round
of funding is worth up to £1.8 billion, with
good bids coming in from local LEPs. We are
assessing the proposals, including those from
Pendle. They will be looked at with the seriousness
my hon. Friend would expect.
>>Liz Saville Roberts (Dwyfor Meirionnydd)
(PC): This is the first Christmas that Hayley
Aldirmaz of Pwllheli will not see her husband
Hasan. They have been together for 10 years
and married for over four, with two young
children. It is evident that they are in a
long-term relationship, but Hayley’s Turkish
husband was refused a spouse visa in 2012
because she earns less than the Home Office
threshold of £18,600. Last year, half the
full-time workers of Dwyfor Meirionnydd earned
only £293 a week or less. This, I might say,
compares with the Prime Minister’s own constituency,
where the median salary was £571, or almost
£30,000 a year. Can the Prime Minister explain
why living in Dwyfor Meirionnydd means Hayley
has less chance of a proper family life, and
will she please help to unite the family this
Christmas?
>>The Prime Minister: I will not comment on
the individual case. I know that the hon.
Lady sent me the details of this specific
case in writing. I will make sure that she
gets a full reply from the Immigration Minister.
On the broader issue she raises about the
income threshold for those wishing to join
a partner here in the United Kingdom, the
Government asked the independent Migration
Advisory Committee to advise on the level
of the income threshold. The committee suggested
a range of figures and we actually took the
lowest figure, £18,600, in that range. It
recommended that figure because it is the
level at which a British family generally
ceases to be able to access income-related
benefits, and is able to support themselves
and integrate into society. We believe it
is important that people coming here are able
to support themselves.
>>James Cartlidge (South Suffolk) (Con): My
constituents were delighted to learn this
week that Gainsborough’s House, a unique
museum and art gallery based in the very building
where Gainsborough was born in Sudbury, is
to receive almost £5 million of National
Lottery funding to become a national cultural
attraction. Will my right hon. Friend join
me in congratulating the director Mark Bills
and his team on their success, and does she
agree that if in Suffolk we are bold and positive
and go for devolution, we can look forward
to much more of this sort of transformative
investment in the years to come?
>>The Prime Minister: I join my hon. Friend
in commending all those who have been involved
in the bid at Gainsborough’s House. Many
people will enjoy visiting Gainsborough’s
House in the future as a result of the work
that will be able to be done. I know the importance
of the Heritage Lottery Fund. It supported
the excellent Stanley Spencer gallery in my
own constituency, so I have seen the impact
it can have. He is absolutely right. The point
about devolution deals is people coming together
with that ambition for their local area to
generate the transformative investment he
talks about. Suffolk is looking at the sort
of deal it might wish to have locally.
>>Mr Ben Bradshaw (Exeter) (Lab): With Russian
and Assad regime war planes bombing civilians
in Aleppo at an unprecedented rate, will the
Prime Minister join France in calling for
those responsible for these war crimes to
be referred to the International Criminal
Court? Will she re-examine, with allies, the
feasibility of a no-fly zone to protect the
Syrian people before it is too late?
>>The Prime Minister: We are very clear that
it is for the courts to decide where a war
crime is being committed. We co-sponsored
a UN Security Council resolution in May 2014
to refer those responsible for war crimes
and crimes against humanity in Syria, regardless
of affiliation, to the International Criminal
Court. Of course, that was vetoed by Russia
and China. On the issue of a no-fly zone,
this has been addressed. People have looked
at this over a number of years. The scenes
we see of the indiscriminate slaughter of
innocent civilians are absolutely appalling.
We want to see an end to that, but there are
many questions about a no-fly zone. Who is
it there to protect? Would it lead to Assad
bombing people in the expectation that they
would then move to that zone? How would a
safe area actually be enforced there? Who
would do that enforcement? There are many
questions that need to be looked at in those
sorts of issues. What we all know is that
the only real solution for peace and stability
in Syria is political transition, and it is
time Russia accepted that: that the future
of Syria is a political transition to a stable
Syria, free of Assad.
>>Fiona Bruce (Congleton) (Con): At Middlewich
High School in my constituency, the most vulnerable
pupils and their families are impressively
supported, pursuant to the school’s motto
of “Achievement for All”. Will the Prime
Minister confirm that under her plans for
education, and in a country that works for
everyone, parents can be assured that there
will be the right school place for their child,
whatever their ability?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for the example she has given of the work
that is taking place in her constituency.
The whole aim of the Government’s education
policy is to increase the number of good school
places, so parents can have the confidence
that their child will have a good school place
and they will have the school place that is
right for them. That is why we want to see
universities more involved in schools, more
faith schools being opened up and the independent
sector helping the state sector where that
is sensible and its expertise can help. And
yes, we do want to lift the ban that currently
says that one type of good new school cannot
be opened. It is illegal to open a new good
school that is a selective school. We want
to remove that ban so that pupils of all abilities
get the opportunity.
>>Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
The Prime Minister appears to have made a
choice, and that choice is to side with the
protectionists and nationalists who have taken
over her party, as surely as Momentum has
taken over the Labour party. She has chosen
a hard Brexit that was never on anybody’s
ballot paper and she has chosen to turn her
back on British business in the process. As
a result, petrol and food retailers have warned
of huge price rises at the pumps and on the
supermarket shelves in the coming days. When
will she put the interests of hard-working
British people ahead of an extremist protectionism
that absolutely nobody voted for?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman asks
about who we are siding with. I will tell
him who this Government are siding with. We
are siding with the British people, who voted
to leave the European Union. It is high time
the hon. Gentleman listened to the vote of
the British people and accepted that that
is exactly what we are going to do.
>>Victoria Prentis (Banbury) (Con): Does the
Prime Minister share my sadness that the majority
of Banbury’s babies cannot currently be
delivered, as I was, in the Horton general
hospital? Will she join me in using any influence
and putting any pressure we can on the trust
to encourage it to recruit the obstetricians
we need to reopen our much valued unit?
>>The Prime Minister: I can say that I believe
every effort is being made to fill the vacant
obstetrics posts at the Horton general hospital.
I understand that those mothers who are having
a midwife-led delivery are still able to go
to the Horton general hospital, but others
have to go to the John Radcliffe hospital
in Oxford. Maternity services are important
to people and I believe the trust is actively
looking to ensure it can fill those posts.
What matters is a safe maternity service for
mother and baby.
>>Ms Angela Eagle (Wallasey) (Lab): Many people
across the House will be reassured that the
Government accepted the amendment to the Opposition
motion to be debated later this afternoon
that guarantees that this House is able properly
to scrutinise the plan for leaving the European
Union before article 50 is invoked. Can she
tell us: will that scrutiny involve a vote?
>>The Prime Minister: I have to say to the
hon. Lady that the idea that Parliament was
somehow not going to be able to discuss, debate
or question issues around Brexit is, frankly,
completely wrong. Let me provide her with
some examples. The Secretary of State for
Exiting the European Union has already made
two statements—and I believe four hours
of questions followed from those. A new Select
Committee has been set up, which crucially
includes representatives from all parts of
the United Kingdom to look at these issues.
Only just over a week ago, I announced that
there will be a great repeal Bill in the next
Session to repeal the European Communities
Act 1972. Parliament will thus have every
opportunity to debate this issue.
>>Will Quince (Colchester) (Con): Every year
in the UK, 3,500 babies are still-born, and
I commend the Government for setting the target
of a 20% reduction by the end of this Parliament
and a 50% reduction by 2030. Does the Prime
Minister agree that in Baby Loss Awareness
Week we must do all we can to provide the
best-quality bereavement care for those parents
who sadly lose a baby?
>>The Prime Minister: I think my hon. Friend
is absolutely right, and I am pleased to say
that the Health Secretary will attend the
Baby Loss Awareness Week reception, which
will be held in Parliament immediately after
today’s Prime Minister’s Questions. I
encourage other Members to attend it, too.
My hon. Friend is absolutely right that the
loss of a baby must be absolutely devastating;
I am aware that some people sitting in this
Chamber have been through that tragedy in
their lives. What is absolutely essential
is that the best possible bereavement care
be given to parents at this tragic moment
in their lives when they are at their most
vulnerable. That is why we have provided money
to introduce dedicated bereavement rooms at
40 hospitals, as well as investing more in
improving birthing facilities, which are also
important. Care and counsel for people who
have lost a baby is essential; I think we
all accept that.
>>Stella Creasy (Walthamstow) (Lab/Co-op):
On 2 July, the Home Office was given details
of the 178 children who are still stuck in
the Calais refugee camp, but who had a legal
right to be here in the UK with their families
to keep them safe and protected. Given the
delays in acting, what responsibility does
the Prime Minister think this Government have
to the 18 of those children who have now gone
missing?
>>The Prime Minister: Far from not acting,
this Government have been working with the
French Government on dealing with those who
are in the camps. We have put extra resource
into speeding up the process of dealing with
the claims of the unaccompanied children,
making that process faster and quicker, with
more children coming here as a result. That
is alongside all the other work we are doing
in relation to refugees and unaccompanied
minors. Crucially, of course, we are also
working to ensure that we deal with the traffickers
and the smugglers who are often in the camps;
we need to make sure that they do not have
access to children in the future. We have
speeded up the process and more children are
coming here as a result.
>>Jo Churchill (Bury St Edmunds) (Con): Tomorrow
is secondary breast cancer awareness day,
and I would like to ask the Prime Minister
to join me in wishing these men and women
well. Currently, only a third of NHS trusts
collect the data in this area. Does my right
hon. Friend agree that better data collection
can inform diagnosis, treatment and the use
of NHS resources across the piece and give
better outcomes for all patients?
>>The Prime Minister: I entirely accept my
hon. Friend’s point that better information
provides greater opportunity to address these
issues. I join her in commending and wishing
well all those—as she says, both men and
women—who have suffered from breast cancer
and who have come through that, as I know
my hon. Friend has. Other Members and so many
people across the country are in the same
position; it is important that they receive
the right care so that they can come through
that and see a bright future.
>>Alison McGovern (Wirral South) (Lab): Last
night, a huge number of MPs presented in this
House WASPI—Women Against State Pension
Inequality—petitions from towns up and down
the country, so will the Prime Minister now
commit to overturning those mistaken arrangements
of 2011 and provide justice and transitional
arrangements for WASPI women?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady should
know that transitional arrangements are already
in place. We did make changes. We committed
£1 billion to lessen the impact of the state
pension age changes on those who were affected,
so that no one would experience a change of
more than 18 months. In fact, 81% of women’s
state pension ages will increase by no more
than 12 months, compared to the previous timetable.
The Department for Work and Pensions informed
people of the change in the state pension
age after the changes that were made in 2011.
Moreover, in the future women will gain from
the new pension arrangements that are being
introduced. Women’s pensions are a long-standing
issue, but there will be better pension arrangements
for them in the future because of the changes
that the Government have made.
>>Rishi Sunak (Richmond (Yorks)) (Con): I
gather that the Prime Minister made Chancellor
Merkel a gift of Wainwright’s “Coast to
Coast Walk”, which describes the fabulous
walk that runs through my constituency. Is
she aware that the “coast to coast” is
not, in fact, an official national trail,
and will she meet me to discuss my campaign
to give this national treasure its deserved
national status?
>>The Prime Minister: As my hon. Friend knows,
I enjoy walking as well. There are some fantastic
walks across the United Kingdom. I have not
yet done the “coast to coast” myself,
however; there is not much time for me to
do it at the moment. My hon. Friend probably
knows that the decision about the designation
of the “coast to coast” is more appropriately
one for Natural England, and I am sure that
he will do all he can to lobby Natural England
on the issue.