>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
know the whole House will wish to join me
in remembering all those who lost their lives
and were affected by the Aberfan disaster
50 years ago this week. It claimed the lives
of 144 people, the vast majority of them children.
It caused devastation to the local community.
It is right that we pause and reflect on this
important anniversary, and recognise the solidarity
and resilience of the people of Aberfan to
overcome this powerful tragedy.
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. I will have further
such meetings later today, in addition to
my duties in this House.
>>Mr Peter Bone (Wellingborough) (Con): May
I associate myself with the remarks of the
Prime Minister? I am of an age that I can
remember the terrible black and white film
of this tragedy. It affected everyone. We
in this House pass on our thoughts to the
people of Aberfan today.
Mr Speaker, as you might know it is my birthday
today. The Prime Minister has already given
me a huge birthday present by letting everyone
know that we will be out of the European Union
no later than 31 March 2019. May I press her
for another present? Her excellent policy
of closing Victorian prisons and opening modern
ones is spot-on. Will she support the reopening
of Wellingborough prison as part of this excellent
programme, or would she rather just sing happy
birthday?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to wish
my hon. Friend a very happy birthday today:
many happy returns! I hope that Mrs Bone is
going to treat the occasion in an appropriate
manner. [Laughter.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I want to hear what is
coming next.
>>The Prime Minister: Calm down, Mr Speaker.
On the serious issue about prisons, I welcome
the fact that my hon. Friend applauds the
policy we are following of closing out-of-date
prisons and building new ones. I hear the
lobbying he has made for Wellingborough, and
I can assure him that Wellingborough is one
of the sites that is being considered. The
Secretary of State will look at the issue
very carefully and make an announcement in
due course.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): I
join the Prime Minister in commemorating the
disaster at Aberfan all those years ago when
118 children along with many adults died.
Many in that community are still living with
that tragedy, and they will live with it for
the rest of their days. As a young person
growing up at that time, I remember it well,
particularly the collections for the disaster
fund. The BBC documentary presented by Huw
Edwards was brilliant and poignant, and serves
to remind us all of what the disaster was
about.
One in four of us will suffer a mental health
problem. Analysis by the King’s Fund suggests
that 40% of our mental health trusts had their
budgets cut last year, and six trusts have
seen their budgets cut for three years in
a row. Is the Prime Minister really confident
that we are delivering parity of esteem for
mental health?
>>The Prime Minister: First, like the right
hon. Gentleman and my hon. Friend the Member
for Wellingborough (Mr Bone), I am of an age
when I can remember seeing on television those
terrible scenes of what happened in Aberfan.
I did not see the whole of Huw Edwards’
documentary, but I thought the bits that I
happened to see last night were very poignant,
as the right hon. Gentleman said. Interestingly,
what it showed again was the issue of those
in power not being willing to step up to the
plate initially and to accept what had actually
happened, but the inquiry was very clear about
where the responsibility lay.
It is right that we are introducing parity
of esteem for mental health in our national
health service. We have waited too long for
this, and it is important that it is being
done. We are actually investing more in mental
health services—an estimated record £11.7
billion. In particular, we are increasing
the overall number of children’s beds to
the highest number for mental health problems,
which I think is important. There is, of course,
more for us to do in looking at mental health,
but we have made an important start and, as
I say, that funding will be there.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I received a letter from
Colin, who has a family member with a chronic
mental health condition. Many others, like
him, have relatives going through a mental
health crisis. He says that the “NHS is
so dramatically underfunded” that too often
it is left to the underfunded police forces
to deal with the consequences of this crisis.
Indeed, the chief constable of Devon and Cornwall
has this month threatened legal action against
the NHS because he is forced to hold people
with mental conditions in police cells because
there are not enough NHS beds. I simply ask
the Prime Minister this: if the Government
are truly committed to parity of esteem, why
is this trust and so many others facing an
acute financial crisis at the present time?
>>The Prime Minister: May I first of all say
to Colin that I think all of us in this House
recognise the difficulties people have when
coping with mental health problems? I commend
those in this House who have been prepared
to stand up and refer to their own mental
health problems. I think that has sent a very
important signal to people with mental health
issues across the country.
The right hon. Gentleman raises the whole
question of the interaction between the NHS
and police forces. I am very proud of the
fact that when I was Home Secretary I actually
worked with the Department of Health to bring
a change to the way in which police forces
dealt with people in mental health crisis.
That is why we see those triage pilots out
on the streets and better NHS support being
given to police forces, so that the number
of people who have to be taken to a police
cell as a place of safety has come down. Overall,
I think it has more than halved, and in some
areas it has come down by even more than that.
This is a result of the action that this Government
have taken.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The reality is that no one
with a mental health condition should ever
be taken to a police cell. Such people should
be supported in the proper way, and I commend
the police and crime commissioners who have
managed to end the practice in their areas.
The reality is, however, that it is not just
Devon and Cornwall that are suffering cuts;
the Norfolk and Suffolk mental health trust
has been cut in every one of the last three
years.
I agree with the Prime Minister that it is
a very good thing for Members to stand up
and openly discuss mental health issues that
they have experienced, because we need to
end the stigma surrounding mental health conditions
throughout the country. However, NHS trusts
are in a financial crisis. According to NHS
Providers, it seems to be the worst financial
crisis in NHS history: 80% of acute hospitals
are now in deficit. There was a time, in 2010,
when the NHS was in surplus. What has happened?
>>The Prime Minister: Let me remind the right
hon. Gentleman what has happened in relation
to NHS funding. We asked the NHS itself to
come up with a five-year plan, and we asked
the NHS itself to say what extra funding was
needed to deliver on that. The NHS came up
with its five-year plan, led by Simon Stevens
as its chief executive. He said that £8 billion
was needed. We are giving £10 billion of
extra funding to the NHS. I might also remind
the right hon. Gentleman that at the last
election, it was not the Conservative party
that was refusing to guarantee funding for
the NHS; it was the Labour party.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: In six years, the NHS has
gone from surplus to the worst crisis in its
history. A total of £3 billion was wasted
on a top-down reorganisation that no one wanted,
and Simon Stevens made it very clear to the
Select Committee yesterday that he did not
believe that NHS England had enough money
to get through the crisis that it is facing.
May I offer an analysis from the Care Quality
Commission, which seems to have quite a good
grasp of what is going on? It says that cuts
in adult social care are
“translating to increased A&E attendances,
emergency admissions and delays to people
leaving hospital, which in turn is affecting
the ability of a growing number of trusts
to meet their performance and financial targets.”
Will the Prime Minister also address the reckless
and counterproductive adult social care cuts
that were made by her predecessor?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
quoted what had been said by Simon Stevens,
the chief executive of NHS England. At the
time of the autumn statement last November,
he said that “our case for the NHS has been
heard and actively supported.”
The right hon. Gentleman also raised the question
of social care, and the interaction between
healthcare and social care. More than £5
billion extra was put into the better care
fund in order to deal with precisely those
issues, and local authorities are able to
raise 2% of council tax to deal with the social
care costs that they face. What is important,
however, is for the health service and local
authorities to work together to ensure that
they deliver the best possible service to
people who require that social care. I saw
a very good example of that at Salford Royal
on Monday, and I want to see more examples
throughout the national health service, delivering
for patients. We have put in the funding,
which the right hon. Gentleman’s party would
not have done, so that the NHS will receive
better care for patients.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: We all want local government
and the NHS to work closely together, but
the problem is that local government funding
has been cut, and 400,000 fewer people are
receiving publicly funded social care as a
result. The NHS is having difficulty coping
with the crisis that it is in, and unfortunately
there is bed-blocking. Acute patients cannot
leave, because no social care is available
for them somewhere down the line. The issue
is a funding crisis in both the NHS and local
government. Figures published by NHS trusts
show that the total deficit is £2.45 billion,
but the chief executive of NHS Providers says
that the figure may be even bigger. The Government
are disguising the extent of the crisis through
temporary bailouts. [Interruption.] They are
bailing out trusts in a crisis. That is, of
course, a good thing, but why are the trusts
in
a crisis in the first place?
Next month, sustainability and transformation
plans are going to be published. Many people
across the country are quite alarmed by this
because of the threat to accident and emergency
departments. Will the Prime Minister deal
with this issue now by quite simply saying
there will be no downgrades and no closures
of A&E departments in the statement coming
out next month?
>>The Prime Minister: I say to the right hon.
Gentleman that over the course of this Parliament,
the Government will be spending over half
a trillion pounds on the national health service.
That is a record level of investment in our
national health service. There is a key difference
between the way the right hon. Gentleman approaches
this and how I approach it: Conservative Members
believe that people at a local level should
be able to make decisions about the national
health service, and that decisions about the
national health service should be led by clinicians—it
should not be a top-down approach, which is
typical of the Labour party.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Wow! Well, top-down was what
we got. It cost £3 billion for a reorganisation
that nobody wanted at all.
I started by asking the Prime Minister about
parity of esteem. All this Government have
produced is parity of failure—failing mental
health patients; failing elderly people who
need social care; failing the 4 million on
NHS waiting lists; failing the five times
as many people who are waiting more than four
hours at A&E departments—and another winter
crisis is looming. The Society for Acute Medicine
has it right when it says that this funding
crisis and the local government funding crisis
are leaving the NHS “on its knees”.
>>The Prime Minister: What has happened in
the NHS over the past six years? More patients
being treated, more calls to the ambulance
service, more operations, more doctors, more
nurses—that is what has been happening in
the NHS. But let us just look at the right
hon. Gentleman’s party’s approach to the
national health service: a former shadow Health
Secretary said that it would be “irresponsible”
to put more money into the national health
service; and a former leader of the Labour
party wanted to “weaponise” the national
health service. At every election the Labour
party claims that the Conservatives will cut
NHS spending; after every election we increase
NHS spending. At every election Labour claims
the Tories will privatise the NHS; after every
election when we have been in government we
have protected the NHS. There is only one
party that has cut funding for the NHS: the
Labour party in Wales.
>>Marcus Fysh (Yeovil) (Con): Is the Prime
Minister aware that research shows that infrastructure
investment most benefits areas that are prepared
to capitalise on it with new associated possibilities
for housing, skills and jobs? Will she ensure
that current opportunities are taken for inward
investment to preserve and re-energise essential
national industries such as rotorcraft in
the Yeovil area as we seek to capitalise on
the dualling of the A303?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right. We are right to invest in infrastructure
such as the A303. That can make a real difference
to local communities, but it is important
that local communities embrace those opportunities.
I know that my hon. Friend has been putting
together ideas for a vision for Yeovil and
I am sure he will share them with my right
hon. Friend the Communities Secretary.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): I join the
Prime Minister and the leader of the Labour
party in remembering the Aberfan disaster.
Our thoughts are with everyone affected by
that.
Thousands of innocent civilians have now been
killed by Saudi air strikes in Yemen. Can
the Prime Minister assure the House that those
civilians have not been killed by Paveway
IV missiles partially manufactured in Scotland
that are under licence from her Government
to Saudi Arabia?
>>The Prime Minister: First, may I congratulate
the right hon. Gentleman on his election as
deputy leader of the Scottish National party?
As the right hon. Gentleman knows, we have
one of the toughest regimes in the world in
relation to arms exports. When allegations
arise, we press—I have pressed in the past
and my right hon. Friend the Foreign Secretary
has pressed—the Saudi Arabia Government
to properly investigate the issues and to
learn lessons from them.
>>Angus Robertson: I thank the Prime Minister
for her kind wishes but, to return to the
subject of my question, it is beyond doubt
that Saudi air forces are bombing Yemen. Planes
made in Britain are being flown by pilots
who were trained by Britain and dropping missiles
that are made in Britain. I asked her a direct
question and she could not answer it, so I
will try a second time. Can she give the House
an assurance that civilians have not been
killed by Paveway IV bombs being dropped on
Yemen that are partially manufactured in Scotland
under license by her Government? If she does
not know the answer to that question, how
can she possibly, in good conscience, continue
selling them to Saudi Arabia?
>>The Prime Minister: In response to the right
hon. Gentleman, the point that I made was
very simple: we press for proper investigations
into what has happened in those incidents
before we reach a decision or a conclusion.
We have a very strong relationship with Saudi
Arabia, which is important for this country
in terms of dealing with counter-terrorism
and a number of other issues, but what matters,
when incidents happen about which there is
concern, is that they are properly investigated.
>>Nigel Adams (Selby and Ainsty) (Con): A
few weeks ago I thought that I had successfully
bought four tickets online for one of my favourite
bands, Green Day, only to be told that the
tickets were unavailable and the gig was sold
out, but within minutes I could buy the tickets
on another site, for twice the price. It turns
out that the ticket site had been the victim
of a computerised attack by organised touts
who then resell tickets at inflated prices.
Will the Prime Minister ask her Ministers
to give close consideration to my amendment
to the Digital Economy Bill that would make
the computerised harvesting of tickets for
resale an offence? Similar legislation exists
elsewhere, and it would go a long way towards
protecting consumers and genuine music fans.
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising that issue. I am sure that he
is not the only Member of the House who has
had that experience, and he is certainly not
the only person who has been affected, as
Members will know from their constituency
mailbags. The Consumer Rights Act 2015 introduced
a review of online ticket sales. Professor
Mike Waterson’s independent report on online
secondary ticketing makes a number of recommendations,
including some whereby the industry itself
could better protect itself from the problem.
The Government will look very carefully at
those recommendations to see what can be done
to address the issue.
>>Lisa Nandy (Wigan) (Lab): The child abuse
inquiry needs to regain the trust of survivors.
In September, the Home Secretary said that
she had no information about serious leadership
failings, but on Monday she told the House
that she had known about serious problems
since July. Yesterday it emerged that senior
Home Office officials were briefed as early
as April. The Prime Minister set up the inquiry
and appointed the chair. She was the individual
responsible for the inquiry’s success. She
was the Home Secretary in April and the only
person who had the power to act. Will she
now finally tell us when she personally learned
of the serious problems developing in the
inquiry, and why she took no action at all?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise that the
hon. Lady has taken a particular interest
in this issue. I am sure that she will recognise,
as I hope other Members do, why it was that
I set up the inquiry. For too long, people
who had been subjected to child—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order.
>>The Prime Minister: For too long, the voices
of people who had been subjected to child
sexual abuse went unheard and they felt that
they were not getting justice. That is why
it is very important that the inquiry is able
to continue and to find that justice for them.
I have to say to the hon. Lady that one of
the important aspects of this is that, over
the years, too many people have had concerns
that those in positions of power have intervened
to stop them getting justice. There were stories
around about the inquiry and about individuals
related to the inquiry, but the Home Secretary
cannot intervene on the basis of suspicion,
rumour or hearsay.
The hon. Lady refers to the statement that
was made in this House yesterday about information
being discussed with a director general at
the Home Office. She will also have noted
that it was asked that that conversation would
be confidential, and it was, as far as I am
aware, treated as such. It is important for
us to recognise that when the Home Office
was officially informed of issues, it acted.
It is now for the inquiry to get on and deliver
for victims and survivors.
>>Mrs Cheryl Gillan (Chesham and Amersham)
(Con): Having been born in and grown up in
south Wales, and as a former Secretary of
State for Wales, may I associate myself with
the heartfelt tributes paid by Members on
the Front Bench and throughout this House
to the valley community of Aberfan? That absolutely
unparalleled tragedy stunned the world. Will
the Prime Minister now step up to the plate,
to use her own words, reconfirm her commitment
to Wales and ensure that her Government work
with the Welsh Government, particularly after
leaving the EU, to maintain the investment
that is so vital to the long-term social and
economic development of the valleys communities
and the rest of Wales?
>>The Prime Minister: As a former Secretary
of State for Wales, my right hon. Friend is
well aware of the impact of the Aberfan disaster
on south Wales and those local communities.
As I said in my opening remarks, the events
were absolutely tragic and the thoughts of
the whole House are with those affected by
them. I can give the commitment that she is
asking for to Wales and to working with the
Welsh Government. I am clear that this Government
will deliver a country that works for everyone,
and that means every part of the United Kingdom.
Of course, the Wales Bill will put in place
a historic transfer of powers to the Welsh
Assembly. It will allow the Welsh Government
to focus on the job of transforming the Welsh
economy and, of course, we are talking to
the Welsh Government about how we go forward
with negotiations for leaving the EU.
>>Mr Speaker: Order. Progress today has been
very slow, so I appeal to colleagues to speed
up. I call Stephen Pound.
>>Stephen Pound (Ealing North) (Lab): I am
much obliged, Mr Speaker. Can there be a single
Member of this House who does not have reason
to be grateful to those heroes of our high
street, community pharmacists? Can there be
any member of the public who is not as bemused
as I am that the Government are proposing
a 12% cut in the community pharmacy budget,
potentially leading to 3,000 closures? Will
the Prime Minister express her support for
community pharmacies and have another look
at this divisive, corrosive and destructive
proposal?
>>The Prime Minister: Everybody in this House
recognises the role and contribution of community
pharmacies up and down the country, but it
is also right that we look at how we are spending
NHS money. That is why the Government are
looking carefully at this whole issue. If
the hon. Gentleman supports community pharmacies,
perhaps he ought to have a word with the Leader
of the Opposition, because his right hon.
Friend’s policy is to nationalise the health
service completely, lock, stock and barrel—GP
surgeries, Macmillan nurses and community
pharmacies.
>>Richard Fuller (Bedford) (Con): May I welcome
the fact that next week this Government will
finally make a decision on airport capacity
in the south-east, which eluded three of my
right hon. Friend’s predecessors and will
help to boost trade? Does the Prime Minister
agree that, on this issue, substance matters
more than symbolism, and will she outline
to the House her timetable for implementation?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising this issue, and he is absolutely
right. This month, the Government will take
a decision on the appropriate site for extended
airport capacity in the south-east. The subject
has been debated, discussed and speculated
about for 40 years; this Government will take
a decision, but then a formal process has
to be undertaken. The Government will identify
their preferred site option. That will go
to a statutory consultation, and then the
Government will consider the results of that
consultation and introduce an airports national
planning statement on which the House will
vote.
>>Drew Hendry (Inverness, Nairn, Badenoch
and Strathspey) (SNP): Does the Prime Minister
agree that any move to close the historical
barracks at Fort George would be not only
a poor military decision after 250 years of
service, but a betrayal of the Black Watch
and a slap in the face to the highlands?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the strength
of the hon. Gentleman’s view. No decisions
on Fort George or other locations have been
taken and the Ministry of Defence will engage
with all parties impacted by any such decisions,
including in Scotland.
>>Mr Kenneth Clarke (Rushcliffe) (Con): My
right hon. Friend has expressed reluctance
to submit to the House even the broad plans
for our negotiations with the EU because of
worries that to do so might weaken her Government’s
negotiating position. She might have noticed
that, this week, one or more Brexiteer members
of her Cabinet have been briefing the newspapers
copiously on every proposal being put forward
in papers to the relevant Cabinet Committee
by their colleagues and launching political
attacks on Cabinet colleagues who seem to
disagree with them. Will she take firm action
to stop this process? Does she also agree
that the proper approach should involve parliamentary
scrutiny of the broad strategy, once her Government
have reached agreement on what it should be?
>>The Prime Minister: The Government are very
clear that the vote on 23 June was a vote
to ensure that we had control of movement
of people from the EU into the UK. Also, we
want the best possible access for businesses
for trading in goods and services, and for
operating within the European market. That
is what the Government will be aiming for,
and we will be ambitious in that. Parliament
will have its say. There are going to be lengthy
negotiations over the course of the two years
and more, and Parliament will have its say
in a whole variety of ways, not least in relation
to the great repeal Bill.
>>Maria Eagle (Garston and Halewood) (Lab):
Some of my constituents who have had their
tax credits suddenly stopped by Concentrix
have been accused of being in a relationship
with the previous tenants of their homes,
even though they have never met them, and
in some cases of being in a relationship with
members of their own families and told to
prove that they are not. This Kafkaesque situation
is causing deep distress and hardship among
working mothers in my constituency. Is this
what the Prime Minister means by being on
the side of working people? What is she going
to do to put this right?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady raises
an issue that is a matter of concern to Members
across the House. I am making sure that those
who are being assessed are being assessed
properly and that the right decisions are
being taken. The Department for Work and Pensions
is looking at the whole process of what should
be done and how those assessments should be
undertaken. I hope that she welcomes the fact
that this Government have said that those
with long-term conditions that are not going
to improve will not be put through the regular
assessments that they had under her Labour
Government.
>>Rebecca Pow (Taunton Deane) (Con): The first
nuclear science degree apprenticeship, with
apprenticeships with EDF at Hinkley Point
and with the Ministry of Defence, has just
been launched at Bridgwater and Taunton College.
This is at the forefront of the Government’s
apprenticeship reform policy. The course combines
academic study with practical work experience
and it is paid. Does the Prime Minister agree
that this is exactly the kind of business-led
course that the nation needs if it is to forge
ahead?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely agree with
my hon. Friend. I commend Bridgwater and Taunton
College for the steps it is taking to work
with businesses to ensure that its courses
are what business needs. That is exactly what
we want to see. We also want a regeneration
of our expertise in the nuclear industry.
>>Anne McLaughlin (Glasgow North East) (SNP):
The Prime Minister recently celebrated her
60th birthday, but she is not going to retire.
That is her choice, but she is denying that
same choice to many of my constituents, including
women such as Christine from Springburn, who
has worked every bit as hard as the Prime
Minister, but will now have to work for an
extra six years. When will the Prime Minister
do the right thing and give the WASPI women
their transitional arrangements so that they,
too, can make the choices that she enjoys?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure that the hon.
Lady knows that we have transitional arrangements
in place and that action was taken by the
Government to ensure that the period of time
for the pension age change would be no more
than 18 months compared with the previous
timetable. For 81% of women affected by the
2011 change, it will be no more than 12 months.
>>Heidi Allen (South Cambridgeshire) (Con):
The employment figures that have come out
today are of course fantastic news, but I
am wary about the economic volatility that
could result from Brexit, with the potential
for inflation to rise and the cost of living
to go up for people on very modest wages.
Does the Prime Minister agree that we need
to keep as many people in employment as possible?
We have made the right decision on tax credits.
May I urge her personally, ahead of the autumn
statement, to look at the cuts that are still
embedded in universal credit to ensure that
she understands what they will do to people
who are trying to get into work?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is right
to talk about the importance of getting people
into work, which has a benefit not just in
terms of families having an income. I am proud
of the Conservative Government’s record
over the past six years of getting more and
more people into work so that hundreds of
thousands fewer households now have no work
income coming in. That is extremely important.
The point of universal credit is to ensure
that the transition from benefits into work
means that people do see a benefit if they
get into the workplace. The previous system
meant that some people said that they were
better off on benefits. We want to see people
in work and that is what the system is there
to encourage.
>>Alison Thewliss (Glasgow Central) (SNP):
I have been asking questions for 15 months
about this Tory Government’s appalling two-child
policy and rape clause, but the Government
still do not know how it will work. From one
feminist to another, can the Prime Minister
tell me how she justifies putting vulnerable
women through the trauma of proving that their
third child was born as the result of rape?
>>The Prime Minister: We have been clear that
women who have a third child as a result of
rape would not be subject to the limit that
is being considered in relation to benefits.
I absolutely recognise that the hon. Lady’s
point addresses concern about dealing with
individuals who have been through the trauma
of rape, and that is why the Government are
taking their time to consider that. We are
consulting at the moment and looking at how
to ensure that we do this in absolutely the
right way.
>>Sir Hugo Swire (East Devon) (Con): Given
the increasing relevance of the Commonwealth
for trade, will the Prime Minister give her
personal support to the first ever meeting
of Commonwealth Trade Ministers here in the
UK next year? When she goes to India next
month, will she commit to persuade Prime Minister
Modi to attend the 2018 Commonwealth Heads
of Government meeting in the UK?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to encourage
all leaders to attend CHOGM when it takes
place here in the United Kingdom. I assure
my right hon. Friend that we are indeed looking
at the possibility of trade deals in relation
to the Commonwealth. I applaud that first
ever meeting of Commonwealth Trade Ministers,
which is an important step as we look to forge
a new global role in the world, ensuring that
we make a success of leaving the EU and trading
our way around the world.
>>Mr Jamie Reed (Copeland) (Lab): Local clinicians
are absolutely clear that the removal of 24-hour
consultant-led maternity services from the
West Cumberland hospital in Whitehaven will
cost lives. Ultimately, it is a decision that
the Government will have to make. Will the
Prime Minister please commit today to visit
my constituency to see what the effect of
the decision will be on west Cumbrian families,
women and children?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise that this
is not the first time that the hon. Gentleman
has raised concerns about West Cumberland
hospital. The point of how we are approaching
this is that decisions are taken at and generated
from the local level. It is the local area
that will be looking at the services that
people need, and at ensuring that they can
be provided and are safe for his constituents
and those in other parts of Cumbria.
>>Robert Neill (Bromley and Chislehurst) (Con):
The tragic murder of one prisoner and the
critical wounding of two others at Pentonville
prison last night brings home the stark decline
in safety in our prisons. Will the Prime Minister
give the Secretary of State for Justice her
full support in commissioning an immediate,
thorough and complete review of the operation,
management, capacity, leadership and resourcing
of the National Offender Management Service,
which has singularly failed to arrest this
declining situation?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
a matter that was one of the first issues
that my right hon. Friend the Lord Chancellor
and Secretary of State for Justice raised
with me: violence and safety in prisons. That
is why my right hon. Friend is looking across
the board at the action that needs to be taken.
She has already announced extra money for
more staff in prisons and recognises the importance
of this particular issue.
>>Lucy Powell (Manchester Central) (Lab/Co-op):
Just one in every 1,000 pupils is a child
on free school meals in a grammar school.
Does the Prime Minister agree that that tiny
number is a flimsy evidence base on which
to create a new national schools policy? Would
it not be better for her to look at the real
evidence base and at how to reduce inequality
in education?
>>The Prime Minister: I want to see every
child getting the education that is right
for them. I want every child to be able to
get on as far as their talents and hard work
will take them. That is why we need to increase
the number of good schools in this country.
If we look at the gap in attainment in grammar
schools between those who are from disadvantaged
backgrounds and those who are not, we see
that it is virtually zero—that is the not
the same in other schools. I just say to the
hon. Lady that it is wrong that we have a
system in this country where a law prevents
the opening or expansion of good schools.
That is what we are going to get rid of.
>>Pauline Latham (Mid Derbyshire) (Con): Will
the Prime Minister work with her Ministers
and Secretaries of State to champion a reduction
in the ivory trade and in the trade in the
organs of endangered species throughout the
world so that this country tries to lead by
example?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important issue. This is something the
Government have been taking up, and I can
assure her that my right hon. Friend the Foreign
Secretary has not only heard her representations,
but promoted this as an issue that the Government
will take up.
>>Robert Flello (Stoke-on-Trent South) (Lab):
The pottery industry is witnessing a modest
renaissance, in part through EU exports and
EU action on Chinese ceramic dumping. The
previous Prime Minister said that he would
make sure that the ceramic industry’s voice
is heard and that we would get a good negotiation.
What is this Prime Minister doing to ensure
that Stoke-on-Trent’s ceramic manufacturers
maintain both tariff-free access to the EU
and a level playing field in the face of protectionist
dumping?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very pleased to
welcome the renaissance in the ceramics industry
that the hon. Gentleman refers to. His constituency,
of course, has a long-standing history of
and tradition in ceramics. What are we doing?
As we go through the negotiations for leaving
the European Union, we will be ensuring that
this country has the best possible access
to trade with and operate within that European
market. That is what people want and that
is what we will deliver.
>>Oliver Dowden (Hertsmere) (Con): Many constituents
have contacted me to express concern about
anti-Semitism. I am sure that every Member
of this House can agree that we should show
zero tolerance of anti-Semitism, but does
the Prime Minister also agree that we must
ensure that all parties do not allow a situation
to arise in which it appears that an environment
is created where anti-Semitism is tolerated?
>>The Prime Minister: Yes, I absolutely agree
with my hon. Friend that this House should
send a very clear message that we will not
tolerate anti-Semitism. I have been concerned
about the rise in the number of incidents
of anti-Semitism in this country. We should
very clearly ensure that those incidents of
anti-Semitism are properly investigated and
dealt with, and that we give the clear message
that we will not tolerate it. But that does
have to be done by every single political
party in this Chamber, and I say to the Leader
of the Opposition that given the report of
the Home Affairs Committee about anti-Semitism
and the approach to anti-Semitism in the Labour
party, he needs to think very carefully about
the environment that has been created in the
Labour party in relation to anti-Semitism.
>>Andy Burnham (Leigh) (Lab): We are now just
one month from the start of the new inquest
into the Birmingham pub bombings. West Midlands
police has set aside for itself a legal fund
of £1 million, but as of today, the bereaved
families have no legal funding. Prime Minister,
this is a shameful state of affairs. Please
intervene and show the Birmingham families
the same compassion as was shown to the Hillsborough
families.
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
might be aware that the Birmingham families
have been encouraged to apply—I believe
they have applied—to the legal aid fund
for exceptional funding. That was, as I understand
it, what happened after the 7/7 bombings.
The Home Secretary has made clear her expectation
that funding will be provided. We are waiting
for the decision from the legal aid fund,
and we are hopeful that it will be a positive
one.
>>Mrs Theresa Villiers (Chipping Barnet) (Con):
Why attempt to build a new runway at Heathrow
when we could deliver one at Gatwick in half
the time, for half the cost and with a fraction
of the environmental impact?
>>The Prime Minister: I assure my right hon.
Friend that no decision has been taken on
the site of airport expansion in the south-east.
As she will know from her previous background,
the Davies commission said that airport capacity
in the south-east should be expanded and the
Government accepted that argument. The Davies
commission identified three sites, all of
which it said would be credible and deliverable,
and the Government will take a decision this
month.
>>Mr Speaker: It is fitting that we finish
with a question from Mr Gerald Jones.
>>Gerald Jones (Merthyr Tydfil and Rhymney)
(Lab): May I thank the Prime Minister, the
Leader of the Opposition and other Members
for their comments about the Aberfan disaster,
and about the resilience and quiet dignity
shown by the people of Aberfan? At 9.15 on
Friday morning—the anniversary of the disaster—the
people in that community and communities across
Wales will mark the disaster with a minute’s
silence. As the disaster affected communities
right across the country, if not the world,
will the Prime Minister support that minute’s
silence being marked across the UK as well?
>>The Prime Minister:
I know that the Secretary of State for Wales
will be attending the memorial that will take
place in the hon. Gentleman’s constituency
on Friday. It is appropriate that we all show
our respect for those who lost their lives
and for the families who suffered as a result
of the Aberfan tragedy 50 years ago. As we
said earlier, it was a terrible tragedy not
just for individual families, but for a whole
community, and it is right that we recognise
that and mark it.