>>Wendy Morton (Aldridge-Brownhills) (Con):
If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 16 November.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
am sure that the whole House will join me
in expressing our condolences to the families
and friends of the seven people who lost their
lives and those who were injured in the tragic
tram incident in Croydon last Wednesday. We
all thank those involved in the rescue operation.
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in this House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Wendy Morton: Will the Prime Minister join
me in welcoming today’s news that the unemployment
rate has fallen to an 11-year low? Will she
join me in thanking all those businesses that
create jobs, such as Jennifer Ashe &amp; Son,
whose funeral home on Brownhills High Street
in my constituency I was kindly asked to open
last weekend?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely agree with
my hon. Friend. I am pleased to say that in
the last year, employment in her constituency
of Aldridge-Brownhills has gone up by 88,000.
It is good to hear of companies that are providing
new jobs. The employment figures show the
strength of the fundamentals of our economy:
the employment rate has never been higher
and the unemployment rate is lower than it
has been in more than a decade. I am sure
that Members from all parts of the House will
welcome yesterday’s news that Google will
create another 3,000 jobs.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): I
concur with the remarks the Prime Minister
made about the disaster in Croydon last week.
We send our sympathies to all those who lost
loved ones and express our solidarity with
the emergency workers who went through such
trauma in freeing people from the wreckage.
It appears from press reports that the Chagos
islanders who were expelled from their homes
over 40 years ago will suffer another injustice
today with the denial of their right of return.
Yesterday, the Foreign Secretary told European
media that Brexit would “probably” mean
leaving the customs union. Will the Prime
Minister confirm whether that is the case?
>>The Prime Minister: I think the right hon.
Gentleman was trying to get two issues in
there. On the issue of the Chagos islanders,
there will be a written ministerial statement
to the House later today, so everybody will
be able to see the position the Government
are taking.
On the whole issue of the customs union and
the trading relationships we will have with
the European Union and other parts of the
world once we have left the European Union,
we are preparing carefully for the formal
negotiations, but—[Interruption.] We are
preparing carefully for the formal negotiations.
What we want to ensure is that we have the
best possible trading deal with the European
Union once we have left.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I asked the Prime Minister,
actually, about the Foreign Secretary’s
remarks about leaving the customs union. He
is only a few places down from her. Mr Speaker,
would it be in order for the Foreign Secretary
to come forward and tell us what he actually
said? I
am sure we would all be better informed if
he did.
Earlier this week, a leaked memo said
that the Government are
“considerably short of having a plan for
Brexit…No common strategy has emerged…in
part because of the divisions within the Cabinet.”
If this memo is, as the Prime Minister’s
press department says, written by ill-informed
consultants, will she put the Government’s
plan and common strategy for Brexit before
Parliament?
>>The Prime Minister: I have to say to the
right hon. Gentleman that, yes, we do have
a plan. Our plan is to deliver the best possible
deal in trading with and operating within
the European Union. Our plan is to deliver
control of the movement of people from the
European Union into the United Kingdom. Our
plan is to go out there across the world and
negotiate free trade agreements around the
rest of the world. This Government are absolutely
united in their determination to deliver on
the will of the British people and to deliver
Brexit. The right hon. Gentleman’s shadow
Cabinet cannot even decide whether it supports
Brexit.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Well, the word does not seem
to have travelled very far. I have to say,
I sympathise with the Italian Government Minister
who said this week, about the Prime Minister’s
Government:
“Somebody needs to tell us something, and
it needs to be something that makes sense.”
Is not the truth that the Government are making
a total shambles of Brexit, and nobody understands
what their strategy actually is?
>>The Prime Minister: Of course those in the
European Union whom we will be negotiating
with will want us to set out at this stage
every detail of our negotiating strategy.
If we were to do that, it would be the best
possible way of ensuring that we got the worst
result for this country. That is why we will
not do it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Talking of worst results,
the Foreign Secretary has been very helpful
this week, because he informed the world that
“Brexit means Brexit”—we did not know
that before—and that
“we are going to make a titanic success
of it.”
Taking back control, if that is what Brexit
is to mean—[Interruption.] The Prime Minister
is getting advice from the Foreign Secretary
now; can we all hear it? Taking back control
clearly requires some extra administration.
Deloitte has spoken, saying:
“One Department estimates it needs a 40%
increase in staff to cope with its Brexit
projects”,
and that overall expectations are of an increased
headcount of between 10,000 and 30,000 civil
servants. If that estimate is wrong, can the
Prime Minister tell the House exactly how
many extra civil servants will be required
to conduct these negotiations? Her Ministers
need to know—they are desperate for an answer
from her.
>>The Prime Minister: I repeat for the right
hon. Gentleman that we are doing the preparations
necessary for the point at which we will start
the complex formal negotiations with the European
Union. I have set up a Department for Exiting
the European Union, and my right hon. Friend
the Secretary of State is doing an excellent
job there in making those preparations.
I have to say to the right hon. Gentleman
that from the confusion that he has on his
Benches in relation to the issue of Brexit,
it seems to be yet another example from Labour
of how where they talk, we act. They posture,
we deliver. We are getting on with the job,
he is not up to the job.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Well, Mr Speaker—[Interruption.]
That was exciting, wasn’t it? Mr Speaker—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. There is far too much
noise in the Chamber. I say to the hon. Member
for Kingston and Surbiton (James Berry), calm
yourself, man. You should seek to imitate
the calm and repose of your right hon. and
learned Friend the Member for Rushcliffe (Mr
Clarke), who is setting an example for all
Members of the House.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I do not wish to promote
any further division on their Benches, Mr
Speaker.
These are the most complex set of negotiations
ever undertaken by this country. The civil
service has been cut down to its lowest level
since the second world war. The Prime Minister’s
main focus surely ought to be coming up with
a serious plan. May I ask her to clarify something?
If, when the Supreme Court meets at the beginning
of December, it decides to uphold the decision
of the High Court, will the Lord Chancellor
this time defend our independent judiciary
against any public attacks?
>>The Prime Minister: As the right hon. Gentleman
knows, there have been two cases in the UK
courts on the prerogative power and its use.
The Northern Ireland court found in favour
of the Government; the High Court found against
the Government. We are appealing to the Supreme
Court. We have a good argument, and will put
the case to the Supreme Court. I believe and
this Government believe in the independence
of our judiciary, and the judiciary will consider
that decision and come to their judgment on
the basis of the arguments put before them.
But we also believe that our democracy is
underpinned by the freedom of our press.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was on defending
the independence of the judiciary. We should
all be doing that. We have an International
Development Secretary who is opposed to overseas
aid, a Health Secretary who is running down
our national health service, a Chancellor
with no fiscal strategy, a Lord Chancellor
who seems to have difficulty defending the
judiciary, a Brexit team with no plan for
Brexit and, as has just been shown, a Prime
Minister who is not prepared to answer questions
on what the actual Brexit strategy is. We
need a better answer than she has given us.
>>The Prime Minister: I will tell the right
hon. Gentleman what we have got. We have an
International Development Secretary delivering
on this Government’s commitment to spend
0.7% of gross national income on international
development, a Health Secretary delivering
on £10 billion of extra funding for the health
service and a Chancellor of the Exchequer
making sure we have the stable economy that
creates the wealth necessary to pay for our
public services. And what we certainly have
got is a Leader of the Opposition who is incapable
of leading.
>>Mr John Baron (Basildon and Billericay)
(Con): The Prime Minister understands that
we are a one nation party or we are nothing,
something our political opponents consistently
underestimate, to their cost. In the autumn
statement next week will she continue to pursue
that agenda with all the resource and vigour
she can muster, including by increasing significantly
further the personal allowance, so that the
lower paid disproportionately benefit?
>>Fiona Mactaggart (Slough) (Lab): They do
the absolute opposite!
>>Mr Speaker: Order. It is always interesting
to hear the thoughts of the right hon. Member
for Slough (Fiona Mactaggart) but they should
not be articulated from a sedentary position
and will have to wait for another occasion.
>>The Prime Minister: Before I answer my hon.
Friend’s question, may I wish his wife all
the very best in the treatment she is going
through at the moment? The thoughts of the
House are with her.
My hon. Friend is right. We have a manifesto
commitment to increase the personal allowance.
By increasing it from £6,475 in 2010-11 to
£11,000 in 2016-17 and £11,500 next year,
we have cut income tax for more than 30 million
people and have taken 4 million people out
of paying income tax altogether. That is important.
It has helped people at the lower end of the
income scale.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): We join the
Prime Minister and the Leader of the Opposition
in extending our condolences following the
tragedy in Croydon and in paying tribute to
the emergency services.
The Institute for Government, which has close
ties to the civil service, has published a
report saying that the UK Government’s approach
towards Brexit is “chaotic and dysfunctional”,
that Brexit poses an “existential threat”
to operations in Whitehall Departments, that
the Prime Minister has a “secretive approach”
towards Brexit, and that the present situation
is “unsustainable”. Does the Prime Minister
plan to carry on like this regardless?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
will not be surprised when I tell him what
the Government are doing in relation to Brexit.
As I said earlier, the most important thing
for the Government to do is calmly and carefully
to get on with the job of preparing for complex
negotiations. One of the most important things
we can do is to make sure that we are not
giving a running commentary on those negotiations
and on our stance, because that would be the
best way to get the worst deal for this country.
>>Angus Robertson: On the day we hear that
“post-truth” has become the international
word of the year, we have a running commentary
from the Foreign Secretary. He is prepared
to tell the media in the Czech Republic that
the United Kingdom is likely to leave the
EU customs union post-Brexit, but that it
still wants to trade freely afterwards. In
response, his colleague from the Netherlands
said that that option “doesn’t exist”
and is “impossible”. Both those things
cannot be correct, so will the Prime Minister
confirm today, to Parliament and to the country,
whether the UK is likely to leave the EU customs
union post-Brexit—yes or no?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
does not actually seem to understand that
the customs union is not just a binary decision,
but let us set that to one side. Let us look
at what we need to do: get the best possible
deal for access to, trading with and operating
within the single European market. He stands
up time and again in Prime Minister’s questions
and says to me that he wants access to the
single European market. I might remind him
that it was only a couple of years ago that
he wanted to take Scotland out of the single
European market by making it independent.
[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. [Interruption.] Order.
Mr Docherty-Hughes, you are in a very emotional
condition. I normally regard you as a cerebral
denizen of the House. Try to recover your
composure, man!
>>James Duddridge (Rochford and Southend East)
(Con): In Southend, crimes such as burglary
and vehicle theft are down, but knife crime
is on the increase, particularly that perpetrated
by drug dealers and drug users. Can my right
hon. Friend confirm that this will be a priority
for Her Majesty’s Government? Specifically,
is there anything more that she can do to
help police and crime commissioners such as
Roger Hirst to deal with this very big challenge?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising an issue that is very important
for everybody in the House. Certainly the
Government will do all they can to support
police and crime commissioners such as Roger
Hirst, who is already doing an excellent job
in Essex. Since 2009, knife crime figures
have fallen overall, but I recognise my hon.
Friend’s concerns. That is why the Home
Office has been supporting police forces such
as Essex in conducting weeks of action against
knives under Operation Sceptre. We have legislated
to ban dangerous knives, including zombie
knives. We are putting tough sentences in
place and making sure that offenders are punished.
We should send a very clear message that we
will not tolerate knife crime in this country.
>>Tommy Sheppard (Edinburgh East) (SNP): Many
people in this country visit the United States
every year to study, on business, or simply
to enjoy one of the greatest countries on
earth. What action will the Prime Minister
take if the new President-elect carries through
his campaign promise to discriminate against
our citizens on the basis of their religion?
Will she give a commitment that the special
relationship which she believes her Government
have with the US presidency will be conducted
on the basis of respect for the dignity of
all our citizens, irrespective of their race
or religion?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to say to
the hon. Gentleman that our special relationship
with the United States is, I think, very important
to both the United States and the United Kingdom.
We will continue to build on it, as was clear
from the conversation that I had with President-elect
Trump shortly after his election, and of course
we want to ensure the dignity of our citizens.
It is up to the United States what rules it
puts in place for entry across its borders,
but we will ensure that the special relationship
continues, and does so in the interests of
both the UK and the US.
>>Andrea Jenkyns (Morley and Outwood) (Con):
Last Tuesday, I attended an infection prevention
and control summit that highlighted the great
work done by the Department of Health, the
NHS and other organisations dramatically to
decrease MRSA infection rates, yet also raised
the growing threat of E. coli and sepsis.
Will my right hon. Friend join me in commending
such events and outline the Government’s
strategy for combatting superbugs?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely join my
hon. Friend, who raises a very important issue,
in commending such events. It true that the
DOH, Public Health England and the NHS are
doing vital work to decrease infection rates.
We have already seen some very good results—a
57% reduction in MRSA bloodstream infections
since 2010 and a 47% reduction in C. diff
infections—but of course there is more to
do, which is why we are setting bold objectives
to halve gram-negative blood infections by
2020, and why last week we announced a new
national infection lead to champion and oversee
this effort. This is an important issue and
I am grateful to my hon. Friend for raising
it.
>>Mr Douglas Carswell (Clacton) (UKIP): Free
trade is vital to our future prosperity, and
Brexit does not mean rejecting globalisation.
Will the Prime Minister ensure that any new
trade deals with the wider world after Brexit
are based on the mutual recognition of standards,
not on the kind of over-elaborate, prescriptive,
top-down regulatory regime that underpins
the European single market?
>>The Prime Minister: I welcome the hon. Gentleman’s
support for free trade. He is absolutely right
that as we leave the EU we will be looking
for opportunities to develop flexible trading
relationships around the world that suit the
United Kingdom. Given the strength of our
economy, I believe that we can go out there
and be a global leader in free trade, and
I welcome his support for that.
>>Chris Philp (Croydon South) (Con): Last
Wednesday, seven people tragically died and
50 were injured in a tram accident in Croydon.
I am sure that the whole House will join the
Prime Minister, the Leader of the Opposition
and the leader of the SNP in extending our
heartfelt condolences to the bereaved families.
Three investigations—by British Transport
Police, the Office of Rail and Road, and the
Rail Accident Investigation Branch—are under
way. Will the Prime Minister assure the House
and the families that any recommendations
to improve safety on trams in Croydon and
across the country that are made by those
investigations will be rapidly implemented
by the Government?
>>The Prime Minister: I join my hon. Friend
in once again sending our condolences to the
families and friends of the seven people who
died in this terrible incident, in expressing
our sympathies for those injured and affected,
and in thanking our emergency services. It
is important that we allow these investigations
to continue and that they can come up with
recommendations in due course; we will, of
course, look very seriously at them. We can
never be complacent about safety and security
regarding such issues, so we need to make
sure that if there are lessons to be learned,
they are
indeed learned.