>>Peter Dowd (Bootle) (Lab): May I take the
opportunity to wish you, Mr Speaker, and all
Members of the House a merry Christmas and
a happy new year?
In the light of the Foreign Secretary’s
display of chronic “foot in mouth” disease,
when deciding on Cabinet positions, does the
Prime Minister now regret that pencilling
“FO” against his name should have been
an instruction, not a job offer?
>>Mr Speaker: Order. There is far too much
noise in the Chamber. We have heard the question,
but I want to hear the Prime Minister’s
answer.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
join the hon. Gentleman in wishing everybody
a happy Christmas. I will of course have an
opportunity to do that again on Monday, when
I am sure the House will be as full for the
statement on the European Council meeting.
[Hon. Members: “Hear, hear.] Funny, that
seemed to come from this side of the House
but not from the Labour side. I have to say
that the Foreign Secretary is doing an absolutely
excellent job. He is, in short, an FFS—a
fine Foreign Secretary.
>>Amanda Milling (Cannock Chase) (Con): Rugeley
has a really bright future ahead—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I want to hear the voice
of Cannock Chase.
>>Amanda Milling (Cannock Chase) (Con): Rugeley
has a really bright future ahead, but only
if we are ambitious, bold and visionary in
our redevelopment plans. Will my right hon.
Friend outline how the Government’s industrial
strategy can create the conditions that will
help us to build a sustainable local economy
and highly skilled jobs for future generations?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right that communities across this country
have a bright future ahead of them, but we
need to ensure that we create the conditions
for that future. That is why we will be producing
a modern industrial strategy that will show
how we can encourage the strategic strengths
of the United Kingdom and deal with our underlying
weaknesses. It will enable companies to grow,
invest in the UK and provide those jobs for
the future, but we also need to make sure
that that prosperity is spread across the
whole of the United Kingdom and is prosperity
for everyone.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): May
I start by wishing you, Mr Speaker, all Members
of the House and everyone who works in the
House a very happy Christmas and a prosperous
new year?
Sadly, our late colleague Jo Cox will not
be celebrating Christmas this year with her
family. She was murdered and taken from us,
so I hope the Prime Minister will join me—I
am sure she will—in encouraging people to
download the song, which many Members helped
to create, as a tribute to Jo’s life and
work and in everlasting memory of her.
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
is absolutely right to raise this issue. I
am sure that everybody in this House would
wish to send a very clear message: download
this single for the Jo Cox Foundation. It
is a very important cause. We all recognise
that Jo Cox was a fine Member of this House
and would have carried on contributing significantly
to this House and to this country, had she
not been brutally murdered. It is right that
the Chancellor has waived VAT on the single.
Everybody involved in it gave their services
for free, and I am having a photograph with
MP4 later this afternoon. Once again, let
us encourage everybody to download the single.
>>Mr Speaker: For the benefit of those observing
our proceedings from outside, I should state
that the Prime Minister was, of course, referring
to the outstanding parliamentary rock band
MP4.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I applaud the work of MP4,
but for the benefit of air quality I am not
a member of it! I thank the Prime Minister
for her answer.
Social care is crucial. It provides support
for people to live with dignity, yet Age UK
research has found that 1.2 million older
people are currently not receiving the care
they need. Will the Prime Minister accept
that there is a crisis in social care?
>>The Prime Minister: I have consistently
said in this House that we recognise the pressures
on social care, so it might be helpful if
I set out what the Government are doing and
the position in relation to social care. As
I say, we recognise those pressures. That
is why the Government are putting more money
into social care through the better care fund,
and by the end of this Parliament it will
be billions of pounds extra. That is why we
have enabled the social care precept for local
authorities. We recognise that there are immediate
pressures on social care. That is why this
will be addressed tomorrow by my right hon.
Friend the Secretary of State for Communities
and Local Government in the local government
finance settlement. We also recognise that
this is not just about money; it is about
delivery. There is a difference in delivery
across the country. We need to make sure that
reform is taking place, so we see best practice
in the integration of health and social care
across the country. We also need to ensure
that we have a longer-term solution to give
people reassurance for the future that there
is a sustainable system that will ensure that
they receive the social care they need in
old age. That is what the Government are working
on. There is a short-term issue; there is
medium-term need to make sure local authorities
and the health service are delivering consistently;
and there is a long-term solution that we
need to find.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Care Quality Commission
warned as recently as October that evidence
suggests we have approached a tipping point.
Instead of passing the buck on to local government,
should not the Government take responsibility
for the crisis themselves? Will the Prime
Minister take this opportunity to inform the
House exactly how much was cut from the social
care budget in the last Parliament?
>>The Prime Minister: We have been putting
more money into social care and health [Hon.
Members: “How much?”]. We have been putting
more money in and, as I say, we recognise
the pressures that exist. That is why we are
looking at the short-term pressures on social
care, but this cannot be looked at as simply
being an issue of money in the short term.
It is about delivery; it is about reform;
it is about the social care system working
with the health system. That is why this issue
is being addressed not just by the Secretary
of State for Communities and Local Government,
but by the Secretary of State for Health.
If we are going to give people the reassurance
they need in the longer term that their social
care needs will be met, we need to make it
clear that this is not just about looking
for a short-term solution. It is about finding
a way forward that can give us a sustainable
system of social care for the future.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Prime Minister does not
seem to be aware that £4.6 billion was cut
from the social care budget in the last Parliament.
Her talk about putting this on to local government
ought to be taken for what it is—a con.
Two per cent. of council tax is clearly a
nonsense; 95% of councils used the social
care precept, and it raised less than 3% of
the money they planned to spend on adult social
care. Billions seem to be available for tax
give-aways to corporations—not mentioned
in the autumn statement—and underfunding
has left many elderly people isolated and
in crisis because of the lack of Government
funding for social care.
>>The Prime Minister: Many councils around
the country have taken the benefit of the
social care precept and as a result have actually
seen more people being able to access social
care and more needs being met. Sadly, there
are some councils across the country—some
Labour councils—that have not taken that
opportunity and we see worse performance on
social care. The right hon. Gentleman once
again referred to money, so I remind him that
the then shadow Chancellor said at the last
election that if Labour was in government
there would be “not a penny more” for
local authorities. When recently asked about
spending more money on social care and where
the money would come from, Labour’s shadow
Health Secretary said:
“Well, we’re going to have to come up
with a plan for that”.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: This Government have cut
social care and the Prime Minister well knows
it, and she well knows the effects of that.
She also well knows that raising council tax
has different outcomes in different parts
of the country. If you raise the council tax
precept in Windsor and Maidenhead, you get
quite a lot of money. If you raise the council
tax precept in Liverpool or Newcastle, you
get a lot less. Is the Prime Minister saying
that frail, elderly, vulnerable people in
our big cities are less valuable than those
in wealthier parts of the country?
This is a crisis for many elderly people who
are living in a difficult situation, but it
is also a crisis for the national health service.
People in hospital cannot be discharged because
there is nowhere for them to go. I ask the
Prime Minister again: the crisis affects individuals,
families and the national health service,
so why does she not do something really bold:
cancel the corporation tax cut and put the
money into social care instead?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
referred to Newcastle council in his list.
I have to say that Newcastle City Council
is one of the councils that saw virtually
no delayed discharges in September, so elderly
people were not being held up in hospital
when they did not need or want to be. That
shows that it is possible for councils to
deliver on the ground. Councils such as Newcastle
and Torbay are doing that, but councils such
as Ealing are not using the social care precept
and the result is different. The difference
between the worst performing council in relation
to delayed discharges and the best is twentyfold.
That is not about the difference in funding;
it is about the difference in delivery.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Councils across the country
work hard to try to cope with a 40% cut in
their budgets, and the people paying the price
are those who are stuck in hospital who should
be allowed to go home and those who are not
getting the care and support they need. The
social care system is deep in crisis. The
crisis was made in Downing Street by this
Government. The former Chair of the Health
Committee, Stephen Dorrell, says that the
system is inadequately funded. The current
Chair of the Health Committee, the hon. Member
for Totnes (Dr Wollaston), said that
“this issue can’t be ducked any longer
because of the impact it is having not just
on vulnerable people, but also on the NHS.”
Why does the Prime Minister not listen to
local government, the King’s Fund, the NHS
Confederation and her own council leaders
and recognise that this social care crisis
forces people to give up work to care for
loved ones because there is no system to do
that? It makes people stay in hospital longer
than they should and leads people into a horrible,
isolated life when they should be cared for
by all of us through a properly funded social
care system. Get a grip and fund it properly,
please.
>>The Prime Minister: The issue of social
care has been ducked by Governments for too
long. That is why this Government will provide
a long-term sustainable system for social
care that gives people reassurance. The right
hon. Gentleman talks about Governments ducking
social care, so let us look at the 13 years
of Labour government. In 1997, they said in
their manifesto that they would sort it. They
had a royal commission in 1999, a Green Paper
in 2005 and the Wanless report in 2006. They
said they would sort it in the 2007 comprehensive
spending review. In 2009, they had another
Green Paper: 13 years and no action whatsoever.
>>Tim Loughton (East Worthing and Shoreham)
(Con): Today, a constituent of mine from Shoreham
will struggle to get to University College
hospital, London, for life-saving cancer drug
trials, and across Sussex thousands of others
will be unable to get to work, to school or
to college because ASLEF objects to their
drivers on Southern operating the doors. Yet
today, ASLEF drivers will be driving Thameslink
trains on the same rails, operating the doors
on the London to Brighton line. Can the Prime
Minister give her assurance that everything
will be done at the ACAS talks today to end
this nonsense of a strike, address any residual
safety issues and give our constituents their
lives back?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right to raise this issue. This is an appalling
strike and he is right to raise the discrepancy
in the attitude of ASLEF; we have seen driver-only
operated trains on rail networks in the UK
for decades and they are on Thameslink. I
hope that the talks at ACAS are going to lead
to an end to this strike, but I have a suggestion
for the Leader of the Opposition, as he could
do something to help members of the public.
The Labour party is funded by ASLEF. Why does
he not get on the phone and tell it to call
the strike off immediately?
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): We join the
leader of the Labour party and the Prime Minister
in wishing great success to the Jo Cox single,
which is available for download on Friday—I
am sure we are all going to download it.
Civilians have suffered grievously from the
bombing of hospitals, schools and markets.
The United Nations believes that 60% of civilian
casualties are caused by airstrikes. In the
past 24 hours, the United States has stopped
the supply of precision-guided munitions to
Saudi Arabia to bomb Yemen. When will the
UK follow suit?
>>The Prime Minister: As the right hon. Gentleman
knows, we have a very strict regime of export
licences in relation to weapons here in the
United Kingdom. We exercise that very carefully,
and in recent years we have indeed refused
export licences in relation to arms, including
to Yemen and Saudi Arabia.
>>Angus Robertson: The US Government have
just said that
“systematic, endemic problems in Saudi Arabia’s
targeting drove the US decision to halt a
future weapons sale involving precision-guided
munitions”.
The Saudis have UK-supplied precision-guided
Paveway IV missiles—they are made in Scotland.
The UK has licensed £3.3 billion-worth of
arms to Saudi Arabia since the beginning of
the bombing campaign. What will it take for
the UK to adopt an ethical foreign policy
when it comes to Yemen?
The Prime Minister
As the right hon. Gentleman knows, the intervention
in Yemen is a UN-backed intervention. As I
have said previously, where there are allegations
of breaches of international humanitarian
law, we require those to be properly investigated.
We do have a relationship with Saudi Arabia.
The security of the Gulf is important to us,
and I would simply also remind him that Saudi
intelligence—the counter-terrorism links
we have with Saudi Arabia and the intelligence
we get from Saudi Arabia—has saved potentially
hundreds of lives here in the UK.
>>Dr Sarah Wollaston (Totnes) (Con): One of
my constituents has just had to move to residential
care because no carers could be found to support
her in her own home. She is at the sharp end
of a crisis in social care that is as much
about inadequate funding as it is about a
shortfall in our very valued social care workforce.
I am looking forward to hearing what immediate
further support will be provided for social
care, but is it not time that rather than
having confrontational dialogues about social
care funding, all parties work together, across
this House, to look for a sustainable long-term
solution for the funding of both integrated
health and social care?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is right
to raise the issue of looking at a sustainable
way in which we can support integrated health
and social care, and a sustainable way for
people to know that in the future they are
going to be able to have the social care that
they require. As I said earlier in response
to the Leader of the Opposition, we recognise
the short-term pressures that there are on
the system, but it is important for us to
look at those medium-term and longer-term
solutions if we are going to be able to address
this issue. I was very pleased to be able
to have a meeting with my hon. Friend to discuss
this last week, and I look forward to further
such meetings.
>>Mark Durkan (Foyle) (SDLP): A cross-party
delegation led by the right hon. Member for
Cynon Valley (Ann Clwyd) will meet the Russian
ambassador tomorrow morning to discuss Aleppo.
We will reflect and amplify the sort of terms
that the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary
have used about Russia, the Assad regime and
Iran, not least because we want to protect
those who have heroically struggled to save
lives in that city and who will now be at
particular risk because of what they have
witnessed. Does the Prime Minister accept
that many of us believe that these messages
are more cogent when we are equally unequivocal
about the primacy of human rights and international
humanitarian law when we meet the Gulf states?
>>The Prime Minister: We do raise the issue
of human rights when we meet the Gulf states,
but the hon. Gentleman is absolutely right
in relation to the role that Russia is playing
in Syria. There is a very simple message for
President Putin. He has it within his own
hands to say to the Assad regime that enough
is enough in Aleppo. We need to ensure that
humanitarian aid is there for people and that
there is security for the people who have,
as the hon. Gentleman has said, been heroically
saving the lives of others. I am sure that
that is a message that he and others will
be giving to the Russian ambassador. It is
in President Putin’s hands; he can do it,
why does he not?
>>Victoria Prentis (Banbury) (Con): On the
same subject, will the Prime Minister join
me in thanking the many Members from all parts
of this House who sung for Syrians last night
in St Margaret’s, Westminster? Singing for
Syrians was created to pay the salaries of
the medical staff in Aleppo. Since our hospital
was bombed two weeks ago, we have been buying
prosthetic limbs with all our money. We have
a waiting list of 30,000 people. What can
we do to target our humanitarian aid to ensure
that it gets to the most vulnerable people
in Syria—the old, the very young, and people
who are too injured to move?
>>The Prime Minister: First of all, I absolutely
join my hon. Friend in congratulating everyone
who took part in Singing for Syrians. I am
sure the whole House welcomes the work that
that group is doing and the money that it
is raising and putting to extremely good use.
The House was struck when she mentioned the
number of people who are on the waiting list
for prosthetic limbs. Our humanitarian aid
support for Syria is the biggest such effort
that the UK has made. Of course we are giving
money to the refugees who have fled from Syria.
We are also working diplomatically to try
to reduce the suffering and to ensure that
the sort of aid and medical support that she
is talking gets through to the citizens of
Aleppo. We will continue to ensure that our
humanitarian aid is being put to good use—helping
those who are vulnerable and also helping
those who need the education and support to
be able, in due course, to rebuild Syria when
it is stable and secure.
>>Nick Smith (Blaenau Gwent) (Lab): Rip-off
interest rates on household goods are wrong.
Companies such as BrightHouse exploit families
who have no other way to furnish their homes.
Will the Prime Minister look at capping those
interest rates to help those who are just
about managing?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
an important issue. I recognise that there
are many people who are just about managing
and struggling to get by who find themselves
having to revert to support from companies
that do, sadly, charge the sort of interest
rates that he is talking about. Action has
been taken in relation to some of those activities
in the past, but I will look at the issue
that he raised.
>>Helen Whately (Faversham and Mid Kent) (Con):
Across the country, and particularly in Kent,
lorry fly-parking is a blight. It is antisocial
and dangerous. Will my right hon. Friend the
Prime Minister support my campaign for more
lorry parking spaces, more effective enforcement
and, ultimately, a ban on lorries parking
in unauthorised places?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the concern
that my hon. Friend has raised; it is one
that is shared by many Kent MPs who see this
problem only too closely in their own constituencies.
May I assure her that the Government share
the desire to ensure that we do not see this
fly-parking of lorries across Kent and that
we do provide suitable lorry parking facilities
in Kent? I know that the Under-Secretary of
State for Transport, my hon. Friend the Member
for Harrogate and Knaresborough (Andrew Jones),
is looking at this issue very carefully. I
recognise, from my time as Home Secretary,
the pressure that can be put on the roads,
villages and towns in Kent at particular times.
The Government are working on it, and we will
find a solution.
>>Ian Blackford (Ross, Skye and Lochaber)
(SNP): Now we know, courtesy of the Government’s
infrastructure watchdog, that mobile coverage
in the UK is worse than in Romania, will the
Prime Minister take steps to introduce a universal
service obligation? In the highlands it is
fairly typical to get the message, “No signal.”
It would often be better to use carrier pigeons.
Does the Prime Minister recognise that that
is not acceptable, and will she take responsibility?
It is time to connect the highlands to the
rest of the world.
>>The Prime Minister: I can assure the hon.
Gentleman that the issue of decent mobile
coverage does not only affect the highlands.
There are parts of England, Wales and Northern
Ireland that are also affected. The Government
have very strong commitments in relation to
this; we have very strong commitments in relation
to broadband. My right hon. Friend the Secretary
of State for Culture, Media and Sport will
deliver on those.
>>Anna Soubry (Broxtowe) (Con): Money cannot
compensate someone who has been accused of
a very serious criminal offence and who then
finds that the details are in the press along
with their name. Nothing, in truth, can restore
their reputation after it has been trashed
in those circumstances. In 2011, I tried to
change the law with a private Member’s Bill.
Today, Sir Bernard Hogan-Howe said that it
was time to introduce new legislation. Will
the Prime Minister agree at least to consider
changing the law so that everyone, with a
few exceptions, has the right to anonymity
if they are a suspect in criminal proceedings
until such time as they are charged?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the interest
that my right hon. Friend takes in this issue.
She will know that it has been debated on
a number of occasions in the House. The general
assumption is that someone should not be named
before the point of charge, but there is an
allowance for the police to be able to raise
someone’s name if it is a case where they
believe that doing so will perhaps help other
victims to come forward. This is of particular
concern in matters of sexual violence—rape,
for example—or where the police believe
that the naming of an individual will help
in the detection of the crime. This is a delicate
issue, and I recognise my right hon. Friend’s
concern. The College of Policing is looking
at it very carefully, and is due to provide
new guidance to the police in the new year
in relation to the media.
>>Lucy Powell (Manchester Central) (Lab/Co-op):
The heart-breaking humanitarian crisis and
genocide in Syria continue to take place as
the world watches impotently, yet there is
no end in sight. Does the Prime Minister agree
with the right hon. Member for Tatton (Mr
Osborne) that what is happening in Syria is
a failure of western leadership, and does
she agree with me that what is urgently required
is what our dear friend, Jo Cox, called for
nearly a year ago: a UK-led strategy to protect
civilians, whether they are fleeing persecution,
whether they are surrendering, or whether
they are still besieged?
>>The Prime Minister: We must all take responsibility
for decisions that we have taken, whether
we take them sitting around the National Security
Council table or, indeed, whether we take
them in the House, with the decision it took
in 2013. The hon. Lady raised the question
of UK-led action in relation to the protection
of civilians. The UK has been pressing for
action in the United Nations Security Council,
working with the French. The two most recent
emergency UN Security Council meetings were
called for by us, and the most recent took
place yesterday. As she will know, there have
been six UN Security Council resolutions which
have been vetoed by Russia. The most recent
was also vetoed by China. We continue to work
with the United Nations, but if we are to
get a solution that works on the ground other
countries have to buy into it, and it has
to be a solution that Russia buys into, as
well as the regime.
>>Robert Jenrick (Newark) (Con): I have received
a message from Nick from Grantham—actually,
it was a text message from our hon. Friend
the Member for Grantham and Stamford (Nick
Boles). For the avoidance of doubt, this is
one text message that he is willing to have
read out in public. Other than getting rid
of his tumour and making a swift return to
this place, nothing matters more to him than
ensuring that round-the-clock emergency services
are restored to his local hospital in Grantham.
Will my right hon. Friend receive the petition
that he has organised, ensure that the passionate
views of his constituents are heard, and above
all reassure people in that rural area that
they will always have access to safe emergency
care for them and their families?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure the thoughts
of the whole House are with our hon. Friend
the Member for Grantham and Stamford (Nick
Boles), and I wish him the very best for his
recovery as he goes through this illness.
I recognise the strength of feeling he has
about the emergency services in his local
hospital. I believe that those concerns are
shared by our new hon. Friend the Member for
Sleaford and North Hykeham (Dr Johnson). I
can assure my hon. Friend the Member for Grantham
and Stamford that the process that is taking
place, which is looking at the development
of local services, is about listening to local
people, hearing the local voice and, above
all, ensuring that the services available
to people in their local area are the right
services for that area and that they can be
delivered safely and securely for local people.
>>Justin Madders (Ellesmere Port and Neston)
(Lab): At the last election the Conservative
party manifesto said that“we will help local
authorities keep council tax low for hardworking
taxpayers, and ensure residents can continue
to veto high rises”.Band D council tax payers
in Ellesmere Port and Neston now face paying
an extra £125 a year, with no veto, because
of the Government’s failure to tackle the
social care crisis. Will the Prime Minister
now admit that her party’s pledge on council
tax has been abandoned?
>>The Prime Minister: Obviously we have put
the social care precept in place in recognition
of the pressures on social care, but I am
very pleased to say that we have seen many
examples over the country of good local authorities
ensuring that they are keeping council tax
down, including the Royal Borough of Windsor
and Maidenhead, which cut council tax for
six years running.
>>Gareth Johnson (Dartford) (Con): On 14 August
my constituents George Low and Ben Barker
were the victims of a vicious knife attack
in Ayia Napa. George Low, sadly, died later
that day from his injuries. The two culprits
fled to northern Cyprus, where they were arrested
on unrelated matters. Despite representations
made by the Foreign Office, one of those men
was recently able to walk free, and it is
feared that the second man will follow shortly.
Will the Prime Minister do all she can to
help to bring justice for George Low and Ben
Barker for what was an horrific, vicious attack
that was completely without provocation and
has been devastating for both their families?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure all of us
across the House send our deepest sympathies
to the family of George Low, and our very
best wishes to Ben Barker for a full recovery
from the terrible injuries that he suffered
as a result of what was, as my hon. Friend
said, a violent and completely unprovoked
attack. The case was raised most recently
with the relevant Government by the Foreign
Secretary during his visit to Cyprus on 30
November, and he set out clearly our desire
to see those guilty of this attack brought
to justice. The Foreign and Commonwealth Office
will continue to offer help and support to
both families. We will continue to raise this
issue, and I am sure the Foreign and Commonwealth
Office will keep my hon. Friend informed of
any developments.
>>Mike Weir (Angus) (SNP): The Arbroath smokie,
along with many other food and drink products,
has benefited greatly from the European Union’s
protected geographical indication scheme.
What guarantee can the Prime Minister give
us that it will continue to get that protection,
should we end up leaving
the EU?
>>The Prime Minister: We will need to address
such issues as we look at the arrangements
that will be in place following our exit from
the EU. I am sure everybody recognises the
significance of the Arbroath smokie and other
products from around the United Kingdom. At
the end of his question the hon. Gentleman
said “should we leave the EU”. I can tell
him that we will be leaving the EU.
>>Derek Thomas (St Ives) (Con): On 19 December
35 years ago, 16 people lost their lives in
ferocious storms off the coast of west Cornwall.
Eight of them were men from Mousehole, who
had launched the Penlee lifeboat, the Solomon
Browne, to rescue the crew of the Union Star.
Thirty-five years later, this tragedy still
haunts the village of Mousehole and West Penwith,
and many people mark the anniversary every
year. Will the Prime Minister join me in remembering
these brave men and the loved ones they left
behind, and pay credit to all our lifeboat
men and women, who are prepared to risk their
lives for those in peril on the sea?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising this issue. I absolutely join
him in marking the 35th anniversary of the
Penlee lifeboat tragedy and in sending our
sympathies to all those families who were
affected, but also to the local communities
who were affected, as he has set out. I am
sure everybody in this House would want to
pay tribute to the Royal National Lifeboat
Institution as well and the tireless work
it does. As an island, it is important that
we have that security and safety around our
shores. The RNLI works tirelessly to protect
people who, as he said, are in peril on the
sea, and we pay tribute to it.
>>Ms Gisela Stuart (Birmingham, Edgbaston)
(Lab): The Prime Minister knows that I and
colleagues from all parties on both sides
of the House are keen to guarantee the rights
of some 3 million EU and European economic
area citizens in this country at the earliest
possible date. This will be the largest administrative
task the Home Office has ever undertaken.
Could I encourage her to look at the report
produced by British Future, which has some
very practical suggestions on how the Home
Office can implement this, and could I possibly
even encourage the Home Secretary to update
us on any progress made?
>>The Prime Minister: I say to the hon. Lady
that I am keen to ensure that we can protect
the rights of EU citizens living here, but
I am also keen that the rights of UK citizens
who are living in the EU are protected as
well. The Home Secretary, I think, is aware
of the proposals that have been put forward
and is looking at them very carefully.
>>Lucy Frazer (South East Cambridgeshire)
(Con): In October, hundreds of people from
across Europe attended a neo-Nazi rally in
Haddenham, a small village in my rural constituency.
What steps is the Prime Minister taking to
tackle racial hatred?
>>The Prime Minister: First of all, can we
once again, from this House, send a very clear
message that there is no place for racial
hatred in our society? This is so important.
The Home Office has done a lot of work on
racial hatred and hate crime. It has published
a hate crime action plan, which shows what
we are going to be doing during the lifetime
of this Government. Of course, earlier this
week, my right hon. Friend the Home Secretary
proscribed the right-wing organisation National
Action, which means that being a member of,
or inviting support for, that organisation
will be a criminal offence. It is important
that we take every step we can to stop racial
hatred in this country, and I was pleased
to announce on Monday that Britain will be
the first country in Europe to adopt the International
Holocaust Remembrance Alliance’s definition
of anti-Semitism.
>>Naz Shah (Bradford West) (Lab): Yesterday,
I met the chief executive officer of Provident
Financial, one of two FTSE 100 companies in
Bradford—yes, outside London, right in the
heart of the north, Provident being in my
constituency. We agreed that for Bradford
to fulfil the potential of its young people,
we need to have better educational outcomes
and better transport. We have been overlooked
for too long, so can I invite the Prime Minister
to come to, and meet the leaders of, my great
city, and pave the way for long-overdue investment
for Bradford?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady is right
to raise the role that education plays in
ensuring the futures of young people in Bradford.
That is why I am pleased to say that there
has been an increase of nearly 16,000 children
in Bradford who have been at good or outstanding
schools since 2010. We are taking action to
ensure the quality of education, but I want
to make sure that there are enough good school
places for children across the whole country,
and that is what our education consultation
is about.
>>Heidi Allen (South Cambridgeshire) (Con):
I came to Prime Minister’s questions today
from an incredibly moving and powerful private
session with the Work and Pensions Committee,
where we talked and listened to victims of
modern slavery who are now living in safe
houses—I do not think I will ever forget
it in my life. Please will the Prime Minister
take her enthusiasm and the passion with which
she drove this issue as Home Secretary and
work with the Secretary of State for Work
and Pensions? These people are vulnerable.
When they come to the jobcentre, so often
their background and their cases are not understood.
As with survivors of domestic violence, they
need to be fast-tracked through the system.
If ever vulnerable people needed the state
to step up and support them, it is these people.
Please can we do more?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right. Nothing brings home the absolutely
horrific nature of the crime of modern slavery
than actually sitting down and hearing the
testimony of a victim. These people have,
very often, gone through the most horrendous,
dehumanising experiences. It is absolutely
right that the Government brought forward
the Modern Slavery Act 2015. It is right that
we have been looking at how victim support
is provided and at the national referral mechanism—a
whole number of steps—and of course we will
work with the DWP in looking at the support
that is given. She makes an important point
in referring to jobcentres, but of course
it is not just about jobcentres. One of the
things we need to do is to ensure that those
in authority who come into contact with people
who have been the victims of modern slavery
are able to recognise the signs, and able
to treat it in the right way and deal with
people sensitively and sympathetically in
an appropriate way.
>>Caroline Lucas (Brighton, Pavilion) (Green):
I do not think the Prime Minister has any
idea of the level of pain that rail passengers
and businesses in Brighton and beyond are
suffering. It is not just on strike days;
this has been going on for well over 18 months.
Given the failure of her passive Transport
Secretary, who apparently has no intention
of acting to deal with this utterly incompetent
company, will she sack him, strip GTR of the
franchise, and freeze fares for long-suffering
passengers?
>>The Prime Minister: First of all, my right
hon. Friend the Transport Secretary has been
taking steps in relation to the general performance
of Southern railway. We have stepped in to
invest £20 million specifically to tackle
the issue and bring a rapid improvement in
services. We announced Delay Repay 15 from
11 December for the whole of Southern railway,
which will make it easier for passengers to
claim compensation. We have announced that
we will give passengers who are season ticket
holders on Southern a refund for a month’s
travel. We have been looking at the wider
issue. The hon. Lady raises the question of
the current strike. There is only one body
responsible for the current strike, and that
is ASLEF. This a strike by the trade unions,
and she should be standing up and condemning
that strike, because it is passengers who
suffer.
>>Sir Hugo Swire (East Devon) (Con): The £1.5
billion of additional funding for the better
care fund is both needed and welcome, but
the problem is that this money is not available
until 2019. Will my right hon. Friend therefore
look at seeing whether some of this funding
can be drawn down earlier than that in order
to alleviate the pressure on social care in
areas such as Devon, where there is a very
high level of elderly people?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
raises an important point about the short-term
pressures on social care. That is why the
Government have been looking at what measures
can be taken to alleviate those short-term
pressures. As I say, my right hon. Friend
the Communities Secretary will be making a
statement on the local government finance
settlement tomorrow, but we do need to look
at the medium-term issues of delivery and
the longer-term reassurance that we can provide
to people in ensuring that we have a sustainable
system of social care that gives people the
comfort of knowing that they will be cared
for in their old age.
>>Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
May I join colleagues who urged people in
this House and beyond to go out and buy the
Jo Cox Foundation single by the excellent
MP4, which is not just available on download
but in hard copy for those of us who prefer
that kind of thing?
Every day since the Brexit result on 23 June
seems to have been a good day to bury bad
news, and the worst news is in our social
care and health system: the daily wave of
tragedies, indignities and near misses; the
£2.5 billion shortfall in social care funding;
and thousands of operations already cancelled.
Yesterday the Secretary of State for Health
said that the NHS and social care needed more
money, yet the Chancellor of the Exchequer
did not offer a single extra penny for health
or social care in the autumn statement. Which
of the two does the Prime Minister agree with?
Will she take this opportunity to provide
health and social care with the money it needs
this side of Christmas?
>>The Prime Minister: The Secretary of State
for Communities and Local Government will
be making a statement tomorrow on the local
government finance settlement. I suggest that
the hon. Gentleman waits for that statement.
>>Philip Davies (Shipley) (Con): Back in 2010,
the overseas aid budget was around £7 billion
a year. By 2020, it will have more than doubled
to over £15 billion a year. The shortfall
in social care funding by 2020 is estimated
at about £2.5 billion a year. Surely the
Government priority should be to look after
the elderly, vulnerable and disabled people
in our own country before we hand money over
to other countries. Will the Prime Minister
take some of that money—a small amount of
that increase—from the overseas aid budget
and spend it on elderly, vulnerable and disabled
people in our own country? Surely charity
begins at home.
>>The Prime Minister: I think it is absolutely
right that the Government are taking steps
on the pressures on social care here in the
United Kingdom, but it is also important for
us that we take into consideration those who
are in different circumstances across the
world. This Government’s record of ensuring
that 0.7% of our GDP is spent on overseas
aid is a record second to none. We should
all be proud of the help and support that
we are giving to people around the world who,
often, are living in incredibly difficult
circumstances. We look after old people here
in the UK; we also take seriously that moral
responsibility for people around the world.