>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): This
morning I had meetings with ministerial colleagues
and others. In addition to my duties in this
House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Peter Grant (Glenrothes) (SNP): “Bairns
come first” is the title of a report recently
produced by a number of organisations, including
Fife Gingerbread and Citizens Advice and Rights
Fife. It found that a third of families who
should have been claiming child maintenance
support did not apply, that a major barrier
to applying was the £20 application fee,
and that the 4% collection fee had a serious
impact on family budgets. Will the Prime Minister
undertake to review those unfair charges?
>>The Prime Minister: Trying to ensure that
those responsible for children actually pay
for their children when a family has broken
up has been a long-standing question which
this House has addressed. There have been
various ways of dealing with it through the
agency that has been responsible. It is right
that the changes that have been introduced
are on a more level basis and more people
are able to access the support they need as
a result.
>>Daniel Kawczynski (Shrewsbury and Atcham)
(Con): The Government have rightly focused
on economic growth, jobs and prosperity—something
all of us on the Conservative Benches can
get behind. With that in mind, will the Prime
Minister back our highly competitive bid for
funding for the north-west relief road in
Shrewsbury, which will not only deal with
the congestion our town is facing but dovetail
into that narrative?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising that. I know that the issue of
the north-west relief road in Shrewsbury has
been of particular concern to him; it is a
priority for him and it has received considerable
local backing. I understand that the local
Marches LEP has put in a bid for feasibility
funding so that it can prepare a business
case for the scheme. What I can say at the
moment is that the announcement of the successful
bids for feasibility funding is expected very
shortly indeed.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): The
Government’s sustainability and transformation
plans for the national health service hide
£22 billion of cuts to our service, according
to research by the British Medical Association.
That risks
“starving services of resources and patients
of vital care.”
That quote comes from Dr Mark Porter of the
BMA. When he calls this process “a mess”,
where is he wrong?
>>The Prime Minister: The national health
service is indeed looking for savings within
the NHS which will be reinvested in the NHS,
and I remind the right hon. Gentleman that
it is this Government who are providing not
just the £8 billion of extra funding that
the NHS requested, but £10 billion of extra
funding. Sustainability and transformation
plans are being developed at local level in
the interests of local people by local clinicians.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: It is very strange that the
Prime Minister should say that, because the
Select Committee on Health, chaired by her
hon. Friend the Member for Totnes (Dr Wollaston),
says that the figure is actually £4.5 billion,
not £10 billion; there is quite a big difference
there.
Part of the reason for the strain on our national
health service is that more than 1 million
people are not receiving the social care they
need. As a result of that, there has been
an increase in emergency admissions for older
patients. Margaret wrote to me this week—[Interruption.]
It is not funny. She described how her 89-year-old
mother suffered two falls leading to hospital
admissions due to the lack of nursing care,
and went on to say,
“My mother is worth more than this.”
What action will the Prime Minister take to
stop the neglect of older people, which ends
up forcing them into A&amp;E admissions when
they should be cared for at home or in a care
home?
>>The Prime Minister: Of course social care
is an area of concern, and it is a key issue
for many people. That is why the Government
have introduced the better care fund and the
social care precept for local authorities,
and why we are encouraging the health service
and local authorities to work together to
deal with precisely the social care and bed
blocking issues that the right hon. Gentleman
has raised.
We have introduced the better care fund and
the social care precept, but let us just look
at what the Labour Government did in their
13 years. They said that they would deal with
social care in their 1997 manifesto. They
introduced a royal commission in 1999, a Green
Paper in 2005 and the Wanless review in 2006.
They said they would sort it in the comprehensive
spending review of 2007, and produced another
Green Paper in 2009. Thirteen years, and they
did nothing.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: As the Prime Minister well
knows, health spending trebled under the last
Labour Government and the levels of satisfaction
with the health service were at their highest
ever in 2010. This Government’s choice was
to cut social care by £4.6 billion in the
last Parliament, at the same time as they
found the space, shall we say, to cut billions
from corporate taxation bills. This is affecting
patients leaving hospital as well. In the
last four years, the number of patients unable
to be transferred from hospital due to the
lack of adequate social care has increased
by one third. Will the Prime Minister ensure
that her Government will guarantee all our
elderly people the dignity they deserve?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the importance
of caring for elderly people and providing
them with the dignity they deserve. The right
hon. Gentleman says that this Government have
done nothing on social care, but I repeat
that we have introduced the social care precept,
which is being made use of by my local authorities
and by his local authority. We have also introduced
the better care fund. He talks about support
for elderly people, but let me remind him
which Government it was who put in place the
triple lock for pensioners. That has ensured
the largest increase in pensions for elderly
people.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The precept is a drop in
the ocean compared with what is necessary
for social care. I shall give Members an example.
I am sure the whole House will have been appalled
by the revelations in the BBC’s “Panorama”
programme this week. They showed older people
being systematically mistreated. The Care
Quality Commission’s assessment is that
the care homes run by the Morleigh Group “require
improvement”, and it has issued warning
notices. The commission goes on to say that
the owner
“has allowed the services to deteriorate
even further. She has utterly neglected her
duty of care to the residents of these homes.”
What action are the Government going to take
to protect the residents of those homes?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
raises the issue of the quality of care that
is provided in homes and the way in which
elderly people are treated. I am sure everybody
is appalled when we see examples of poor and
terrible treatment being given to elderly
and vulnerable people in care homes. What
we do about it is ensure that the Care Quality
Commission is able to step in and take action
and that it has powers to ensure that nobody
in the chain of responsibility is immune from
legal accountability. We know that there is
more that can be done, and that is why the
CQC is looking into ways of improving its
processes and increasing its efficiency. The
Under-Secretary of State for Health, my hon.
Friend the Member for Warrington South (David
Mowat), the Minister for community health
and care, will be writing to the CQC shortly
to see how we can improve what it does. It
is the CQC that deals with these issues, and
we have that in place. Is there more we can
do? Yes, and we are doing it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The problem seems to be that
that home was understaffed. We should not
blame often underpaid and hard-pressed care
workers; we should be ensuring that there
are enough of them—properly paid—in all
such homes. There was a serious problem of
understaffing, and it was the last Labour
Government who established the CQC. A warning
notice is insufficient—we need stronger
action than that.
Yesterday, the Government proposed that patients
may have to show passports or other ID to
access non-emergency healthcare. Have the
Government considered the impact on elderly
people? The last census showed us that 9.5
million people in this country do not have
passports. Instead of distracting people with
divisive, impractical policies, could the
Prime Minister provide the NHS and social
care with the money that it needs to care
for the people who need the support?
>>The Prime Minister: Over this Parliament,
the Government will be spending half a trillion
pounds on the national health service. The
right hon. Gentleman asks about a process
to ensure that people who are receiving NHS
treatment are entitled to receive that NHS
treatment. For many years, there has been
concern about health tourism and about people
turning up in the UK and accessing health
services but not paying for them. We want
to ensure not only that those who are entitled
to use the services are indeed able to see
them free at the point of delivery, but that
we deal with health tourism and those who
should be paying for the use of our health
service.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Simon Stevens told us two
weeks ago that the next three years will be
the toughest ever for NHS funding and that
2018 would see health spending per person
cut for the first time ever in this country.
The National Audit Office has reported that
the cost of health tourism is over a hundred
times less than the £22 billion of cuts that
the NHS faces from this Government. The reality
is that under this Government there are 6,000
fewer mental health nurses and a record 3.9
million people on NHS waiting lists. All of
us who visit A&amp;E departments know the
stress that staff are under and that waiting
times are getting longer and longer. One million
people in this country are not receiving the
social care that they need. Instead of looking
for excuses and scapegoats, should not the
Prime Minister be ensuring that health and
social care is properly resourced and properly
funded, to take away the stress and fear that
people face in old age and the stress that
is placed on our very hard-working NHS and
social care staff?
>>The Prime Minister: Billions of pounds extra
into social care through the social care precept
and the better care fund; half a trillion
pounds being spent on the national health
service; a record level of investment in mental
health in the national health service—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. Members must not shout
down or attempt to shout down the Prime Minister.
The question has been asked and was heard,
and the answer must be heard.
>>The Prime Minister: There is a fundamental
point that the right hon. Gentleman refrains
from mentioning: we can afford to pay for
the national health service and for social
care only if we have a strong economy creating
wealth, and that is precisely what he is going
to hear from the Chancellor of the Exchequer
in a few minutes’ time.
>>Gordon Henderson (Sittingbourne and Sheppey)
(Con): On 23 June, my constituents voted by
a margin of 62% to 28% to leave the European
Union. Many of those people are unhappy and
frustrated by what they see as delaying tactics
from some remainers, who do not seem to understand
the meaning of the word “democracy”—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. This is very discourteous.
The hon. Gentleman has a legitimate question
and it and every other question should be
heard fully and with politeness.
>>Gordon Henderson: Thank you, Mr Speaker—and
I will repeat it. Some remainers do not seem
to understand the meaning of the word “democracy”,
which I would remind them is government by
the people, especially the rule of the majority.
With that in mind, what reassurance can my
right hon. Friend give my constituents and
me that article 50 will be triggered by March
next year?
>>The Prime Minister: I am clear that we will
trigger article 50 by the end of March next
year. My hon. Friend is absolutely right to
make the key point: it was decided by this
Parliament, six to one, that the people should
have the opportunity to vote on membership
of the European Union. The vote was held,
the turnout was high and the public gave their
verdict. There must be no second referendum
and no attempt to weasel out of this, and
this is the Government who will deliver on
the vote of the British people.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): We on the
Scottish National party Benches have repeatedly
brought up the issue of the devastating impact
on disabled people of the UK benefits system.
The Government plan to cut support for people
with long-term health difficulties by £30
a week. Last week, my hon. Friend the Member
for Airdrie and Shotts (Neil Gray) proposed
a motion, which was passed by this House with
support from both Labour and Conservative
Members, for these cuts to be postponed. Will
the Prime Minister act on the vote of this
House?
>>The Prime Minister: Let me tell the right
hon. Gentleman what we have been doing in
relation to benefits for disabled people:
the overall funding for disability benefits
will be higher in every year up to 2020 than
it was in 2010; we have been focusing support
on those who most need it—those who are
not able to get into the workplace; and for
those who are able, at some stage, to get
into the workplace, we have been providing
a wider package of support. I am pleased to
say that over the last three years nearly
600,000 more disabled people are now in the
workplace, with the dignity of having a job,
which is what many people with disabilities
want to have. So we are focusing help on those
who most need it and helping those with disabilities
who want to get into the workplace to do just
that.
>>Angus Robertson: But it is widely trailed
that the Prime Minister will make changes
that will impact on benefit recipients in
work. Will she confirm that she has no intention
of helping people with disabilities and medical
conditions? Why should people who are unable
to earn a living be punished for their disability
or illness by losing £30 a week? Does she
have any intention of changing that?
>>The Prime Minister: I have just set out
for the right hon. Gentleman the ways in which
we are providing support and help for those
people who have disabilities. As I said, the
overall spending on disability benefits will
be higher in every year to 2020 than it was
in 2010. But it is also important to recognise
that when we give support for people with
disabilities, it is not simply about the benefits
system and how much money they are given;
for those who are able to get into work and
are on that part of the employment and support
allowance, we provide packages that are outside
the benefits as well, because we recognise
that people want the dignity of getting into
the workplace. That is what we are helping
people with disabilities who can work to do.
>>Sir Simon Burns (Chelmsford) (Con): Does
my right hon. Friend agree that thousands
of road commuters, including many of my constituents
who use the A12, are travelling on roads that
need to be repaired and upgraded? To improve
connectivity and to speed up daily commute
times, does she accept that the proposed £1.3
billion investment in improving our road network
is warmly welcome and will do a great deal
to enhance connectivity in the country?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
is absolutely right about the importance of
infrastructure expenditure in helping to deal
with productivity in our economy, and I am
pleased that that £1.3 billion for new roads
does show us investing in the long-term future
for Britain. It is about delivering jobs and
economic growth, and about making sure that
this economy works for everyone. It is just
one part of the package that we are proposing,
but of course my right hon. Friend the Chancellor
will be setting our proposals out more clearly
in a few minutes’ time.
>>Tulip Siddiq (Hampstead and Kilburn) (Lab):
My constituent Nazanin Ratcliffe, a British
national, is in prison in Iran. She has been
separated from her husband and her two-year-old
daughter for eight months. She has been on
hunger strike and is now suicidal. The Prime
Minister needs to reunite this mother, this
daughter and this wife with her family. Will
it take Nazanin’s death for the Government
to start taking her seriously?
>>The Prime Minister: Obviously, this is a
very difficult time for the whole family.
I am sure that we are all concerned about
the reports of the impact that detention in
Iran is having on Nazanin Ratcliffe’s health.
This is an issue that has repeatedly been
raised with the Iranian Government by the
UK Government—by both the previous Foreign
Secretary and the current Foreign Secretary.
I personally raised it with President Rouhani
on 20 September in New York, and I stressed
the importance of finding a resolution as
soon as possible. I have since written to
President Rouhani requesting confirmation
of the charges, the sentence and the appeals
process, and I have asked for assurances that
Mrs Zaghari-Ratcliffe will be allowed full
legal representation and regular contact with
her family. We will continue to do everything
that we can for the family and that includes
the British Government remaining ready to
help to bring back Mrs Zaghari-Ratcliffe’s
daughter to Britain if that is the request.
>>Mr Peter Lilley (Hitchin and Harpenden)
(Con): Does my right hon. Friend agree that
most of our social problems are either caused
or aggravated by the acute shortage of housing,
so even if we manage to reduce the net immigration
to this country, as I hope we will, we will
have to build far more new homes? Is not the
recommendation by the European Banking Authority
to increase by 50% the reserves that banks
must hold against house building, which makes
it even more costly for them to lend for housing
than for unsecured credit cards, profoundly
unhelpful and perverse?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure my right hon.
Friend will recognise that we are subject
to our own Prudential Regulation Authority,
but the overall point that he makes about
the importance of house building is absolutely
correct. We do need to build more homes. That
is something that the Government have been
doing. We have seen something like 900,000
new homes being built since 2010, but there
is more for us to do, and that is what this
Government are working on.
>>Angela Smith (Penistone and Stocksbridge)
(Lab): The Brexit Secretary and the Foreign
Secretary are described by a senior German
politician as having no idea what Brexit really
means. The Times reports today that EU ambassadors
think that the Foreign Secretary’s more
colourful outbursts are damaging our relationships
with member states. When will the Prime Minister
get a grip on her Ministers and demonstrate
to the country and to our EU colleagues that
she has a coherent, workable plan for Brexit?
>>The Prime Minister: I have been very clear
in this House on many occasions about the
plan that we have for Brexit. Crucially, we
will be leaving the European Union and we
will be triggering article 50 by the end of
March next year, and that is when the formal
negotiations will start. It is absolutely
right that we do not set out at this stage
every single detail of our proposed negotiating
strategy, because that would be the best way
to get the worst possible deal for Britain.
>>Mrs Cheryl Gillan (Chesham and Amersham)
(Con): As we leave the European Union, maintaining
the UK’s cutting edge and world leadership
in scientific and technological discovery
is of paramount importance to our industries
and universities. May I welcome the Prime
Minister’s announcement that, each year,
we will invest a further £2 billion in research
and development to boost our science and engineering
base? Is not this just the type of vital support
that our businesses and researchers need,
rather than the threats from the Labour party
to slash the R and D tax credits, which would
hamper innovation and harm our economy?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
is absolutely right. The extra investment
that we will be putting into research and
development is a crucial part of our long-term
task of ensuring that we have the economy
and the growth and prosperity that we need
in this country. The new funds will help to
put us at the cutting edge of scientific discovery.
That is already happening. I visited the Wellcome
Genome Campus in Cambridge on Monday and saw
for myself the really exciting and transformational
work that is being done, and it is coming
out of the knowledge base and the scientific
research of the United Kingdom. We want to
see more of that, which is why we will be
investing in it.
>>John Woodcock (Barrow and Furness) (Lab/Co-op):
Aleppo’s hospitals are destroyed and Syrians
who avoid the barrel bombs and the chlorine
gas are starving from the Russian-backed blockade.
We must do more. Will the Prime Minister revisit
the prospect for aid drops, and will she look
at backing the campaign to stop this daily
perpetrator of war crimes by stripping it
of its right to hold the 2018 World cup?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman is
right to raise the issue of the appalling
atrocities that are taking place in Aleppo,
and it is right that we, along with our international
allies, should be doing all that we can to
try to bring this to a stop. He will recognise
that the issue of who hosts sporting events
is not in the Government’s remit. What is
in the Government’s remit and what we are
doing, as I say, is working with our international
allies to put more pressure on Russia to stop
the appalling atrocities—the appalling attacks—that
are taking place in Aleppo. What we want to
see is an agreement for a political transition
to a Syria without President Assad.
>>Mr John Whittingdale (Maldon) (Con): Does
my right hon. Friend agree that if the UK
is to remain competitive and our citizens
are to enjoy the benefits of the digital revolution,
it is essential that we should be at the forefront
of the deployment of both ultra-fast broadband
and 5G mobile connectivity? May I therefore
welcome the announcement, which we are led
to believe may be made shortly, of a £1 billion
investment to achieve this?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
will, of course, be waiting in anticipation
for my right hon. Friend the Chancellor’s
autumn statement, but he is absolutely right
that, as we look at improving productivity
in this country and as we look to the economy
of the future, the provision of superfast
broadband and those new technological opportunities
for people is absolutely a crucial part of
that, and that is something that this Government
recognise and will act on.
>>Holly Lynch (Halifax) (Lab): One day last
week, four police officers in my constituency
were assaulted over a single 24-hour period.
There were over 23,000 assaults on police
officers last year, and an assault on a police
officer is an assault on society. What will
the Prime Minister do to ensure that the toughest
deterrents are in place to protect front-line
officers, and when will she reduce the need
for unsafe single crewing by restoring the
number of police on our streets?
>>The Prime Minister: May I send our best
wishes to those police officers who were assaulted
in the hon. Lady’s constituency last week?
It is important that we recognise that when
police officers go out on duty—and, indeed,
for many off duty—they sometimes find themselves
intervening in situations where they are on
the receiving end of assaults and violence
against them. They are willing to go forward
in the line of duty, where others are not,
and we recognise that. One of the things we
want to do in relation to this is to identify
rather better the number of assaults that
are taking place. That is why last year we
issued some provisional figures. We are improving
those figures now this year. Sentencing guidelines
already allow for an assault on a police officer
to be taken as an aggravating factor into
account, but also new developments, like the
body-worn videos, actually help to provide
the evidence that ensures that people can
be brought to justice and that actually deter
assaults in the first place.
>>Dr Andrew Murrison (South West Wiltshire)
(Con): I know that the Prime Minister shares
my concern at the level of acute hospital
bed blocking. Does she agree that part of
the solution is to promote community hospital
beds, where they still exist in places such
as Warminster and Shaftesbury, as part of
the sustainability and transformation planning
process?
>>The Prime Minister: As regards the STP process,
of course, that will take place at local level—it
will be at the local level that these proposals
will be considered and put forward by local
clinicians—but the concept of being able
to deal with bed blocking in a variety of
ways is absolutely right. There are good examples
around the country of where having those step-down
beds available is actually resolving the problem
of bed blocking. There are other ways in which
that is being done—in those parts of the
country where social workers are being employed
by hospital trusts, for example. But is it
very good to recognise the good practice when
it is being done, and we shall see more of
that across the country.
>>Tom Elliott (Fermanagh and South Tyrone)
(UUP): Earlier this month, IRA man turned
lawyer, Kieran Conway, confessed to the BBC
that he took part in robberies, bombings and
gun attacks that murdered British soldiers.
He stated that he will never disclose information
on any fellow IRA man, despite knowing details
of IRA actions that he defines as constituting
war crimes. Can the Prime Minister assure
me that Her Majesty’s Government will apply
for the extradition of this terrorist for
questioning from the Republic of Ireland?
>>The Prime Minister: The question of whether
or not an individual would be extradited or
a request would be made for extradition is
for the appropriate investigation and prosecution
authorities to decide. We do, of course, recognise
the concerns about those cases where it is
still possible to bring people to justice,
and obviously we want to see that being done.
>>John Stevenson (Carlisle) (Con): During
the past six years we have had three major
referendums, all eliciting varying degrees
of excitement. Does the Prime Minister agree
that one can have too much excitement, and
will she therefore rule out any further referendums
in this Parliament?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is trying
to tempt me down a particular route. One thing
that I will certainly rule out is a second
referendum on whether we leave the European
Union.
>>Kirsty Blackman (Aberdeen North) (SNP):
Aberdeen Cyrenians have launched a financial
appeal because of the increasing number of
people finding themselves homeless as a direct
result of the UK Government’s pursuit of
austerity. How can the Prime Minister sleep
in her warm bed at night knowing that her
Government’s policies have consigned people
to a cold Christmas?
>>The Prime Minister: The
Government are taking action in a variety
of ways to address homelessness. One of the
key things we need to do is ensure that we
see more homes being built in this country.
The hon. Lady talks about austerity in the
tone that she uses, but austerity is about
us living within our means. When we talk about
the Government providing support for individuals,
we should always remember that taxpayers have
to pay for that support, and many taxpayers
are themselves struggling to get by.
>>Kevin Foster (Torbay) (Con): The Prime Minister
will be aware that yesterday the Peninsula
Rail Task Force launched its report, which
was commissioned following the storms that
severed Devon and Cornwall’s vital rail
link, just as our vital rail link was severed
again, this time by flooding. Does she welcome
the report and will she commit the Government
to ensuring that the vision it outlines is
delivered?
>>The Prime Minister: May I suggest that my
hon. Friend exercises a little more patience
and listens very carefully to what my right
hon. Friend the Chancellor has to say?
>>Wayne David (Caerphilly) (Lab): In these
uncertain times we would all surely agree
that Britain needs strong defence, so how
can the Prime Minister justify her Government’s
decision to scrap all the Navy’s heavyweight
surface-to-surface guided missiles without
any replacement?
>>The Prime Minister: I do not recognise the
picture that the hon. Gentleman presents of
what the Government are doing in relation
to the armed forces. We are investing billions
of pounds in ensuring that our armed forces
do have the missiles, the ships for the Royal
Navy and the other pieces of equipment for
the other armed forces. The picture that he
presents is not the picture I recognise.
>>Mr Julian Brazier (Canterbury) (Con): Does
my right hon. Friend agree that it would be
good for confidence in the rule of law if
judges did not enter into speculative public
thoughts on cases that they are about to hear?
>>The Prime Minister: In this country we value
the independence of our judiciary—that is,
the independence of members of the judiciary
when they come to make their judgments in
court. Also, they are independent and it is
for them to determine what they choose to
put in their speeches. It is not for the Government
to tell them what to do.
>>Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
As millions of public sector workers face
another year of suppressed pay, after another
week of shambolic Brexit negotiations, and
with the national health service facing a
winter crisis and crying out for cash, does
the Prime Minister worry that her Government
are only just about managing?
>>The Prime Minister: We are very clear about
the amounts of money that we are putting into
the national health service. The hon. Gentleman
talks about the negotiations. Actually, the
negotiations for us leaving the European Union
do not formally start until we trigger article
50. We will trigger article 50 by the end
of March next year. The hon. Gentleman wants
to stop us leaving the European Union by denying
the people the decision and the deliverability
of the vote that they took, rightly, on 23
June. He wants to deny people what they want;
we are going to give it to them.
>>Charlie Elphicke (Dover) (Con): May I raise
with the Prime Minister the concerns of millions
of drivers and hauliers across the United
Kingdom who worry about the cost of driving
and fuel duty? Will the Government look at
keeping that down? Will they also look at
how forecourt pricing has worked as the oil
price changes? The prices jump like a rocket
and fall like a feather.
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise that, as
my hon. Friend says, many people look with
very great concern at the cost of motoring
in this country. I suggest, as I have to some
of my other hon. Friends, that he should be
a little more patient and wait for the Chancellor’s
autumn statement.
>>Ms Angela Eagle (Wallasey) (Lab): The Prime
Minister has talked about her worries about
social care, but surely we have to judge her
by her actions. In the last six years there
has been an average 37% cut in local authority
funding—57% in my area—and nearly a quarter
of all those older people in need of social
care have been denied any help at all. What
is she going to do about it?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady might
have noticed that I have been asked several
questions about social care—[Interruption]—and
I
will give the answer that I have given previously.
What the Government are doing about social
care is to put more money in through the better
care fund, to give local authorities the opportunity
that is in the social care precept and to
make sure that health and social care come
together to ensure that we deal with the issue
of bed blocking.
>>Richard Drax (South Dorset) (Con): How many
of us would charge into a darkened store at
night knowing that inside were three mask-wearing,
crowbar-wielding thugs trying to rob it? My
two constituents, Nigel Dunmore and Grant
McGarry, did just that; as a result of their
intervention, the thugs fled, leaving the
money, and the staff were hurt less, although
one of the gentlemen was himself hurt. Will
my right hon. Friend join me in praising their
courage and selflessness in carrying out this
extraordinary act of bravado?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely agree with
my hon. Friend and I commend the bravery and
courage shown by those two individuals—Nigel
and Grant, I think he said—who stepped into
that situation to ensure that it was not as
bad as it might have been. That is incredible
bravery; many members of the public would
not have been willing to step forward in that
way. Will he pass my best wishes—and the
best wishes of the whole House, I am sure—on
to those individuals?
>>Gloria De Piero (Ashfield) (Lab): Does the
Prime Minister believe that big companies
should put a worker on the board?
>>The Prime Minister: I believe that we should
see workers’ representation on boards. I
make no apology for the fact that this Government
are going to deliver on that. For all its
years in government, the Labour party did
nothing.