>>The Leader of the House of Commons (Mr David
Lidington): I have been asked to reply. My
right hon. Friend the Prime Minister is visiting
the Gulf Co-operation Council summit in Bahrain.
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in the House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Dr Philippa Whitford (Central Ayrshire)
(SNP): Yesterday’s signing of a memorandum
of understanding with Houston spaceport and
the Rice Space Institute brings the reality
of a Prestwick spaceport closer, with the
huge boost that that could give to the UK
aerospace industry. Will the UK Government
join the Scottish Government in supporting
an Ayrshire growth deal to literally get this
off the ground?
>>Mr Lidington: I can certainly assure the
hon. Lady that the Government are looking
keenly at the opportunities for Scotland,
and indeed the whole United Kingdom, arising
from the possible future development of commercial
space operations. The Ayrshire project that
she has described will, I am sure, be examined
closely by my ministerial colleagues who are
particularly concerned about this area of
policy. We definitely want to see the UK as
a pioneer in seizing these new commercial
opportunities.
>>Sir Peter Bottomley (Worthing West) (Con):
Perhaps thinking of rail passengers trying
to get to their jobs, the general secretary
of the TUC has spoken about “shafted and
abandoned” workers, while Unite’s Len
McCluskey is doing a UKIP dance move by resigning
before trying to return. Will my right hon.
Friend encourage union and other political
leaders to tell the National Union of Rail,
Maritime and Transport Workers that 250 people
with guaranteed employment should not be putting
the lives, jobs and safety of 600,000 Southern
rail passengers at risk?
>>Mr Lidington: I am sure that my hon. Friend
speaks on behalf of thousands of rail passengers
in his constituency and many others in the
south of England. It is deeply disappointing
that some unions are threatening to strike
over the Christmas period. The Government
are now investing record amounts in improving
our railways—up to £40 billion over the
next five years—and we need everyone in
industry, both management and unions, to work
together to secure the best deal for passengers.
I have to say that the RMT’s action shows
co-ordinated contempt for the travelling public,
and it seems designed to do nothing except
to bring about the maximum damage to people’s
lives—[Interruption.] There is some heckling
from Opposition Members. The Conservative
party is on the side of rail passengers, and
I hope that the Labour party will join me
in saying to the rail union leaders, “Sort
it out, put the travelling public first, stop
the squabbling, and tell your members to get
back to work.”
>>Emily Thornberry (Islington South and Finsbury)
(Lab): I am sure that the whole House will
want to join me in commemorating the 75th
anniversary of the Pearl Harbour attack, in
which thousands of American service personnel
and civilians died. The next day, Winston
Churchill summoned Parliament to debate the
British response and said:
“It is indispensable to our system of government
that Parliament should play its full part
in all the important acts of State”.—[Official
Report, 8 December 1941; Vol. 376, c. 1358.]
These words are a vital reminder that even
at a time of crisis—in fact, especially
at a time of national crisis—the role of
Parliament is central.
In the same spirit, we welcome the Government’s
decision to accept our motion today; they
will show Parliament their plan for Brexit
before article 50 is triggered. May I ask
the Leader of the House one central question
about this plan: do the Government want the
UK to remain part of the customs union?
>>Mr Lidington: I join the hon. Lady in marking
the anniversary of Pearl Harbour and remembering
all those who lost their lives at that time,
and also in marking—with a sense of some
celebration, even—the fact that Prime Minister
Abe is joining President Obama in going to
Pearl Harbour. He is the first Japanese Prime
Minister so to do, and that sign of reconciliation
and putting ancient conflicts behind them
is welcome.
To turn to the hon. Lady’s point about Europe,
the Government have always made it clear that
we would seek to give additional clarity about
our position at the earliest opportunity,
but it has been the case, as my right hon.
Friend the Prime Minister has said many times,
that one of our core objectives will be to
secure the maximum freedom for British companies
both to have access to and to operate within
the single European market.
>>Emily Thornberry: I thank the Leader of
the House for that answer, but I respectfully
say to him that surely on this issue the answer
should be straightforward. We all know that
it would be a disaster for British business
if we did not remain part of the customs union.
The Leader of the House said himself in February:
“Everything we take for granted…—trade…without
customs checks or paperwork at national frontiers…—would
all be up in the air... It is massive what
is at risk.”
On this side of the House, we would agree
with him—we could not agree with him more—so
can he put it beyond doubt and tell us right
now: do the Government want the UK to stay
in the customs union?
>>Mr Lidington: The hon. Lady and I—she
is right—both argued passionately for the
remain cause during the referendum. What separates
us now is that I am part of a Conservative
Government who are working together to respect
the democratic verdict of the British people
and to secure the best possible outcome for
the prosperity and security of the entire
United Kingdom from the negotiations, whereas
the hon. Lady, even just two months ago, was
telling us that she wanted
“to go back to the British people in some
way”.
She needs to decide whether she accepts the
democratic verdict or not.
>>Emily Thornberry: Of course we accept the
democratic decision of the British public—[Hon.
Members: “Ah!”] Of course we do. The difference
between our side of the House and the Government
side is that we want to leave the European
Union on behalf of 100%—on behalf of the
whole of this nation.
We really need a straightforward answer to
a straightforward question. Leaving the customs
union would mean having to check every container
coming in at Dover. It would mean UK firms
having proof of origin tests whenever they
export to Europe. It would mean chaos and
it would mean gridlock for cross-border supply
chains. As the Leader of the House said in
May, I believe about lamb and beef exports:
“They go tariff free, they go without any
extra…checks…you cannot guarantee any
of that if we are outside.”
Again, Labour Members agree with what he said
six months ago. The question is: does he still
agree with himself?
>>Mr Lidington: I thought it had not escaped
even the hon. Lady’s attention that there
has been a rather significant referendum since
February. That changes the context in which
we are now having to operate. We face a deep,
challenging and wide-ranging negotiation,
and it would be harmful to the national interest
for me or other Ministers to engage in the
sort of detailed exposition of our negotiating
position that she is now pressing upon me.
None of the other 27 Governments are doing
that; nor should we.
>>Emily Thornberry: Dear oh dear. We are not
asking for details; we are asking about a
central plank of the negotiations. If the
right hon. Gentleman cannot give us an answer
on the customs union—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. Both the questions and
the answers will be heard. If the juvenile
behaviour could stop, that would be really
helpful to the scrutiny process.
>>Emily Thornberry: We have not had an answer
on the customs union as a whole, so may I
ask the right hon. Gentleman a question about
one specific point? Since 1993, there have
been no customs checks on the land border
between Northern Ireland and the Irish Republic.
In May, when visiting Northern Ireland, he
said that if the UK
“were not part of the customs union…there
would have to be customs checks at the border.”
He also said that for anyone to pretend otherwise
“flies in the face of reality.”
Will he confirm that that remains the position?
If that is right, he really must make it clear
today that the Government are determined to
avoid that situation.
>>Mr Lidington: The Prime Minister and the
Northern Ireland Secretary have repeatedly
made it clear that we want the very long-standing
common travel and free trade arrangements
across the Irish border to continue, as indeed
do the Irish Government. We are actively engaged
in talking both to the Northern Ireland Executive
and to the Government of the Republic of Ireland
about those matters. There is goodwill on
all sides towards trying to reach a solution
that works for people north and south of the
border.
>>Emily Thornberry: The Leader of the House
has made the familiar arguments—he cannot
give answers; it is all to be resolved through
negotiations; Brexit means Brexit; Brexit
means breakfast—but that was not what the
Secretary of State for Brexit said when he
was asked about the customs union in September.
He said that he had looked at the matter carefully
and that
“that is exactly the sort of decision that
we will resolve before we trigger article
50.”—[Official Report, 5 September 2016;
Vol. 614, c. 54.]
If the Government are going to decide their
position on this issue before 31 March, will
the Leader of the House confirm that the British
people and the British Parliament will be
told some answers to my questions before the
Government tell the rest of Europe?
>>Mr Lidington: If the answers sound familiar,
it might be because we need constant repetition
before the hon. Lady understands and appreciates
the principal argument. The Government are
at the moment engaged in a consultation with
more than 50 sectors of United Kingdom business
to ascertain precisely which aspects of European
Union membership work well for them, which
they see as harmful and where the opportunities
beyond EU membership lie. We will come to
a decision and we will go into negotiations
on behalf of the full 100% of the United Kingdom
population and all four nations of the UK.
>>Emily Thornberry: The fact is—the Leader
of the House knows it, as do we all—that
he can consult as much as he likes, but the
answer will come back that we should be part
of the customs union. It is hugely disappointing
that on a day when the Government are committing
to greater transparency on their intentions
for Brexit, we are getting the usual stonewalling.
We have a Government who are promising to
tell us the plan while refusing to give us
answers to the most basic of questions, and
who are promising to give Parliament a say
while spending we do not know how much taxpayers’
money across the road in the Supreme Court
trying to stop Parliament from having a say
on this. In short, we have a Government who
cannot tell us the plan because they do not
have a plan. In February, the Leader of the
House said that what he was hearing from the
leave campaign was “confusing, contradictory,
nonsense”. My final question is this: are
we hearing anything different from the Government
today?
>>Mr Lidington: We will publish, before article
50 is triggered, a statement about our negotiating
strategy and objectives, as the Prime Minister
said yesterday. The hon. Lady seems to be
in a state of utter denial about the consequences
that flow from the referendum decision. No
other EU Government are seeking to reverse
or question the legitimacy of that vote in
the way that she and a number of her colleagues
are still trying to do. I am afraid that that
just indicates how distant the Labour party
now is from any aspirations to be back in
government again. We watch them in action,
quarrelling like “Mutiny on the Bounty”
as re-shot by the “Carry On” team. [Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. There is far too much
noise. I want to hear the words flowing. There
is no reason why the Chair should be denied
the hearing of these matters. It is very important.
>>Mr Lidington: They are rudderless. They
are drifting on Europe, as on so many other
aspects of policy. It is little wonder that
so many decent working people, who for generations
looked to Labour to be their champion, have
given up in despair and are turning to the
Conservative party as the authentic voice
of working families.
>Bob Blackman (Harrow East) (Con): In 1943,
a 16-year-old girl was forcibly taken to Auschwitz-Birkenau,
where she witnessed the horrors of the death
camps. On liberation, she came to this country
with her mother. She raised a family and became
a nurse. She dedicated her life to making
sure the people of this country and beyond
know the horrors of the holocaust. Last week,
that lady turned 90. Kitty Hart-Moxon is with
us today at Prime Minister’s Question Time.
[Applause.] Will my right hon. Friend join
me, and I think the whole House, in wishing
Kitty a very happy belated birthday, and thank
her for her lifetime of dedication to raising
this important issue? Will he also pay tribute
to the Holocaust Educational Trust, which
does everything possible to ensure we all
remember and bear witness to the horrors of
the worst part of the 20th century?
>>Mr Lidington: First, I am grateful to my
hon. Friend for raising this important issue.
I would like to join him in marking the achievements
of Kitty Hart-Moxon and the Holocaust Educational
Trust. I can never forget the impact of discovering,
as a schoolboy, that two of the boys in my
class had fathers who survived Auschwitz.
It is only a couple of generations ago that
Europe was plunged into this unspeakable horror.
It is important that not just the Holocaust
Educational Trust but all of us play our part
in ensuring that the memory of the holocaust
lives on, and that the wider lessons of that
dark period in our history are learned. I
would be grateful for the support of all Members,
right across the House from all political
parties, in working together to ensure that
that vital work continues.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): Some of the
most deprived communities in the country are
in Glasgow, yet today we learn that apparently
the Government plan to close jobcentres in
those very communities, in Parkhead, Bridgeton,
Easterhouse, Castlemilk, Langside, Anniesland,
Cambuslang and Maryhill. Is it true that the
Government are planning to close these important
offices and bring misery to the lives of the
many tens of thousands of people in Glasgow
who currently use these centres?
>>Mr Lidington: Clearly, the Department for
Work and Pensions, like every Department,
looks from time to time at its estate and
the number of offices it has, but the right
hon. Gentleman makes a perfectly reasonable
point on behalf of people in Glasgow. I will
ask my right hon. Friend the Work and Pensions
Secretary to contact him with the details
he is seeking.
>>Angus Robertson: I am sorry but that is
not good enough. [Interruption.] I am being
heckled while standing up for deprived communities.
That will ill behove Tory Members in Scotland.
The Leader of the House is correct that the
Department has plans to cut the estate by
20%, but it is planning to cut it by 50% in
Glasgow. Why are the Government planning disproportionately
to cut vital jobcentres in some of the most
deprived communities in our country?
>>Mr Lidington: The key element in any such
decision that a Department has to make is
not the raw number of offices there should
be but how accessible the offices and the
services they provide continue to be for the
people who need to use them. I am absolutely
confident that that criterion is at the heart
of my right hon. Friend’s thinking in planning
for the future of offices in Scotland and
everywhere else in the United Kingdom.
>>Amanda Milling (Cannock Chase) (Con): Passengers
on the Chase line face chaos and utter misery
every autumn, and this year it has been worse
than ever. Delayed, cancelled and overcrowded
trains are leaving passengers stranded at
stations and making them late for work and
school. Will my right hon. Friend outline
what measures the Government are taking to
penalise poor-performing train operators?
>>Mr Lidington: I sympathise with my hon.
Friend and her constituents, and all passengers
who come across these problems on the Chase
line. It is clearly unacceptable, and it is
important that the operator works hard to
secure a rapid and sustained improvement.
The Government have introduced new rules to
ensure that rail passengers will soon be able
to claim compensation if their train is more
than 15 minutes late, but as the Transport
Secretary said yesterday, more needs to be
done, and we want to see much closer working
right across the railway industry so that
this kind of problem can be resolved much
more swiftly.
>>Deidre Brock (Edinburgh North and Leith)
(SNP): Does the Leader of the House agree
with the hon. Member for North East Somerset
(Mr Rees-Mogg) that Brexit offers an opportunity
to remove pesky emissions standards? In the
red, white and blue of Brexit, will his Government
still commit to continued tough targets to
protect our environment, or will tackling
global warming become just a load of hot air?
>>Mr Lidington: The Government remain utterly
committed to both national and global ambitions
and targets on climate change. Indeed, my
right hon. Friend the Home Secretary, in her
previous job, played a key role in brokering
the Paris agreement last year—the first
ever global agreement on climate change. I
hope that the hon. Lady would welcome the
fact that we are going to be ahead of our
targets and ambitions in delivering on the
proportion of electricity provided by renewables
in this country and that we continue to work
to get our carbon emissions down.
>>Mr Peter Bone (Wellingborough) (Con): There
has been much talk recently about paying for
access to a tariff-free single market. I think
that that is a very good idea. Given that
the UK is the fifth-biggest economy in the
world and we have a £70 billion trade deficit
with the EU, would the excellent acting Prime
Minister tell the House how much the EU should
pay for tariff-free access to the UK’s single
market?
>>Mr Lidington: I thank my hon. Friend for
the upgrade, but I hope that that does not
turn out to be a career-limiting compliment.
He makes a good point in that a settlement
at the end of our negotiations that maintains
maximum access to and freedom to operate within
the European market—for UK companies elsewhere
in Europe and European companies here—is
in our mutual interest. I hope that will inspire
negotiators on both sides.
>>Patrick Grady (Glasgow North) (SNP): How
does closing Maryhill jobcentre in my constituency,
one of the most deprived parts of the country,
help my constituents who want to find a job?
Does the right hon. Gentleman accept that
travelling further to other centres will mean
increased costs for people already on the
lowest incomes and an increased risk of sanctions?
Why do the Government continue to target the
poorest and most vulnerable in our society?
>>Mr Lidington: If the Government have been
targeting the poorest and most vulnerable,
it has been to get them back to work in record
numbers and to provide a boost to the pay
of people on low incomes through the introduction
of and the increase in the national living
wage. I wish the hon. Gentleman was prepared
to welcome and celebrate those achievements.
>>Andrew Bridgen (North West Leicestershire)
(Con): As we are about to commence the most
important negotiation for decades, does my
right hon. Friend agree that forcing the Government
to disclose their negotiating strategy at
this stage is rather like showing one’s
hand of cards to an opponent before a game
of poker. I urge him to take no advice from
the Labour party; it has only one card to
play—and it is always the joker.
>>Mr Lidington: We have always said that we
would come up with some more details about
our strategic aims going into the negotiation,
but it would harm our national interest if
we were to go into the sort of detailed explanation
of our negotiating position that the Opposition
urge upon us. That is not how any of the other
27 Governments are either acting or thinking,
and we should learn from that example.
>>Mr Nigel Dodds (Belfast North) (DUP): Does
the Leader of the House agree that tonight’s
vote on the Prime Minister’s amendment,
which we fully support, is a vote of the highest
significance and greatest importance, because
for the first time right hon. and hon. Members
will have the opportunity to vote on whether
they respect the will of the people of the
United Kingdom and whether they will get on
and implement it? People will be able to read
in tomorrow’s Hansard who stands by respecting
the will of the people of the United Kingdom.
Does he also agree—I am sure he will—that
the more red, white and blue he makes it,
the better for us on the Unionist Benches?
>>Mr Lidington: As so often, the right hon.
Gentleman makes a powerful and important point.
The vote tonight will be the first opportunity
for Members to decide whether or not they
support the Government’s timetable for triggering
article 50 by the end of March 2017. Any right
hon. or hon. Member who votes against that
motion will, in my view, be seeking to thwart
the outcome of the referendum in the most
profoundly undemocratic fashion.
>>Kit Malthouse (North West Hampshire) (Con):
This country’s nuclear deterrent is our
ultimate defence, and it must be maintained
at all costs, yet hundreds of my constituents
who work at the Atomic Weapons Establishment
are currently on strike or work to rule in
a dispute over pensions. These are people
who, more often than not, have devoted their
entire working lives tending our nuclear defence
and to whom promises were made during privatisation.
Will the Leader of the House commit to sit
down with the Prime Minister to review the
situation to ensure that those promises are
being kept?
>>Mr Lidington: I will certainly ensure that
my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister is
informed about this matter. My hon. Friend
is absolutely right to raise these concerns
on behalf of his constituents. My understanding
is that the proposed changes to the Atomic
Weapons Establishment pension scheme are a
matter for the company as the employer, but
I can assure my hon. Friend that my right
hon. Friend the Defence Secretary has been
in close contact with AWE throughout the process
and has also met the trade unions. He is now
carefully considering recent developments
to see what else might be done.
>>Anna Turley (Redcar) (Lab/Co-op): I know
that the whole House will join me in sending
heartfelt sympathies and condolences to the
family of David Brown, from Eston, who, aged
just 18, took his own life. The inquest into
his death has heard that he did so on the
day he was due to sign on at the jobcentre,
after saying that he felt “belittled”
by staff despite actively looking for work
and seeking an apprenticeship. Shortly before
taking his own life, he told his mum:
“The way the Jobcentre treat people, it
is no surprise people commit suicide.”
Will the Leader of the House undertake to
review that individual case? Will he also
undertake to take stock of six years of brutal
welfare reform, and look into the way the
Department for Work and Pensions treats its
most vulnerable constituents, particularly
young people?
>>Mr Lidington: Let me first express my own
unreserved sympathy for the family of David
Brown. No parent, no family, should have to
go through that kind of shocking experience.
Clearly, human beings in any organisation
sometimes make decisions that get things wrong,
and I will ask the Department for Work and
Pensions to have a look at the particular
case that the hon. Lady has described. However,
I have to say to her that I think the principle
remains right that while staff should always
behave with courtesy towards people seeking
to claim benefits, it is also right for us
to expect people who are receiving benefits
to be subject to the kind of disciplines that
apply to people in work even if they are on
low pay. There is a principle of fairness
here, which is what lies behind the approach
that the DWP takes.
>>Rehman Chishti (Gillingham and Rainham)
(Con): I applaud the Prime Minister’s vision
of a Government for all, but, as chair of
the all-party parliamentary group for communities
engagement, I can tell the House that fewer
than 4% of those on the boards of the companies
in the FTSE 150 are from ethnic minorities.
Will the Government support a vision of helping
to increase that proportion to 10% by 2021?
>>Mr Lidington: It is clear that boardrooms
should do more to reflect the reality of modern
Britain. The Government certainly support
the principle of increasing the diversity
of boards, which is why we are supporting
the business-led ethnic diversity initiative
chaired by Sir John Parker. We strongly encourage
businesses to act on Sir John’s recommendations.
>>Tracy Brabin (Batley and Spen) (Lab): The
response to a recent freedom of information
request shows that Pinderfields hospital has
diverted ambulances destined for its accident
and emergency department to Dewsbury hospital,
in my constituency, 61 times in the past 12
months. Dewsbury is scheduled for a downgrade
next year. In the light of evidence showing
that Pinderfields cannot currently cope, will
the Leader of the House pledge urgent Government
support to keep Dewsbury A&amp;E open?
>>Mr Lidington: The NHS is certainly busier
than it has ever been in its history, which
is why it should be a matter of thanks and
tribute to hard-working NHS staff that 90%
of people going to A&amp;E are still being
seen within the four-hour target. The point
about the configuration of local services
in any part of the country is that they need
to be driven by local clinicians through trusts
working together with the clinical commissioning
groups, who manage and understand what is
needed in each locality. Local authorities,
through their health committees, have the
right to call in proposed changes in services
and refer them to the Secretary of State if
they are uncomfortable with them.
>>Craig Williams (Cardiff North) (Con): I
know that my right hon. Friend will agree
with me about the importance of the creative
sector to our economy. That, in conjunction
with the Welsh language, makes S4C, or Sianel
Pedwar Cymru—which is currently based in
my constituency—hugely important to the
Welsh and British culture and economy. Will
my right hon. Friend reaffirm the Government’s
commitment to protecting the S4C budget while
we review the future of the Welsh language
broadcaster?
>>Mr Lidington: We are fully committed to
the future of Welsh language broadcasting,
and to S4C. I am pleased to say that the licence
fee settlement that we have agreed has provided
financial certainty, protecting S4C’s funding
at more than £74 million a year for the next
five years. We are absolutely committed to
ensuring that the channel continues to make
first-class shows and serve Welsh-speaking
audiences in my hon. Friend’s constituency,
and, for that matter, throughout the United
Kingdom.
>>Naz Shah (Bradford West) (Lab): Is the Leader
of the House aware of reports of Rohingyan
children being massacred and thrown into fires,
of Rohingyan women being raped, and of houses
being razed to the ground? What representations
have the Government made to the Burmese authorities
or the military in that regard?
>>Mr Lidington: Those reports from Rohingya
are extremely concerning. As the hon. Lady
knows, there is a long history of discrimination
against the Rohingya people in Burma. British
Ministers and the British embassy and officials
in London make our concern very clear at regular
intervals to the Burmese authorities.
>>Steve Double (St Austell and Newquay) (Con):
Following the revelations in the BBC “Panorama”
programme, Clinton House in my constituency
is now closed. Three further care homes run
by the Morleigh Group have now been rated
as inadequate by the Care Quality Commission
and two others are under inspection. Concerns
have been raised about these care homes for
many years, and it cannot be acceptable that
it took the BBC to provoke the action that
was desperately needed. Does the Leader of
the House agree that it is now time to urgently
review the role of the CQC to ensure that
in future concerns raised by residents, families
and staff are properly and promptly addressed?
>>Mr Lidington: Older and vulnerable people
deserve the highest quality care possible.
There is no excuse for services that fall
short of expectations in the way my hon. Friend
has described. The CQC has extensive powers
in law to ensure that nobody in the chain
of responsibility is immune to legal accountability,
and I would expect the CQC to exercise those
powers in full in this case. But my hon. Friend
has made some criticisms of the CQC and the
Government have been looking into ways to
improve its processes and increase its efficiency.
The Under-Secretary of State for Health, my
hon. Friend the Member for Warrington South
(David Mowat), is the Minister responsible
for community health and care, and he discussed
this very issue with the CQC earlier today.
>>Geraint Davies (Swansea West) (Lab/Co-op):
US satellite data show that 6% of methane
from fracking is leaked through fugitive emissions.
Given that methane is 86 times worse than
CO2 for global warming over a 20-year timeframe,
will the right hon. Gentleman support the
Council of Europe’s call for the banning
of fracking, or at least for a maximum of
0.1% fugitive emissions at the wellhead?
>>Mr Lidington: No, Mr Speaker. The Government
took their decision to give a go-ahead to
fracking after extensive consideration of
both the economic and the environmental risks
and opportunities involved. We are confident
that fracking can be carried out in a way
that is safe and does not harm the environment,
but which also provides job opportunities
for this country and makes us less dependent
on the import of energy.
>>Mr Steve Baker (Wycombe) (Con): I expect
my right hon. Friend will be astonished, if
not aghast, to learn that a succession of
journalists from the BBC have contacted me
seeking to create—to manufacture—stories
of Back-Bench rebellion on the issue of the
EU. [Interruption.] Will he—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I want to hear about
these activities.
>>Mr Baker: Does my right hon. Friend agree
with me that on these controversial issues
the BBC should stick to its charter obligations
on accuracy and impartiality, instead of seeking
to create problems for the Government?
>>Mr Lidington: I am sure that my hon. Friend
is shocked at the thought that anybody should
look to him as a source of information about
rebellions against the Government. I hope
he will be able to find some comfort in the
fact that the new royal charter and agreement
require the BBC to deliver impartial news—the
very first time impartiality has been enshrined
in the BBC’s mission.
>>Carolyn Harris (Swansea East) (Lab): Having
now received a response from the Prime Minister
to my request for a children’s funeral fund,
I was disturbed to be told that the social
fund could provide a “simple and respectful
funeral.” This answer is both insensitive
and totally lacks any understanding of my
original request. Has the Leader of the House
the authority to facilitate a meeting with
me and other bereaved mothers, so that we
can explain to the Prime Minister exactly
what we are asking for? This request is important
to us as parents, many in this House and,
judging from my postbag, many people and organisations
across the country.
>>Mr Lidington: Burying a child must be an
incredibly painful experience for any family,
and I think we all pay respect to, and have
enormous sympathy with, the hon. Member for
Swansea East (Carolyn Harris). She says she
speaks on behalf of thousands of parents who
have had to go through that anguish. As the
Prime Minister has said, there are mechanisms
in place for making financial support available
from central Government, and local authorities
are of course free to waive funeral fees for
child burials, and many of them do so. I will
talk to my ministerial colleagues about the
hon. Lady’s request for a meeting, and I
am sure that she will receive a response to
that.
>>Richard Graham (Gloucester) (Con): Good
train links are vital in enabling our constituents
to get to work. It is therefore incredibly
frustrating for my constituents that, of the
63 services a day that CrossCountry operates
between Birmingham and Bristol, only three
stop at the city of Gloucester on the way.
Will my right hon. Friend ensure that when
Ministers extend the train operator’s franchise,
they do not allow CrossCountry to go on treating
Gloucester like a leper to be avoided at all
costs, and that they instead oblige the company
to deliver the kind of service that every
city deserves?
>>Mr Lidington: My hon. Friend is as always
speaking up strongly on behalf of his constituents.
Any of us who have been to Gloucester will
know that it is a place we want to be able
to visit frequently and easily. The Government
are investing record amounts in improving
our railways and, in his particular case,
Transport Ministers are working with CrossCountry
and Great Western to see how the Gloucester
service can be improved.