>>John Glen (Salisbury) (Con): If she will
list her official engagements for Wednesday
20 July.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
am sure that the whole House will wish to
join me in welcoming today’s employment
figures, which show employment at another
record high, the lowest unemployment rate
in over a decade and wages rising.
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others, and in addition to
my duties in this House I shall have further
such meetings later today. This afternoon,
I will travel to Berlin to meet Chancellor
Merkel to discuss how we implement the decision
that the British people took in the referendum,
and I expect we will also cover a number of
other pressing international issues. Tomorrow,
I will visit Paris for similar discussions
with President Hollande.
>>John Glen: I warmly welcome the Prime Minister
to her place. Given her unwavering commitment
to delivering economic stability and national
security in our United Kingdom’s interest,
does she welcome Monday’s emphatic vote
in this House for the Trident Successor programme,
and will she ensure that economic stability
and national security remain the guiding principles
of her premiership?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for his kind remarks. I join him in enthusiastically
welcoming the vote taken in this House on
Monday evening to renew our nuclear deterrent.
I think that vote showed the commitment of
this House: it showed that we have not only
committed to our own national security, but
considered the security of European and NATO
allies. We can now get on with the essential
job of renewing our nuclear deterrent. May
I thank the 140 Labour Members of Parliament
who put the national interest first and voted
to renew the nuclear deterrent?
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): May
I welcome the right hon. Lady to her first
Prime Minister’s Question Time, and congratulate
her on her appointment and on becoming the
country’s second woman Prime Minister? I
hope that she will agree with me that Prime
Minister’s Question Time in this House should
be an opportunity to debate seriously the
issues that face our country and our place
in the world.
On the steps of Downing Street, the Prime
Minister talked very eloquently about “fighting…burning
injustice”; yet her last act as Home Secretary
was to shunt the Orgreave inquiry into the
long grass. The Advocate General told the
House of Lords:
“The IPCC told Home Office officials that
if it announced any action to set up an inquiry
or other investigation relating to Orgreave,
it would have an impact on the Hillsborough
investigation.”
The Independent Police Complaints Commission
disputes that account. I hope Parliament was
not misled. Will the Prime Minister now proceed
with a full public inquiry into the terrible
events at Orgreave?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank the right hon.
Gentleman for the welcome he has given me.
He referred to me as the second woman Prime
Minister. In my years in the House, I have
long heard the Labour party asking what the
Conservative party does for women. Well—it
just keeps making us Prime Minister.
I welcome the comments the right hon. Gentleman
made about Prime Minister’s questions. We
do debate serious issues at Prime Minister’s
questions. I look forward to the exchanges
he and I will have, and I hope that we will
be having those exchanges over the Dispatch
Box for many years to come.
As regards the Orgreave inquiry, I think the
shadow Home Secretary has an urgent question
on that this afternoon, to which the Home
Secretary will be responding.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The new Prime Minister also
said on the steps of Downing Street:
“If you’re young, you’ll find it harder
than ever before to own your own home.”
In 1998, more than half of working households
of people aged 16 to 34 were buying their
own homes. Today, the figure is 25% and the
Resolution Foundation suggests it will fall
to 10% in the next nine years. What figure
has the Prime Minister set herself for home
ownership among young people?
>>The Prime Minister: I notice the timeline
that the right hon. Gentleman referred to.
He might have forgotten that during that period
we had 13 years of a Labour Government—a
Labour Government who had a very bad record
on house building. It is this Government who
will change that and this Government who are
putting more into building more homes to ensure
that young people have a better opportunity
to get on the housing ladder. That is why
we are a Government who will govern for everyone
in this country.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: That Labour Government put
a decent homes standard in place in every
part of this country. I am not sure that—[Interruption.]
I am not sure that starter homes at £450,000
for young people earning 7% less than their
parents’ generation represent a good prospect
for people owning their own homes.
The Prime Minister is rightly concerned that:
“If you’re black, you’re treated more
harshly…than if you’re white.”
Before appointing her new Foreign Secretary,
did she discuss with him his description of
black people as “piccaninnies” and ask
why he had questioned the motives of US President
Obama on the basis of his “part-Kenyan”
heritage?
>>The Prime Minister: The
right hon. Gentleman started his question
by making reference to the issue of starter
homes and the upper limit in London of £450,000.
I have sat on these Benches and heard him
raise that with my right hon. Friend the Member
for Witney (Mr Cameron) on a number of occasions
when he was Prime Minister. Can I just explain
this to the Leader of the Opposition? If he
looks at house prices across the country,
he will see that they vary. In Liverpool,
the average house price is just over £116,000.
In London, the average house price is just
over £676,000. That is why we have a higher
limit for starter homes in London. If he objects
to that, he needs to tell his constituents
why he is against their having opportunities
to get on the housing ladder.
The right hon. Gentleman referred to the remarks
I made. It is correct that if you are black,
you will be treated more harshly in the criminal
justice system. That is exactly why, as Home
Secretary, I dealt with the issue of stop
and search. I was concerned to make sure that
nobody should be stopped and searched on the
streets of this country because of the colour
of their skin. I did that as a Conservative;
in 13 years, Labour did nothing on it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was actually
about the language used by the Foreign Secretary.
Earlier this week, the new Chancellor abandoned
the Government’s budget surplus target,
which Labour has long called for. The Prime
Minister’s Government are already missing
their targets on debt, the deficit, the welfare
cap and productivity. Six years of Government
austerity have failed. The long-term economic
plan is clearly dead. Is there a new one?
>>The Prime Minister: It is the long-term
economic plan that has delivered the record
level of employment that we see today. Perhaps
I could put the right hon. Gentleman straight.
We have not abandoned the intention to move
to a surplus. What I have said is that we
will not target that at the end of this Parliament.
He uses the language of austerity; I call
it living within our means. He talks about
austerity, but actually it is about not saddling
our children and grandchildren with significant
debts in the years to come. It is not about
austerity; it is about ensuring that we have
an economy that works for everyone.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Jobless claims have risen
for the fourth month in a row and welfare
claims have risen as well. Austerity actually
means people being poorer, services being
cut and local facilities being closed. In
her speech on the steps of Downing Street
the Prime Minister also addressed insecure
workers, saying:
“You have a job but you don’t always have
job security.”
Does that mean that those people who are worried
about their future in work—[Interruption.]
I am talking of the people who sent us here
to serve them. Does that mean that she is
proposing to scrap employment tribunal fees,
repeal the Trade Union Act 2016 and ban zero-hours
contracts, as more than a dozen European nations
have done already? That would help to give
greater job security to many very worried
people in this country.
>>The Prime Minister: Again, i say to the
right hon. Gentleman that yes, I said that
on the steps of Downing Street, because it
is very important that here in this House
we consider not only what might be called
the more obvious injustices, but life for
those people who are in work and struggling
to make ends meet. That is essential, and
the Government have raised the threshold at
which people start to pay income tax, for
example. It is also about making sure that
we have more well-paid jobs in this country,
which the Government are also doing.
I am interested that the right hon. Gentleman
referred to the situation of some workers
who might have job insecurity and potentially
unscrupulous bosses. I suspect that many Members
on the Opposition Benches might be familiar
with an unscrupulous boss—a boss who does
not listen to his workers, a boss who requires
some of his workers to double their workload
and maybe even a boss who exploits the rules
to further his own career. Remind him of anybody?
>>Jeremy Corbyn: We are sent here to represent
people. Many people in this country are struggling
with low wages and insecure jobs—[Hon. Members:
“You!”] I know this is very funny for
all the Conservative Members, but I do not
suppose there are too many Conservative MPs
who have to go to a food bank to supplement
the food on their family’s table every week.
We should reflect on that.
The Prime Minister highlighted the failures
of her predecessor on social justice, home
ownership, education and the cost of living.
Some might say that, as a Cabinet Minister,
she too was responsible for those. She empathised
with working people, saying:
“I know you’re working around the clock,
I know you’re doing your best, and I know
that sometimes life can be a struggle.”
Yesterday a report from the Institute for
Fiscal Studies found that two thirds of children
living in poverty in Britain have at least
one parent in work. What, other than warm
words, is she going to offer those families
and those children, who are often hungry and
very insecure in their way of living? Is it
not our duty to offer some hope and security
to them?
>>The Prime Minister: Yes it is, and we are
concerned about those people, but the answer
is not the Labour party’s unlimited, uncapped
welfare for people. The answer for people
who are in work and struggling and for those
who want to get into work is to have a strong
economy that delivers jobs, and well-paid
jobs in particular. I assure the right hon.
Gentleman that on the Government Benches we
are focused on building a country that works
for everyone. That means an economy that ensures
that everyone can benefit from the nation’s
wealth, a society where everyone gets the
opportunities they deserve and a democracy
that everyone can have faith in.
Finally, I say to the right hon. Gentleman
that the Labour party may be about to spend
several months fighting and tearing itself
apart; the Conservative party will be spending
those months bringing this country back together.
>>MPs: More!
>>Mr Speaker: There will be more. I call Sir
Edward Leigh.
>>Sir Edward Leigh (Gainsborough) (Con): I
agree with the Prime Minister. [Hon. Members:
“Hear, hear!”] We are leaving the EU and
we are going to make a success of it, so will
she make my day special by saying that she
is prepared to reject staying in the single
regulated market and to offer instead to our
friends in Europe a free trade deal that is
very much in their interests? Let us take
back control.
>>MPs: Hear, hear!
>>The Prime Minister: I am tempted to say
that I probably ought to sit down and enjoy
that for the rest of the day. My hon. Friend
has made my day, and I hope that I can make
his day by wishing him a very happy birthday.
I assure him that as we look at the result
of the referendum, I am very clear that Brexit
does mean Brexit, and as he says, we will
make a success of it. In negotiating the deal,
we need to ensure that we listen to what people
have said about the need for controls on free
movement, and that we also negotiate the right
and best deal for trade in goods and services
for the British people.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): May I extend
my congratulations to the Prime Minister on
her first outing at Prime Minister’s questions,
ahead of her travels to Berlin? The German
Vice Chancellor, Sigmar Gabriel, has already
confirmed how Scotland is able to remain in
the European Union. Did the Prime Minister
discuss that when she met First Minister Nicola
Sturgeon in Edinburgh, and will she do everything
to ensure that remain means remain for Scotland?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank the right hon.
Gentleman for his welcome, for his comments
in Monday’s debate, and for his recognition
of support for my husband Philip. As the right
hon. Gentleman said, we all rely on support
from those around us to do our jobs, and we
should never forget that. I did discuss arrangements
in relation to the negotiations for the United
Kingdom leaving the EU with the First Minister,
and I was very pleased that my first trip
was a trip to Scotland and that I was able
to do that so early in my premiership. As
I have been clear, the Union is very important
to me. I was also clear with the First Minister
that I think that some of the ideas being
put forward are impracticable, but I am willing
to listen to options that are brought forward,
and we will be engaging fully with all the
devolved Administrations.
>>Angus Robertson: Germany has the highest
level of support of any continental European
country for Scotland remaining in the European
Union. Will the Prime Minister thank Chancellor
Merkel for the interest of the members of
her Government and of the Bundestag in having
Scotland remain within the EU? Will she assure
the Chancellor and other Heads of State and
Government that we in Scotland will do everything—everything—that
is necessary for us to remain in the EU?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
has taken that line for some time—he took
it with my predecessor—but I find it a little
confusing, given that only two years ago in
the Scottish referendum, the Scottish National
party was campaigning for Scotland to leave
the United Kingdom, which would have meant
leaving the European Union.
>>Daniel Kawczynski (Shrewsbury and Atcham)
(Con): We all stand with the people of France,
and particularly Nice, following the appalling
terrorist act there last week. Will the Prime
Minister update the House on how the security
collaboration between our two countries can
help to prevent such attacks in future, and
will she reassure the French people that although
we are leaving the European Union, the close
links between our two countries will remain
steadfast?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important topic, and as has been said in
this House before, our thoughts are with all
the people of France after the appalling attack
that took place in Nice last week. We continue
to work with the French authorities in the
aftermath of that attack, and my hon. Friend
is right to say that we must continue our
security co-operation with France and other
European countries. We will not be cowed by
terrorists; we both face the same threats,
and we need to work together to defeat those
threats. I absolutely confirm that, yes, the
United Kingdom will leave the European Union,
but the United Kingdom is not leaving Europe
and our co-operation will continue.
>>Mr Jamie Reed (Copeland) (Lab): I welcome
the Prime Minister to her place and I wish
her well in healing the country in the months
and years to come—after all, it is she and
her colleagues who so bitterly divided it.
I also thank her for her wholehearted support
for and endorsement of official Labour party
policy on Trident. It is such a refreshing
change to hear that from the Dispatch Box.
As a type 1 diabetic and a father and uncle
to children with type 1 diabetes, and on behalf
of 500,000 people in this country, 30,000
of them children, may I thank the Prime Minister
for the example she has shown in demonstrating
without doubt that diabetes does not hold
us back in any way whatsoever? There is no
doubt that the Prime Minister’s predecessor
left the NHS in a much worse condition than
he found it. Will the Prime Minister visit
West Cumberland hospital in my constituency,
honour the promises made by the previous Prime
Minister, and stop her Government cutting
services there further?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman refers
to divisions on the Conservative Benches.
I have to say: which party was it that took
three weeks to decide who its unity candidate
should be? It is the Labour party that is
divided.
I thank the hon. Gentleman for his remarks
on type 1 diabetes. There are many youngsters
out there, from tiny tots to teenagers, living
with type 1 diabetes. It is important that
we send a message to them that their future
is not limited: they can do whatever they
want.
The hon. Gentleman is the first hon. Member
at Prime Minister’s questions to invite
me to his constituency. I will, of course,
look very closely at all invitations I receive.
It is important that decisions about the construct
of local NHS services are taken at a local
level by the NHS. He made a point about the
agreement in the official policy of the Conservative
party and the Labour party on Trident. I simply
remind him that where we did disagree at the
election was that the Conservative party agreed
to put in the money that was necessary for
the NHS. The Labour party refused to commit
to that.
>>Nusrat Ghani (Wealden) (Con): Extremism
takes many forms, from the atrocity in Nice
to the violent murder of Qandeel Baloch by
her own brother in Pakistan. That murder was
justified as an “honour killing”. There
have been 11,000 incidents of self-styled
honour crimes in the UK in the past five years.
Does the Prime Minister agree that such crimes
are in fact acts of terror, not honour? Will
she therefore direct her new Government to
choose to lead and end the use of the word
“honour” to describe these vile acts in
order to stop giving any legitimacy to the
idea that women are the property of men?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
a very important issue, one that I think resonates
across the whole House. She is absolutely
right: extremism does take many forms. That
is why, in the Government’s counter-extremism
strategy, we are looking very widely across
the breadth of issues of extremism, including
tackling the root causes of some practices
within communities, such as so-called honour-based
violence. I absolutely agree with her that
there is absolutely no honour in so-called
honour-based violence. It is violence and
a criminal act, pure and simple.
>>Julie Cooper (Burnley) (Lab): I, too, welcome
the Prime Minister to her first Prime Minister’s
Question Time. Will she listen to the headteachers
of the excellent primary schools in my constituency?
They tell me that the recent unprecedented
changes to primary education, including the
new SATs, have led to negative impacts on
children’s learning outcomes. Will she urge
the new Secretary of State to take those concerns
forward, listen and make useful changes?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank the hon. Lady
for her welcome. Getting education right is
absolutely crucial if we are to ensure that
people can take up the opportunities they
deserve and have the aspiration to take up
those opportunities. Obviously, my right hon.
Friend the new Education Secretary will be
looking across the board at the education
provision that is in place. We have made some
important changes already over the past six
years that are improving the quality of education
and mean that more children are receiving
the quality of education they need. There
is, of course, more for us to do and we will
be looking to do that.
>>Andrew Stephenson (Pendle) (Con): In my
constituency, aerospace is of vital importance,
with Rolls-Royce employing more than 1,000
people at sites in Barnoldswick. Aerospace
is important not just to Pendle, however,
but to the whole UK economy, so will the Prime
Minister congratulate all the companies that
attended the Farnborough airshow last week
on the deals they signed, and does she agree
that the nearly £100 billion of trade deals
already done this year demonstrates that Britain
is very much still open for business?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right that Britain is open for business, and
I know what an important role the aerospace
industry plays in his constituency, as he
pointed out with his reference to Rolls-Royce,
and in constituencies across the country.
I also know of the importance of the Farnborough
airshow. My hon. Friend the Member for Aldershot
(Sir Gerald Howarth) was telling me last night
what a great airshow it was. The Government
committed at Farnborough to providing a new
£365 million fund for research and development
to ensure we retain our leading position in
the sector. As my hon. Friend also said, a
significant number of trade deals have already
been signed, which shows that Britain is open
for business. I would encourage other companies
to go out there and get that business.
>>Catherine McKinnell (Newcastle upon Tyne
North) (Lab): I, too, welcome the right hon.
Lady to her place. Newcastle airport was voted
“best in Britain” this week, but the good
news that it is really waiting for is a decision
on Heathrow expansion. The Prime Minister
knows that Britain needs to be open for business,
so will she do better than dithering Dave
and give us a decision without delay?
>>The Prime Minister: I have fond memories
of Newcastle airport, from the time when I
stood in the North West Durham constituency
some years ago and made quite good use of
the airport. It has changed and expanded rather
since then. Our position on Heathrow has not
changed. Obviously, there was the Howard Davies
review, and further work has been done on
the question of air quality around the proposals
put forward. The Cabinet and the Government
will take a decision, in the proper way, in
due course.
>>Kelly Tolhurst (Rochester and Strood) (Con):
Based on an analysis of the crime survey for
England and Wales by the Children’s Society,
it is estimated that 113 16 and 17-year-old
girls in my constituency experienced a sexual
offence in the past year. Given the progress
made in tackling child sexual exploitation
in the last few years, will my right hon.
Friend outline whether the Government have
plans to strengthen the protection for this
particular vulnerable age group?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
a very important issue. We have seen recently
the appalling circumstances in Rotherham in
relation to child sexual exploitation, but
as she has shown, in every constituency in
the country, young people are being subjected
to sexual offences of various sorts. That
is why, since Rotherham, the Government have
been working with all the appropriate agencies
to ensure we put greater support in place.
We have provided an extra £7 million of funding
to ensure that victims of sexual abuse receive
the right support, launched the whistleblowing
helpline to help authorities spot patterns
of failure, and made child sexual abuse and
exploitation a national threat, meaning that
police authorities have a duty to collaborate
on this terrible crime. In the coming months,
we will also be strengthening our arrangements.
We are all appalled by child sexual abuse,
and we need to carry on making sure that we
eradicate it.
>>Imran Hussain (Bradford East) (Lab): In
her first statement from the steps of Downing
Street, the Prime Minister stated that she
would lead a Government who would work for
everyone. Since she became Prime Minister,
I have tried unsuccessfully to get assurances
on the continuation of the northern schools
strategy and the £80 million set aside for
it. Will she give me that commitment today
so that children in Bradford and the north
can have the same chances as those in London
and the south?
>>The Prime Minister: It is important that
we ensure that children across the country
get the opportunities they deserve, and the
quality of education they receive is an important
part of that. The review launched in March
by Sir Nick Weller will make recommendations
to address this particular issue. I assure
the hon. Gentleman that my right hon. Friend
the Education Secretary will look carefully
at the result of that review and, in due course,
make clear the Government’s response to
its recommendations.
>>Stuart Andrew (Pudsey) (Con): Growing up
on a council estate, I found it tough coming
out—as a Conservative. Difficult as it was,
I understood then, as I do now, that it is
only Conservative Governments that deliver
real social mobility. Does my right hon. Friend
agree that it is the Government’s job to
fight for such opportunities for the people
of Britain, because the Labour party are too
busy fighting each other?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend puts
it very well. If we look at the Conservative
Benches, we see, as he said, Conservative
Members of Parliament who were brought up
in council houses and Conservative MPs brought
up by single parent families, while the chairman
of the Conservative party is a former miner.
It is this party that is looking at opportunity
for all. I am certainly very clear that the
Government I lead will be driven not by the
interests of the privileged few, but by the
interests of everyone in this country. We
are not entrenching the advantages of the
privileged few in terms of opportunity, but
extending opportunity to all.
>>Stuart Blair Donaldson (West Aberdeenshire
and Kincardine) (SNP): Whatever one’s politics,
one cannot help but be inspired by last week’s
image of the female Prime Minister of the
UK meeting the female First Minister of Scotland.
It sends a message to girls everywhere that
they can achieve anything they want, and nothing
should be off limits to them. Does the Prime
Minister agree that to do this, girls and
women should be able to live free from gender-based
violence and domestic abuse, and will she
commit to supporting the Bill of my hon. Friend
the Member for Banff and Buchan (Dr Whiteford)
and ratify the Istanbul convention?
>>The Prime Minister: It is an important symbol
for girls and young women when they can see
women in positions such as Prime Minister
and First Minister of Scotland. I respect
the First Minister; we had a very constructive
first meeting. There were certain issues on
which we disagree and will continue to disagree,
but we will work practically and pragmatically
together.
It is important to deal with the issues of
gender violence and domestic violence against
women and girls. That is why the Government
have—I led this as Home Secretary—a strategy
to deal with violence against women and girls,
which is now being taken on by my right hon.
Friend the new Home Secretary. We have a good
record on what we have done, for example,
putting into operation domestic violence protection
orders and the new coercive control offence,
but there is always more to do and we will
be doing that.
>>Simon Hoare (North Dorset) (Con): I welcome
my right hon. Friend to her place, and if
it is not too untoward to say, I declare it
as game, set and match to her this afternoon.
Last week, when I met local National Farmers
Union representatives in North Dorset, they
understood precisely what we were doing in
delivering on Brexit, but were keen to ensure
that the needs of agriculture and British
farmers are front and centre in those discussions
and that their interests are not neglected.
May I invite my right hon. Friend to make
that commitment today?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to make
the commitment that, as we look at the position
we will take in the negotiations for the UK
to leave the European Union, we will consult
widely. I recognise that agriculture is a
sector that is particularly affected by Brexit,
and I can assure my hon. Friend that we will
consult and listen to the views of farmers
and others involved in the food industry and
agricultural sector.
>>Mr Barry Sheerman (Huddersfield) (Lab/Co-op):
I congratulate the right hon. Lady on becoming
Prime Minister, and gently remind her of the
conversation we had a few weeks ago when I
said she was going to come through the middle
and trounce the men standing for that position.
I was right. I also said I was going to put
some money on her, but I never got round to
it—unfortunately, because the odds were
very good at the time.
May I ask the Prime Minister a serious question
about the younger generation, the millennials?
So many of them in our country believe that
they are citizens of Europe who have the ability
to travel, to work and to be true Europeans.
Will she soon give them her vision of how
that reality as European citizens can be delivered
even in the present circumstances?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank the hon. Gentleman,
and I do indeed remember the conversation
in which he said that I would, as he put it,
“trounce the men”. I have to say, however,
that the Conservative party came up with an
all-woman shortlist, without being required
to do so.
The hon. Gentleman raises an important point
about the younger generation. This is what
I would say to them today. As I said a little
earlier in response to my hon. Friend the
Member for Shrewsbury and Atcham (Daniel Kawczynski),
we are leaving the European Union, but we
are not leaving Europe. Over the coming weeks
and months, we will be setting out our negotiating
position on the relationship with the European
Union when we leave. I would also say to the
young people that the hon. Gentleman talks
about that we should not limit their opportunities
and their horizons by just looking at Europe.
This country will make a success of Brexit,
because we will be out there in the world
as an outward-looking, expansive country,
with opportunities around the globe.
>>Philip Davies (Shipley) (Con): May I warmly
welcome the Prime Minister to her post? Unlike
dithering Barry, I did place a bet on her
becoming the next leader of our party. I apologise
for the fact that my phone was obviously turned
off when she was calling me to invite me to
join her Government.
The reason the people of Yorkshire voted overwhelmingly
to leave the European Union was largely to
do with immigration control. Can the Prime
Minister reassure them that when we finally
do leave the European Union, she will insist
on keeping her original promise to bring the
immigration figures down to the tens of thousands?
>>The Prime Minister: The vote that took place
on 23 June sent a very clear message about
immigration. It sent the clear message that
people want control of free movement from
the European Union, and that is precisely
what we will ensure that we get in the negotiations
that we will undertake. I also remain absolutely
firm in my belief that we need to bring net
migration down to sustainable levels, and
the Government believe that that means tens
of thousands. It will take some time to get
there, but now, of course, there is the added
aspect of the controls that we can bring in
relation to people moving from the European
Union.
>>Mr Speaker: Finally, I call Mr Tim Farron.
[Interruption.]
>>Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
You are all very, very kind.
May I, genuinely, warmly welcome the Prime
Minister to her position? She has come a long
way since we were on the hustings together
in North West Durham, and she is no doubt
reflecting on the fact that she is receiving
more support in the Chamber than either of
us received in Consett working men’s club.
There are reports today that the new Brexit
unit will be hiring lawyers at a cost of £5,000
per head per day. May I ask whether the Prime
Minister will be using the mythical £350
million to pay the legal fees, or is that
still pencilled in for the NHS, as promised
by her Cabinet colleagues who campaigned for
Leave?
>>The Prime Minister: I think it absolutely
right for us to create a new Department to
focus on the work of negotiating the United
Kingdom’s departure from the United Kingdom,
and that Department will need the expertise
that will enable it to undertake the negotiations.
I am very happy to remember the days that
the hon. Gentleman and I spent campaigning
in North West Durham at the time of a general
election. Little did the voters of North West
Durham know that the two unsuccessful candidates
in that election would become leaders of two
of the country’s political parties, although
I would point out to the hon. Gentleman that
my party is a little bit bigger than his.