>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
am sure that the whole House will join me
in wishing people across the United Kingdom
and, indeed, the whole world a very happy
St Andrew’s day.
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others, and in addition to
my duties in this House I shall have further
such meetings later today.
>>Caroline Lucas (Brighton, Pavilion) (Green):
May I suggest to the Prime Minister that “having
your cake and eating it” is not a serious
strategy for Brexit and that Britain deserves
better that having to rely on leaked documents
to know the Government’s plans? How on earth
can she expect MPs to vote to trigger article
50 when she refuses to give any clarity on
what kind of Brexit she is pursuing and whether
it will involve us still being members of
the single market? Is it arrogance, or is
it incompetence?
>>The Prime Minister: I have answered this
question many times in this House. The hon.
Lady asks specifically about the single market
and trading with the European Union, and I
have been very clear that we are ambitious
in getting the best possible deal for trading
with and operating within the single European
market.
>>Mark Menzies (Fylde) (Con): I welcome last
week’s autumn statement announcement of
£556 million for infrastructure in the north
of England, but despite that and years of
hard work, the M55 Lytham St Annes link road
is still not assured. Will my right hon. Friend
the Prime Minister do everything she can to
ensure that this vital local project for jobs
and employment in my constituency is delivered
without further delay?
>>The Prime Minister: I commend my hon. Friend
on the hard work he has put in in relation
to this project. I understand that there is
to be a significant sum of funding from a
developer and that my hon. Friend has been
working with the developer and the county
council on this issue. The local enterprise
partnership has submitted a linked bid to
Highways England that is being actively considered,
and I understand that my hon. Friend is meeting
my right hon. Friend the Minister of State
for Transport this afternoon to discuss this
in more detail.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): May
I join the Prime Minister in wishing everyone
a very happy St Andrew’s day wherever they
are celebrating it, all around the world?
Last week, the autumn statement revealed the
abject failure of this Government’s economic
strategy. Economic growth was revised down;
wage growth was revised down; business investment
was revised down; and borrowing and debt were
revised up, yet again. Surely, now the Prime
Minister accepts that her predecessor’s
long-term economic plan was actually a failure.
>>The Prime Minister: I will give the right
hon. Gentleman some facts. The IMF says that
this will be the fastest-growing advanced
economy in the world this year. Unemployment
is down. We have record numbers of people
in employment and we have companies such as
Nissan, Jaguar Land Rover, Honda, ARM, Google,
Facebook and Apple investing in the UK, securing
jobs here in the United Kingdom. That is what
a good economic plan does.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Government did tell us
that the deficit would be eradicated by 2015.
That was then advanced to 2020, and now it
has been advanced to whenever in the future.
The right hon. Lady quotes the IFS, but she
is being a little selective. It went on to
say that the prospect for workers over the
next six years was “dreadful”, creating
“the worst decade for living standards certainly
since the last war and probably since the
1920s”.
Is it not fair to say that those who are just
getting by are suffering all the pain for
no gain?
>>The Prime Minister: Given that the right
hon. Gentleman cannot differentiate between
the IMF and the IFS, it is probably a good
job that he is sitting there and I am standing
here. Let me tell him what we are doing for
those people, and let us think about those
people who do find life difficult, who are
struggling to get by, who have a job but worry
about their job security, who have a home
but worry about paying the mortgage, and who
are worried about their children’s education
and whether their children will be able to
buy a home. What measures have we taken? We
have increased the national living wage. We
introduced the national living wage. We are
increasing personal tax allowance, taking
more people out of paying tax altogether.
We are increasing the number of affordable
homes being built. But we can only do this
if we have a strong economy, and it is our
plan that delivers that strong economy.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Wages have stagnated; home
ownership is falling; homelessness has doubled;
and queues at food banks are rising every
day. If the Prime Minister really believes
the economy is doing well, why are her Government
forcing through £2 billion of cuts to in-work
support, cutting the incomes of working people
and leaving many households over £2,000 a
year worse off?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
starts his question by talking about home
ownership. Let us be very clear what is happening
in respect of housing. House building starts
fell by 45% under Labour in 12 years. They
have increased by over two thirds since the
Conservatives were in government. Yes, we
are making changes to the welfare system.
He and I have a fundamental difference of
opinion about the welfare system. I think
what is important in the welfare system is
that we remember those who are benefiting
from it and we remember those who are paying
for it. The universal credit system is there
to ensure that work will always pay. I believe
in a welfare system that does help people
to get into work, that does encourage people
into the workplace. He believes in a welfare
system where people are able to live on benefits.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The last Labour Government
took 800,000 children out of poverty. Under
the right hon. Lady’s Government, child
poverty is rising and now covers 4 million
children across this country. Our people are
suffering because of the policies of her Government.
People are paying the price for her failed
economic experiment. The Government have even
now abandoned the previous Chancellor’s
pledge that their so-called national living
wage would be paying at least £9 per hour
by 2020. What is the new pledge on living
wage?
>>The Prime Minister: The pledge on living
wage is set out in the autumn statement and
is as it always has been. The right hon. Gentleman
talks about poverty. Actually, we are seeing
fewer families in absolute poverty and fewer
families in relative poverty. I come back
to the point I have been making in answer
to his previous questions: it is only possible
to do these things by having a strong economy.
The one thing we know is that the policy that
would not deliver a strong economy is Labour’s
policy to increase borrowing by £500 billion.
He talks about the impact on people in work.
Let me remind him what the former shadow Treasury
Minister said: Labour’s policy to increase
borrowing would lead to double the income
tax, double council tax, double VAT and double
national insurance. That will not help anybody
who is in the workplace and just about managing.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I am not entirely sure where
the Government’s credibility lies on borrowing,
since they are borrowing even more, the deficit
is increasing and people are suffering. When
the Prime Minister talks about children in
poverty in response to my question, I simply
remind her 4 million children are living in
poverty—children going hungry to school
in this country because their parents do not
have enough money to feed them properly. It
is a disgrace and should be addressed.
In the autumn statement last week, the Chancellor
spoke for over 50 minutes. During that time,
he did not once mention the national health
service or social care. Some 1.2 million people
are lacking the care they need. Why was there
not one single penny more for social care
in the autumn statement?
>>The Prime Minister: There is absolutely
no doubt that the social care system is under
pressure; we recognise that. If we just look
at the fact that there are 1 million more
people aged over 65 today than there were
in 2010, we see the sort of pressures on the
social care system. That is why the Government
have already acted to put more money into
the social care system: more money through
the better care fund—£3.5 billion extra
through the better care fund—and more money
through the social care precept. But it is
also important that local authorities and
the NHS work together to ensure, for example,
that people have the social care they need,
so they are not ending up blocking beds in
hospital. There is some very good practice
up and down the country, and sadly there is
some not so good practice. What we need to
do is make sure everybody is giving the best
possible service to people who need it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: There is a tragic parallel
going on between an underfunded NHS and an
underfunded social care system all over the
country, and the Prime Minister knows it.
Indeed, she might care to listen to the Tory
leader of Warwickshire Council, Izzi Seccombe,
who says that her council has been “cut
to the bone”, and who says on social care:
“right now we have a £1.3 billion gap which
is not being funded.”
It is a real crisis in every social services
department all over the country and, indeed,
in almost every NHS hospital.
Next year, this Government are handing back
£605 million in corporation tax cuts, rising
to £1.6 billion the year after that and £7.5
billion over the next five years. So could
the Prime Minister explain to the more than
1 million elderly people not getting the care
they need, to the 4 million people on NHS
waiting lists and to the millions of pensioners
worried about losing the protection of the
triple lock why there is not one penny extra
for the NHS or social care? Just what is this
Government’s real sense of priorities?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
talks about funding social care and funding
the national health service: £3.8 billion
extra is going into the national health service
this year. Under Labour’s plans, we would
have seen £1.3 billion less going into the
national health service. Social care funding
is going up under this Government. At the
last election, the shadow Chancellor—lately
of “Strictly” fame—said local authorities
would get not a penny more. Conservatives
are putting money into the NHS and social
care—Labour would deny it.
>>Seema Kennedy (South Ribble) (Con): On a
cross-party basis, Jo Cox and I were establishing
the National Commission on Loneliness when
she was brutally murdered. This work is now
being continued by the hon. Member for Leeds
West (Rachel Reeves) and me. Does my right
hon. Friend agree that loneliness is an issue
for all our communities, and will she urge
her Ministers to engage with the commission
as it carries out its work and reports next
year?
>>The Prime Minister: First of all, may I
just say that I am sure the whole House would
want to join me in commending Jo’s family
for the very dignified way in which they dealt
with matters as the court case was going through.
It must have been very harrowing for them.
I am very pleased that my hon. Friend and
the hon. Member for Leeds West (Rachel Reeves)
are taking forward the work of the commission
on loneliness. Earlier this week I was able
to support the “Good Morning Britain”
1 Million Minutes campaign, which is encouraging
individuals to give 30 minutes of their time
to help—to be with—somebody who is lonely.
We have, over the years, I think, failed to
understand the impact that loneliness has
on people’s psychological health but also
their physical health. Ministers will look
forward to receiving the results from the
commission and to working with my hon. Friend
and others.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): A very happy
St Andrew’s day to everybody celebrating
in Scotland and throughout the world.
There is literally nothing to celebrate about
the humanitarian catastrophe befalling the
people of Syria at this time. The situation
in the besieged city of Aleppo is described
as so bad that it
“could be one of the biggest massacres of
civilian population since World War II”.
What can the UK and the international community
do to end the suffering of the people of Syria?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
is right to draw attention to the appalling
situation in Syria, and particularly the indiscriminate
attacks that we see on civilians in Aleppo.
The United Kingdom has been working with France
to bring forward an emergency discussion on
this issue at the UN Security Council; that
will take place later today. We want to see
a cessation of hostilities. We want to see
an opportunity for humanitarian aid to have
access to Aleppo, and we will be pressing
for that at the Security Council.
>>Angus Robertson: It is extremely welcome
that the discussions are taking place in the
United Nations, and we wish success to all
those who are supporting a humanitarian solution
to the crisis. However, things are so bad
that the agencies are saying that in Aleppo
the situation is a “descent into hell”.
Time is absolutely of the essence. I know
the Prime Minister is seized of this matter;
we are in agreement. Can I please appeal to
her: can absolutely everything be done now
to alleviate the situation of the poor people
of Aleppo and of Syria?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
is right about the horrific situation in Aleppo.
I can assure him that the Government are pressing
hard and we are doing everything that we can
in relation to this. We have consistently
looked at what the possible solutions might
be, to see whether there are other avenues
that we can press for. I think the Security
Council debate is very important. There is
an important message to send to Russia: that
it use its influence with the Assad regime
to stop these appalling atrocities in Aleppo
and let humanitarian aid through.
>>Fiona Bruce (Congleton) (Con): Comments
this week by the equalities commissioners
about not being worried about talking about
Christmas at work were important, because
many Christians are now worried, even fearful,
about mentioning their faith in public. Will
the Prime Minister therefore join me in welcoming
the recent Lawyers’ Christian Fellowship
publication “Speak Up!”, which confirms
that in our country the legal rights of freedom
of religion and freedom of speech to speak
about one’s faith responsibly, respectfully
and without fear are as strong today as ever?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important issue which matters both to her
and me. I think the phrase that was used by
the Lawyers’ Christian Fellowship was “the
jealously guarded principle” of that ability
to speak freely, as she says, respectfully
and responsibly about one’s religion. I
am happy to welcome the publication of this
report and its findings. Of course, we are
now into the season of Advent. We have a very
strong tradition in this country of religious
tolerance and freedom of speech, and our Christian
heritage is something we can all be proud
of. I am sure we would all want to ensure
that people at work do feel able to speak
about their faith, and also feel able to speak
quite freely about Christmas.
>>Chris Bryant (Rhondda) (Lab): Thirty years
ago, I conducted my first funeral as a young
curate. It was for a young teenage boy who
was an enormous fan of Paul Simon, so, as
the crematorium curtains closed, we listened
to “The Sound of Silence”, and many people
cried. The average cost of a child’s funeral
today is £3,675. Some councils do not charge
anything, but some charge a lot, and the social
fund is means-tested. I ask again: will the
Prime Minister please listen to the words
of my hon. Friend the Member for Swansea East
(Carolyn Harris), sign up to her campaign
and put an end to both the means-testing and
the postcode lottery, so that no parents who
lose a child have to deal with the fear of
hardship as well as their grief?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
a very important point. I know that the hon.
Member for Swansea East (Carolyn Harris) spoke
very movingly from personal experience in
the debate that she called on this issue.
I do not think that anybody who has not been
through the death of a child can possibly
understand the pain that that brings, not
just immediately but thereafter, as parents
see others grow up while their child will
not.
I recognise the issue that the hon. Gentleman
has raised about the cost of children’s
funerals. As he has said, there are measures
in place for families who have particular
hardship cases, where money can be given.
It is open to local authorities to waive fees,
and some local authorities do that. We have
left this as a decision for local authorities,
and some do, indeed, waive those fees.
>>Kelly Tolhurst (Rochester and Strood) (Con):
Grammar schools across the Medway towns have
provided good education and opportunities
for hard-working young people from a range
of backgrounds, helping social mobility and
intervening to improve recent Ofsted results
in local primary schools, particularly in
Rochester and Strood. Does my right hon. Friend
agree that our current grammar schools’
contribution to education ought to be valued
and given every support, as part of the educational
mix up and down the country, to help children
to achieve their full potential?
>>The Prime Minister: I agree with my hon.
Friend. I believe that there are now nearly
11,000 more children in good and outstanding
schools in my hon. Friend’s area than there
were in 2010. We want to provide a good school
place for every child. She references the
good work being done by grammar schools in
her area to improve the quality of education
in primary schools, which is one of the issues
that we are looking at in our consultation
on education. We want to remove the legal
ban on expanding or opening new grammar schools,
but we also want to see grammar schools working
to improve standards across the education
system generally.
>>Margaret Greenwood (Wirral West) (Lab):
The sustainability and transformation plan
for Cheshire and Merseyside aims to develop
accountable care organisations. It is a model
from America, where it is used to deliver
private, insurance-based healthcare. Can the
Prime Minister assure me that STPs will not
be used as a means of introducing insurance-based
private healthcare into the NHS?
The Prime Minister
The STPs are about local people determining
the shape of health services in a local area,
to deliver the best service for local people.
Obviously, every area will be looking very
closely at the plans that are being brought
forward. It is important that we see, in those
STPs, health services increasingly working
with local authorities to ensure that they
are providing the right, holistic level of
care for people in their area.
>>Claire Perry (Devizes) (Con): As the Prime
Minister leads us towards a smart and smooth
Brexit—as I like to call it, a “smexit”—I
am sure she shares my view that the flexibility
of Britain’s labour market is one of this
country’s great strengths. However, she
will be aware that the growth of new business
models as part of the so-called gig economy
is causing real concern that employment rights
could be eroded. Indeed, the news that Uber
is seeking a licence to operate in my constituency
has left local people concerned about what
their jobs could look like in the future.
What reassurances can the Prime Minister give
to me and my constituents that the Government
are working to make sure that employment rights
and employment regulations keep pace with
this sort of innovation?
>>The Prime Minister: As I mentioned earlier,
we have seen a significant rise in the number
of people in employment in this country, and
that is because we have got the strong economy
that we have. However, I recognise that employment
and types of employment are changing. Technology
is the driver in many cases. That is why I
have asked the chief executive of the RSA,
Matthew Taylor, to conduct a review of and
report on modern employment practices, so
we can ensure that the legislative framework
is absolutely the right one for the economy
of the future and the jobs of the future.
That shows that it is now the Conservative
party that is the party of working people.
>>Stephen Timms (East Ham) (Lab): The Conservative
election manifesto promised to halve the disability
employment gap by 2020. Ministers justified
their plan to cut the benefit from next April
by promising to recycle some of the savings
into improving employment support for benefit
claimants. It has now become apparent that
funding for employment support is not being
increased; it is being cut. The target for
halving the gap—2020—has been completely
abandoned. Surely the only honourable course
now is for the Government to abandon the benefit
cut as well.
>>The Prime Minister: I am very pleased to
say that, over the past three years, nearly
600,000 more disabled people have got into
the workplace. I think that is very important.
Of course, we want to ensure that all those
disabled people who are able to get into work
are given the support needed to do that. That
is why we have been ensuring not just that
this is about benefits, but that this is about
the support package in total that people are
given. They do have individual support through
the personal independence payment for the
particular long-terms costs that they have
incurred because of their disability. It is
also the support package that is provided
to people in the work group in employment
and support allowance that enables them to
get into work. Nearly 600,000 more disabled
people in work—that is something the right
hon. Gentleman should be celebrating.
>>Mr Peter Lilley (Hitchin and Harpenden)
(Con): I welcome my right hon. Friend’s
eagerness to give EU citizens living and working
lawfully in this country the assurance that
they will be able to remain here after Brexit
and to obtain reassurances for British citizens
living and working in the EU. Does she therefore
share my disappointment that Mr Tusk, in response
to a letter from 80 Members of this House
about resolving this issue speedily, has intransigently
put EU processes ahead of common humanity?
>>The Prime Minister: I can assure my right
hon. Friend that, as I said earlier, I would
hope this is an issue we can look at at an
early stage in the negotiations, and off course
there will be two years of negotiations. I
think it is right that we want to give reassurance
to British citizens living in the EU and to
EU citizens living here in the UK, but I think
the reaction that we have seen shows why it
was absolutely right for us not to do what
the Labour party wanted us to do, which was
simply to give away the guarantee for rights
of EU citizens here in the UK. As we have
seen, that would have left UK citizens in
Europe high and dry.
>>Mr Stephen Hepburn (Jarrow) (Lab): I know
the Prime Minister is handed happy briefs
to read out, but can I tell her that she has
been wrong on the national health service
for weeks now? If she came to South Tyneside
hospital, she would see services closing,
she would see patients worried and she would
see staff demoralised, so when is she going
to get a grip of those bean counters who are
committing criminal damage on the people’s
cherished service in her name?
>>The Prime Minister: There are nearly 30
more doctors and over 950 more nurses in the
South Tyneside NHS Foundation Trust compared
with 2010. This year, the South Tyneside clinical
commissioning group will be getting increased
funding. Health funding in the hon. Gentleman’s
area is going to be £2.7 billion this year,
and that will be increasing by 2020-21. It
is this Government that are putting more money
into the national health service; it is the
Labour party—a former shadow Health Secretary
from the Labour party—who said that more
money for the NHS was “irresponsible”.
>>Chris White (Warwick and Leamington) (Con):
Warwick and Leamington contains many of the
elements of a successful industrial strategy—great
schools, a skilled workforce, strong infrastructure,
manufacturing, creative industries and being
surrounded by world-class research and development
facilities, to name but a few. Will the Prime
Minister outline the Government’s progress
in developing this policy, which is so important
to our nation’s prosperity?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right in what he says about his own constituency
and the midlands engine in relation to the
development of jobs and for the strong economy
of the future. That is why we will be developing
the industrial strategy for the whole of the
United Kingdom, which is an important part
of the Government’s plan for the future.
It is looking at issues such as infrastructure
and skills, ensuring that we can build on
the best and encourage the growth that we
need for the economy of the future. The midlands
engine and the part of the country that my
hon. Friend represents will be an important
part of that growth for the future.
>>Kirsten Oswald (East Renfrewshire) (SNP):
Guests from the Hyderabad diocese have twice
been refused visas to visit the Church of
Scotland presbytery of Glasgow as part of
a twinning initiative, the suggestion being
that the visit was not genuine, despite the
paperwork being correct and the Church bearing
the costs. When I raised this with the Leader
of the House, he spoke of the need for people
to return home after visits, and then the
Immigration Minister told me in a patronising
letter how to apply for a visa. Will the Prime
Minister tell the Church why its visitors
are not welcome and what messages she thinks
it sends to our faith communities?
>>The Prime Minister: We have a very clear
visa system, and decisions are taken according
to its rules, but as the hon. Lady will have
seen, the Home Secretary has heard her comments.
I suggest that if she sends her the details,
she will look at the case.
>>Suella Fernandes (Fareham) (Con): Does my
right hon. Friend agree that, once the will
of the British people, including the residents
of Fareham, is delivered and we break free
from the shackles of the EU, Britain stands
to benefit from the fantastic opportunity
to forge new trade deals with countries such
as India and the USA, and will she meet me
and members of the Legatum Institute special
trade commission, which has projected a 50%
increase in global world product over 15 years
as a result of Brexit, which will enable trade
to boost jobs, growth and hope?
>>The Prime Minister: I am interested in the
results of the Legatum Institute commission’s
report on this issue. I believe absolutely
that free trade is the right way to go—it
is through free trade that we increase growth
and prosperity—which is why I have said
I want this country to be a global leader
in free trade and why we will not just look
to forge new trade deals with other countries
as we leave the EU but see how we can improve
trade with other countries before we leave
it, so that we will continue to strengthen
our economy. I am sure that the Secretary
of State for International Trade will be happy
to meet my hon. Friend to discuss the results
of the commission’s report.
>>Mr Speaker: I warmly welcome the hon. Member
for Blyth Valley (Mr Campbell) back to his
place.
>>Mr Ronnie Campbell (Blyth Valley) (Lab):
Thank you, Mr Speaker. I’ll be able to tell
you more about it next week, when I meet my
consultant.
What plans does the Prime Minister have to
make super-economic zones? The Blyth estuary
was given an economic zone by the last Tory
Chancellor, as we have acres and acres of
land around that river. I hope that that is
in her mind.
>>The Prime Minister: I join you, Mr Speaker,
and others in welcoming the hon. Gentleman
to his place. It is good to see him back in
his usual position, and I wish him all the
very best.
As part of our industrial strategy, we are
looking around the country at where there
are opportunities for economic growth and
how we can encourage them to be taken up.
It is important that economic growth and prosperity
be spread across the whole country to ensure
an economy that works for everyone.
>>Stuart Andrew (Pudsey) (Con): The digital
and creative industry is an important part
of the UK economy, and Leeds is an important
hub in the sector. In welcoming the £1 billion
investment in better broadband in the autumn
statement, may I urge my right hon. Friend
to ensure that Yorkshire gets its fair share,
so that we can build on this success and make
Leeds the capital of this industry?
>>The Prime Minister: I assure my hon. Friend
that I recognise the role played by the creative
and digital industries in our economy, the
excellent example of Leeds and the vibrancy
they bring to the economy there. I am pleased
that we are able to invest a further £1 billion
in gold standard broadband, which will bring
better connections to 2 million more homes
and businesses, and I am sure that Yorkshire
will have a very central role to play in this.
>>Mr David Lammy (Tottenham) (Lab): Yesterday,
the Prime Minister’s Government published
a Green Paper on corporate governance, emphasising
the importance of gender and race diversity.
I congratulate her on that, but why has her
Secretary of State for Culture, Media and
Sport blocked the appointment of a black woman
to the Channel 4 board? Does she not think
there is a woman or a black person in the
country worthy of being on the board of Channel
4?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank the right hon.
Gentleman for the welcome he has given to
the corporate governance Green Paper that
we have produced, which of course covers a
great deal more than simply issues of gender
and diversity in corporate governance and
on corporate boards. I am not aware of the
particular case that he mentioned. In looking
at public appointments, however, I would say
that a very careful process is undertaken
to ensure that the people who are appointed
have the skillset and the requirements needed
to carry out the role. I will look into the
issue he raised, but this is always a question
of the right person for the job. Issues around
the sort of question that he has raised do
not come into it; it is about who is right
for the job.
>>Michael Tomlinson (Mid Dorset and North
Poole) (Con): Mr Donald Tusk’s response
to my letter on reciprocal rights has already
been mentioned. I congratulate the Prime Minister
on her work with individual member states
in this important matter, but does she share
our disappointment and will she join me in
calling for this important matter to be raised
in two weeks’ time at the next European
Council meeting?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the concerns
of my hon. Friend and other Members on the
particular issue of the rights of EU citizens
and UK citizens variously living here in the
UK and in the other member states of the European
Union. I hope it is something that we will
be able to address at an early stage. We have
not yet triggered article 50 and the negotiations
will have up to two years to run, as set out
in the Lisbon treaty. As I say, I hope we
will be able to address this at an early stage
to give people the reassurance they need.
>>Hannah Bardell (Livingston) (SNP): A year
ago this week, my constituent Deborah Pearson
lost her niece Julie, who is believed to have
been unlawfully killed in Eilat, Israel. A
year ago, the Prime Minister’s predecessor
was good enough to give me support, as was
the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, but after
a year of writing letters, having meetings
and putting pressure on the Israeli authorities,
the family is no closer to having justice
for Julie. Will the Prime Minister meet me
and my constituent to understand what further
pressure can be brought to bear so that the
family can get answers and understand who
brought this terrible crime against their
family member?
>>The Prime Minister: I understand the concern
that the hon. Lady rightly shows for her constituent,
and obviously her constituent’s deep concern
to find out what happened in this terrible
tragedy. I understand that the appropriate
Minister in the Foreign Office is actively
working on this question. I will ask him to
respond to the hon. Lady and to meet her to
discuss what more can be done and to set out
exactly what the Foreign Office is doing on
this issue.