>>Mrs Sheryll Murray (South East Cornwall)
(Con): If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 8 March.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
am sure that Members across the House will
wish to join me in marking International Women’s
Day, as we celebrate the social, economic,
cultural and political achievements of women
both here and around the world. We are also
redoubling our efforts to tackle the problems
that women all too often still face.
This morning, I had meetings with Ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in this House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Mrs Murray: I join the Prime Minister in
celebrating International Women’s Day. Since
2010, Conservatives in government have a proud
record of protecting and supporting both the
victims and those at risk of domestic violence
and abuse. I saw that myself when I visited
my local police, and I thank them for the
difficult job that they do. The evil is that
far too many women are still at risk and are
still suffering. What more can the Prime Minister
do to tackle this abhorrent crime?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
a serious issue. It is one in which I have
taken a particular personal interest, and
I attach great importance to the issue. Tackling
domestic violence and abuse is a key priority
for the Government. What we have already done
in government has the potential to transform
the way in which we think about and tackle
these terrible crimes when they take place.
We have already committed to bringing forward
new legislation, and I have confirmed today
an additional £20 million to support organisations
working to tackle domestic violence and abuse.
This means that the total funding available
for our strategy to end violence against women
and girls will be over £100 million in this
Parliament.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): May
I start by wishing all women a very happy
International Women’s Day today? I am proud
that the Labour party has more women MPs than
all other parties in this House combined and
a shadow Cabinet of which half the members
are women.
A month ago, I raised the question of the
leaked texts between the leader of Surrey
County Council and Government officials about
social care. The Prime Minister’s response
was to accuse me of peddling “alternative
facts”. Will she explain the difference
between a sweetheart deal and a gentleman’s
agreement?
>>The Prime Minister: First, the right hon.
Gentleman references women in this House,
and I point out to him that, actually, the
Conservative party has recently taken a further
measure in relation to women in this House
by replacing a Labour male MP with a female
Conservative.
The right hon. Gentleman asks about the issue
in relation to Surrey County Council. The
substance of what he asks is whether there
has been a particular deal with Surrey County
Council that is not available to other councils,
and the answer is no. As I have said before,
the ability to raise a social care precept
of 3% is available to every council. The ability
to retain 100% of business rates will be available
to a number of councils in April. Let us look
at them: Liverpool, Manchester and London.
What do we know about those councils? They
are all under Labour control. So what he is
actually asking me is why a Conservative council
should have access to an arrangement that
is predominantly currently available to Labour
councils.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was about the
arrangement between the Government and Surrey
County Council. A recording has now emerged
showing that the leader of Surrey County Council,
David Hodge, said that there was a “gentleman’s
agreement” between him and the Government
that meant that the council would not have
to go ahead with a referendum. My question
is: what deal was done with Surrey County
Council? There is an acute social care crisis
affecting every council, with £4.6 billion
of cuts made to social care since 2010. Can
the Prime Minister tell every other council
in England what gentleman’s agreement is
available for them?
>>The Prime Minister: On today of all days,
if the right hon. Gentleman could just be
a little patient and wait half an hour for
the Budget, he will find out what social care
funding is available to all councils. If he
is asking me whether there was a special deal
for Surrey that was not available to other
councils, the answer is no. If he is looking
to uncover a conspiracy, I suggest he looks
behind him.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: If all the arrangements are
so clear and above board, will the Prime Minister
place in the Library of the House a record
of all one-to-one meetings between the Secretary
of State for Communities and Local Government
and the Chancellor and any council leader
or chair of social services anywhere in England?
If there is no special deal, can she explain
why Surrey is the only county council to be
allowed into the business rates retention
pilot when it has been denied to others?
>>The Prime Minister: The business rates retention
pilot will come into force for a number of
councils this April, and that includes, as
I have already said, Liverpool, Greater Manchester,
Greater London and others. In 2019-20, it
will be available to 100% of councils. Councils
will be able to apply to be part of a further
pilot in 2018-19, and that goes for all councils
across the country.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The text said that there
was a memorandum of understanding, and the
Prime Minister said that there was no deal.
She is now unclear about that. Did she actually
know what arrangement was made with Surrey
County Council? She is not keen to answer
questions about that.
There is another area of deep concern across
the whole country. Can the Prime Minister
tell us how many new school places will be
needed by 2020?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
really should listen to the answers I give
before he asks the next question. He said
I did not answer the question about a special
deal for Surrey; I think that I have now answered
it three times, but I shall do it a fourth
time: there was no special deal for Surrey
that was not available to other councils.
>>Jeremy Corbyn The Prime Minister was also
asked just a moment ago about the number of
new school places needed by 2020. Perhaps
she could explain why we have a crisis in
school places and class sizes are soaring,
thanks to her Government. What is the answer
on the number of new school places needed,
Prime Minister?
>>The Prime Minister: This Government have
a policy that is about not only increasing
the number of school places but doing more
than that. I want to increase the number of
good school places, so that every child has
an opportunity to go to a good school. That
is what the money we are putting into education
is about. It includes money for new free schools,
which will be faith schools, university schools,
comprehensives, grammar schools and maths
schools. There will be a diversity, because
what I want is a good school place for every
child and for parents to have a choice. What
the right hon. Gentleman wants is for parents
to take what they are given, good or bad.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The National Audit Office
tells us that a very large number of new school
places are needed—420,000. Nothing the Prime
Minister has said gets anywhere near to that.
Instead, she proposes a flagship scheme to
build the wrong schools in the wrong places,
spending millions on vanity projects such
as grammar schools and free schools, while
at the same time per-pupil funding is falling
in real terms. Is it not time that this colossal
waste of money was addressed? It is doing
nothing to help the vast majority of children
and nothing to solve the crisis of school
places and soaring class sizes. That is what
every parent wants, not vanity projects from
her Government.
>>The Prime Minister: It is no vanity project
to want every child to have a good school
place. The majority of free schools that have
been opened have been in areas where there
is a need for school places, and the majority
have been opened in areas of disadvantage,
where they are helping the very children we
want to see have the opportunity to get on
in life. I have to say to the right hon. Gentleman
that this is about a fairer society. On this
Budget day, we see that we are securing the
economy; Labour want to weaken it. We are
working for a fairer society; Labour oppose
every single reform. We are fighting for the
best deal for Britain; Labour are fighting
among themselves. That is Labour: weak, divided
and unfit to govern this great country.
>>Maggie Throup (Erewash) (Con): This week
in Erewash, it is likely that, sadly, four
people will suffer a stroke. With that in
mind and given that the current highly successful
stroke strategy expires later this year, will
my right hon. Friend commit her Government
to publish an updated strategy that includes
advances in stroke treatments, such as mechanical
thrombectomy, which dramatically improves
outcomes for one in 10 patients?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend has raised
an important issue. I assure her that the
NHS wants to continue to build on the successes
of the current stroke strategy. We all recognise
that there have been huge improvements in
stroke care over the past decade, and we want
to deliver our ambition for truly world-leading
care. On the particular treatment to which
she refers, I understand that the NHS has
already approved the use of mechanical clot
retrieval in specific cases. The NHS rigorously
audits the quality of stroke care throughout
the country, so that we can ensure we are
delivering on our commitments. We have some
of the fastest improvements in hospital recovery
rate for strokes and heart attacks in Europe.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): On International
Women’s Day, we wish all campaigners for
equality well, including those from the Women
Against State Pension Inequality Campaign.
The cross-party Brexit Committee has recommended
that the UK must guarantee the status of EU
nationals living in the UK and act unilaterally,
if necessary. The Committee went on to say:
“The current process for consideration of
permanent residency applications is not fit
for purpose and, in the absence of any concrete
resolution to relieve the anxiety felt by
the estimated three million EU citizens resident
in the UK, it is untenable to continue with
the system as it stands.”
Given the massive positive contribution that
European nationals make to this country, what
concrete plans does the Prime Minister have
to deal with this matter?
>>The Prime Minister: As the right hon. Gentleman
knows, we want to have an early agreement
that will enable us to guarantee the status
of EU citizens living in the UK, but also
we need to guarantee the status of UK citizens
living in the European Union. On the process
of application, the Home Office is looking
at that and at how it can improve the systems
and simplify them, which is something that
it regularly does.
>>Angus Robertson: Since 2010, the Home Office
has seen its full-time equivalent staff cut
by 10%, so, at current rates of processing
applications for permanent residency, it would
take the Home Office more than 50 years to
deal with 3.2 million European nationals living
in the UK. That is clearly totally and utterly
unacceptable. Will the Prime Minister tell
us how quickly she hopes to be able to guarantee
all European nationals permanent residency?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
cannot just stand up and say that because
the Home Office is getting more efficient,
it will take longer for answers to be given.
Yes, the Home Office is getting more efficient
at dealing with these things. I do not know
whether he has ever heard about technology,
but these days people apply online and they
are dealt with online.
>>Chris Green (Bolton West) (Con): Following
the recent findings of a study of terror convictions
in Britain, it is clear that there are serious
problems with how communities integrate into
society and a danger that that lack of integration
leads to acts of terror. Will the Prime Minister
update the House on the Government’s counter-extremism
strategy and response to these findings?
>>The Prime Minister: Again, this is a very
serious issue that my hon. Friend has raised.
The Government are taking a comprehensive
approach to tackling terrorism and violent
extremism at source, but also, through our
counter-extremism strategy, we are looking
at extremism more widely. We want to defeat
not just terrorism and violent extremism but
extremism wherever it occurs. We will shortly
be publishing a new counter-terrorism strategy.
In the coming months, we will be responding
to Dame Louise Casey’s report on integration.
That is backed up by additional investment
in our security and intelligence agencies—£2.5
billion over five years—and I am clear that
the Government are doing everything they can
to tackle issues around integration, extremism
and terrorism.
>>Tracy Brabin (Batley and Spen) (Lab): I
come from a Westminster Hall debate on behalf
of my young constituent Sam, who is 11 years
old. He developed narcolepsy as a result of
receiving the Pandemrix vaccine to protect
him from the swine flu. Sam’s mum, Di, is
in the Public Gallery today. In these rare
and devastating cases, the link between Pandemrix
and narcolepsy is proven, yet families like
Di’s face long legal battles with the Government.
Will the Prime Minister today promise that
no more of these disabled children will be
hounded through the courts, apologise to the
families concerned and oversee payments to
support the children’s long-term care needs?
>>The Prime Minister: May I first congratulate
the hon. Lady on securing a Westminster Hall
debate on this important topic? At the end
of her question, she refers to the issue of
payments. I am sure she realises that the
vaccine damage payment scheme is not a compensation
scheme, but a one-off tax-free lump sum that
is paid to help to ease the burden of those
who are disabled as a result of vaccination,
and it is part of a range of support that
is provided. She has raised a very specific
case. Obviously she has had that Westminster
Hall debate, but we want to ensure that the
process is open and fair at every stage. The
Department for Work and Pensions does look
at every claim based on its own facts. If
she wants to write with the details, I am
sure that my hon. Friend the Minister for
Disabled People, Health and Work will look
into the specific case that she has raised.
>>Michael Fabricant (Lichfield) (Con): What
recent assessment she has made of the (a)
performance of the economy and (b) adequacy
of provision of public services in the Midlands
Engine region; and if she will make a statement.
>>The Prime Minister: Although I will not
speculate on the statement that my right hon.
Friend the Chancellor will make very shortly,
I can assure my hon. Friend that the fundamentals
of our economy are strong. Since 2010, employment
in the west midlands has risen by 215,000
and private sector employment alone grew by
80,000 in the past year. We have also seen
schools and police budgets being protected,
and more doctors and nurses in his local hospitals.
>>Michael Fabricant (Lichfield) (Con): And
of course we have also witnessed the post-Brexit
vote of confidence from Nissan, Boeing and
Dyson investing in other parts of the country,
but will my right hon. Friend say a little
bit more about firms like Jaguar Land Rover
in the west midlands?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to say to
my hon. Friend that in the wider sense, of
course, our plans for the midlands engine
show that we want an economy that works for
everyone. We have already confirmed over £330
million in the growth deal funding and money
is going into the midlands engine investment
fund and the Birmingham rail hub, but it is
also important to recognise the investment
that is being made in the UK by companies
like Jaguar Land Rover, which will be building
its new Range Rover model in Solihull. That
is very good news for the west midlands and
also for the British economy. It is a sign
of the confidence that Jaguar Land Rover has
in the UK for the future.
>>Gordon Marsden (Blackpool South) (Lab):
My Blackpool casework is now full of the anxieties
that the DWP and the Home Office are imposing
on vulnerable constituents, including officials’
attempts to overturn tribunal decisions protecting
benefits and residents. That includes a family
settled here for eight years and a man with
a severe brain injury. If the Prime Minister
wants people to respect the idea that “Brexit
means Brexit,” should she not respect the
idea that tribunals mean tribunals and not
try to block them with grubby regulations
affecting 164,000 disabled people?
>>The Prime Minister: If the hon. Gentleman
is referring to the decision that has been
taken in relation to the courts and personal
independence payments, as I explained to the
House last week, and as has been explained
by the Secretary of State, this is about restoring
the system to the state that was intended
when Parliament agreed it. It was agreed by
the coalition Government and by Parliament
after extensive consultation.
>>Mark Menzies (Fylde) (Con): In National
Apprenticeship Week, it is important to recognise
this Government’s commitment to investment,
apprenticeships and skills. Will the Prime
Minister look at encouraging a greater commitment
to degree apprenticeships as part of the Government’s
strategy, as championed by businesses in my
constituency such as BAE Systems, which has
been at the forefront in developing these
new programmes through its engineering degree
apprenticeship scheme?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
a very important issue. As we look to the
future, we want to ensure that people here
in the UK have the skills they need for the
economy of the future, and degree apprenticeships
will be an important part of that. Companies
such as BAE System, which he referred to specifically,
have been right at the forefront of developing
these new programmes. I am pleased to say
that the apprenticeship levy will take the
total investment in England to £2.45 billion,
which is double what was spent in 2010. That
means more opportunities for young people
to gain the skills they need for their future.
>>Dan Jarvis (Barnsley Central) (Lab): Tomorrow
a memorial will be unveiled to those men and
women who served our country in Afghanistan
and Iraq. Does the Prime Minister agree that
we should all pay tribute to their service
and commemorate their sacrifice, not just
with a memorial but with a commitment to learn
from the past and do better in the future?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
a very important point. The unveiling of the
memorial will be a very significant ceremony.
I think that all of us across this House should
pay tribute to those recognised by the memorial
for the sacrifice they made—those in our
armed forces and all those civilians who worked
to deliver aid, healthcare and education.
It is important that we recognise the sacrifices
made by our armed forces and also by their
families. That will be a significant moment
tomorrow. We are very clear that we do need
to learn lessons from the past, and that is
exactly what we will do.
>>Johnny Mercer (Plymouth, Moor View) (Con):
I was delighted by the Prime Minister’s
intervention in mental health in January,
which I still feel has not had the attention
it deserves. In Plymouth we are completely
reconfiguring our mental health services,
because we understand that parity of esteem
means nothing without parity of provision.
Will the Prime Minister visit Plymouth to
see some of the pioneering work that we are
doing, perhaps during national Mental Health
Awareness Week in May, when I am hoping that
Plymouth will take a national lead?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend,
because I know that this is an issue that
he has championed and that is very close to
his area of concern—he has done a lot of
work on mental health. He talks about parity
of esteem, which the Government have introduced,
which is very important. More money is going
into mental health provision than ever before.
I would certainly be delighted to see the
work being done in Plymouth, provided my diary
allows for that.
>>Julie Cooper (Burnley) (Lab): In my constituency
of Burnley, primary and secondary schools
are severely underfunded, and maintained nursery
schools are struggling to survive. Why, then,
at a time when we cannot adequately fund the
schools we already have, is the Prime Minister
suggesting spending millions of pounds to
create new grammar schools that will help
only a minority of children? That is unfair
as a new funding formula, and will do nothing
to help social mobility.
>>The Prime Minister: Let us be clear about
what the Government have done. Record amounts
of funding are going into education. It was
a Conservative-led Government that introduced
the pupil premium and it is a Conservative
Government that has protected the core schools
budget. The new money that will be going into
schools as a result of today’s announcements
is not about a return to a binary system of
grammar schools and secondary moderns. That
is not what we are going to do. What we are
doing is ensuring that there is a diversity
of provision—so, yes, some grammar schools,
but also comprehensives, faith schools, university
schools and maths schools. I want a good school
place for every child and, more than that,
the right school place for every child.
>>Amanda Milling (Cannock Chase) (Con): On
this International Women’s Day, it is absolutely
fantastic that we have the highest female
employment rate and the highest percentage
of women on FTSE 100 boards on record, that
the gender pay gap is at the lowest on record,
and that we have an amazing female Prime Minister.
However, I am sure the Prime Minister will
agree that there is still much more to do,
particularly in supporting women back to work
after a career break. Will my right hon. Friend
outline what more the Government are going
to do to level the playing field?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for her question. When I stood on the steps
of Downing Street back in July and talked
about a country that works for everyone, I
meant that. That is why we are taking a number
of measures, including on International Women’s
Day today. We are setting up a new fund to
help mothers returning to work after a long
career break. Returnships are important. They
are open to men and women, but we should all
recognise that the majority of those who take
time out of a career are women who devote
themselves to motherhood for a period. Getting
back into employment is often very difficult
for them; they find that it is closed off.
That is why, as well as making economic sense,
it is right and fair for those women that
we provide for returnships to enable them
to get back into the workplace.
>>Yasmin Qureshi (Bolton South East) (Lab):
Everyone agrees that early years education
is crucial for the welfare and future of our
children. However, nurseries in my constituency
tell me that the funding for 30 hours of free
childcare is not sufficient, and many of them
will be forced to close. What steps will the
Prime Minister take to ensure that those nurseries
do not close?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady talks
about the 30 hours that is being introduced,
but let us look at what we are doing on childcare.
We have already introduced 15 hours of free
childcare a week for all three and four-year-olds,
15 hours of free childcare a week for disadvantaged
two-year-olds, help with up to 70% of childcare
costs for people on low incomes, and shared
parental leave. We will spend a record £6
billion on childcare support by the end of
this Parliament. That is a Conservative Government,
and it is Conservatives in Government who
have a record of supporting parents with childcare
needs.
>>Alec Shelbrooke (Elmet and Rothwell) (Con):
Does my right hon. Friend agree that it is
indefensible for the Labour police and crime
commissioner in West Yorkshire to be raising
the council tax precept when he has £120
million in reserves and underspent this year’s
budget by £4 million?
>>The Prime Minister: As my hon. Friend knows,
it is of course for the directly elected police
and crime commissioner for West Yorkshire
to decide what to do about the police precept
of council tax, as it is in every area that
has a police and crime commissioner, but I
would always encourage those commissioners
to look at ways to introduce efficiencies
into their forces before looking to increase
local taxes. Over the past six years, we have
seen that police forces can find sensible
savings and reduce crime at the same time.
>>Geraint Davies (Swansea West) (Lab/Co-op):
Mr Speaker, you will know that the Royal College
of Physicians has found that 40,000 people
die prematurely each year from diesel pollution,
at a cost of £20 billion to the economy,
and that YouGov has found that 45% of diesel
drivers are willing to switch, given the right
scrappage or tax incentive schemes. Will the
Prime Minister commit today to a fiscal strategy
and a new clean air Act to put us on a new,
cleaner, healthier trajectory and to take
global leadership, rather than being dragged
into the courts to fulfil basic EU air quality
standards?
>>The Prime Minister: As the hon. Gentleman
will know, we are looking at the measures
that we need to introduce to improve air quality.
There have been improvements in recent years,
but we do need to go further, and that is
what the Government are looking at across
Departments, obviously with the Department
for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs paying
most attention to that, because that is within
its remit. We will be bringing forward proposals
on air quality in due course.
>>Victoria Atkins (Louth and Horncastle) (Con):
International Women’s Day is a chance to
reflect on how Governments and democracies
across the world serve women. Will my right
hon. Friend confirm that, when it comes to
female Prime Ministers, it is 2:0 to the Conservatives?
>>The Prime Minister: I am grateful to my
hon. Friend for having pointed that out, which
I refrained from doing earlier in response
to questions. I think it is very telling that
the Labour party spends a lot of time talking
about rights for women, giving support to
women and getting women on, whereas it is
the Conservative party that is the party in
this House that has provided two female Prime
Ministers.
>>Deidre Brock (Edinburgh North and Leith)
(SNP): Will the Prime Minister give an undertaking
that any new Scotland Act will be drafted
only after full consultation with the people
of Scotland and with the consent of the Scottish
Parliament?
>>The Prime Minister: I am not sure whether
the hon. Lady is referring to discussions
that are currently taking place about the
powers that might be available to the devolved
Administrations once we have left the European
Union, but she knows full well that we undertake
full discussions with the Scottish Government
on measures that are reserved matters and
on measures where we are negotiating on behalf
of the whole of the United Kingdom.
>>Simon Hoare (North Dorset) (Con): Crowdcomms,
a business in my constituency, operates out
of the small market town of Sturminster Newton;
it also has offices in Seattle and Sydney.
It employs 24 people, providing high-quality
IT jobs, and it avails itself of high-tech,
fast rural broadband and mobile telephone
communication. That is the recipe for growing
our rural economy. Will my right hon. Friend
undertake to ensure that her Government do
all they can to fill the blackspots in our
rural areas?
>>The Prime Minister: I can assure my hon.
Friend that we very much want to ensure that
we are doing that. My right hon. Friend the
Secretary of State for Culture, Media and
Sport is looking at our digital strategy and
ensuring that broadband is available in rural
areas and, indeed, at good speeds in other
areas, which might be less rural than my hon.
Friend’s constituency.
>>Mr Speaker: Finally, Mr Tim Farron. [Interruption.]
Order. I do not know whether Members are cheering
because it is “finally” or because of
the popularity of the hon. Gentleman, but
he is going to be heard.
>>Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
You are all so very and characteristically
kind.
On International Women’s Day, we stand with
women and girls across the world and note
with resolve that we must not take for granted
the progress we have made towards equality
over the last few decades.
Yesterday, we heard that hundreds of families
of soldiers who died in Iraq and Afghanistan
have been denied seats at tomorrow’s unveiling
of the memorial to our fallen troops. Inviting
a relative of each of those killed in Iraq
and Afghanistan would have taken up fewer
than a third of the 2,500 seats at that event.
Will the Prime Minister now apologise to those
families for what I assume is a careless oversight
and rectify that mistake immediately so that
bereaved families can come and pay their respects
to their fallen loved ones?
>>The Prime Minister: May I reassure the hon.
Gentleman that charities and groups representing
the bereaved were asked to put forward names
of attendees, and we look forward to welcoming
them so that we can publicly acknowledge the
sacrifice that their loved ones made on our
behalf? Over half of those attending tomorrow
are actually current or former members of
the armed forces. No one from the bereaved
community has been turned away, and everyone
who has applied to attend has been successful,
but I have been reassured that if there are
any bereaved families who wish to attend,
the Ministry of Defence will make every effort
to ensure that they are able to do so.