>> John Mann (Bassetlaw) (Lab):
If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 22 March.
>> The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May):
I would like to express my condolences to
the family and colleagues of the former Deputy
First Minister of Northern Ireland, Martin
McGuinness. Of course, we do not condone or
justify the path he took in the earlier part
of his life, and we should never forget that,
or the victims of terrorism. However, as my
noble Friend Lord Trimble set out yesterday,
he played an indispensable role in bringing
the republican movement away from violence
to peaceful and democratic means and to building
a better Northern Ireland.
This morning, I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in this House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>> John Mann:
The Prime Minister says that there is more
money for the national health service, more
nurses and more doctors, yet Bassetlaw breastcare
unit has been cut back and Bassetlaw children’s
ward has been closed overnight. Something,
clearly, does not add up. Therefore, the mothers
of the most seriously ill children, who use
the children’s ward the most frequently,
and I offer to work with the Prime Minister
to solve this problem. Is her door at No.
10 open to us?
>> The Prime Minister:
If we look at what has happened in the hon.
Gentleman’s area, we see that his NHS Bassetlaw
clinical commissioning group is receiving
a cash increase, and that the Doncaster and
Bassetlaw Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust has
80 more doctors and nearly 30 more nurses.
He talks of listening to the voice of local
people in relation to health services in the
local area, but that is exactly what the sustainability
and transformation plans are about—hearing
from local people and local clinicians, and
putting together the health provisions that
ensure they meet local needs.
>> Lucy Allan (Telford) (Con):
Telford is a story of transformation and progress.
From the ironmasters of the first industrial
revolution through to a new revolution in
high-tech manufacturing at Telford’s T54
today, it has helped to build Britain. As
the Government deliver on the democratic will
of the British people and trigger article
50, will my right hon. Friend tell us how
Telford will prosper from Brexit and from
her plan for Britain?
>> The Prime Minister:
As I have said before, the referendum result
was not just about membership of the EU; it
was a vote to change the way that this country
works, and who it works for, forever, to make
Britain a country that works for everyone,
not just the privileged few. That is why the
plan for Britain is a plan to get the right
deal for Britain abroad, but also to build
a stronger, fairer Britain for ordinary working
families here at home, like those in Telford.
I am pleased that we have already provided
£17 million of funding to The Marches local
enterprise partnership to improve local infrastructure
in Telford. This Government are putting those
resources in, and our plan for Britain will
deliver that stronger, fairer economy and
a more united and more outward-looking country
than ever before.
>> Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab):
I start by echoing the words of the Prime
Minister concerning the death of Martin McGuinness,
the former Deputy First Minister of Northern
Ireland. He died this week, and our thoughts
go to his family, his wife Bernie and the
wider community. Martin played an immeasurable
role in bringing about peace in Northern Ireland,
and it is that peace that we all want to see
endure for all time for all people in Northern
Ireland. This Government are cutting the schools
budget by 6.5% by 2020, and today we learn
that the proposed national funding formula
will leave 1,000 schools across England facing
additional cuts of a further 7% beyond 2020.
Can the Prime Minister explain to parents
why cutting capital gains tax, cutting inheritance
tax, cutting corporation tax and cutting the
bank levy are all more important than our
children’s future?
>> The Prime Minister:
This Government are committed to ensuring
that all our children get the education that
is right for them and that all our children
have a good school place. That is what the
Government’s plans for education will provide.
That is building on a fine record of the past
six and a half—nearly seven—years of Conservatives
in government, when we have seen 1.8 million
more children in good or outstanding schools.
We have protected the schools budget. The
national funding formula is under consultation,
and obviously there will be a number of views.
The consultation closes today and the Department
for Education will respond to it in due course.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
The manifesto on which the Prime Minister
fought the last election promised:
“Under a future Conservative Government,
the amount of money following your child into
school will be protected.”
No wonder even the editor of the London Evening
Standard is up in arms about this. The cut
to school funding equates to the loss of two
teachers across all primary schools and six
teachers across all secondary schools. So
is the Prime Minister advocating larger class
sizes, a shorter school day, or unqualified
teachers? Which is it?
>> The Prime Minister:
We have, as I said, protected the schools
budgets. We now see more teachers in our schools
and more teachers with first-class degrees
in our schools. As I say, we see 1.8 million
more children in good or outstanding schools.
That is a result of this Government’s policies
of diversity in education: free schools, academies,
comprehensives, faith schools, university
schools, grammar schools. We believe in diversity
in education and choice for parents; the right
hon. Gentleman believes in a one-size-fits-all,
take-it-or-leave-it model.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
The Prime Minister was clearly elected on
a pledge not to cut school funding, yet that
is exactly what is happening. Maybe she could
listen to headteachers in West Sussex who
say they believe that savings will come from
“staffing reductions, further increased
class sizes, withdrawal of counselling and
pastoral services, modified school hours,
reduction in books, IT and equipment.” I
have a heartfelt letter from a primary school
teacher by the name of Eileen. Eileen is one
of our many hard-working teachers who cares
for her kids, and she wrote to me to say:
“Teachers are purchasing items such as pens,
pencils, glue sticks and paper out of their
own pockets. Fundraising events have quadrupled,
as funds are so low that parents are having
to make donations to purchase books! This
is disgraceful.”
Does the Prime Minister agree with Eileen?
>> The Prime Minister:
We are seeing record levels of funding going
into our schools. We have protected the schools
budget; we have protected the pupil premium.
But what matters for parents is the quality
of education—
>> Hon. Members:
What about Eileen?
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. People should not keep yelling out,
“What about Eileen?” The Prime Minister
is giving her response to the Leader of the
Opposition, including the references to Eileen.
>> The Prime Minister:
What matters for all of us who are concerned
about education in this country is that we
ensure that the quality of education that
is provided for our children enables them
to get on in life and have a better future.
That is what this Government are about. It
is about ensuring that in this country you
get on on the basis of merit, not privilege;
it is about ensuring that every child—[Interruption]—every
child across this country has the opportunity
of a good school place. That is what we have
been delivering for the past seven years,
and it is what we will deliver into the future—and
every single policy that has delivered better
education for children has been opposed by
the right hon. Gentleman.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Maybe the Prime Minister could have a word
with her friend the hon. Member for The Cotswolds
(Geoffrey Clifton-Brown), who said this week:
“Under this new formula, all my large primaries
and all of my secondaries will actually see
a cash cut in their budgets.”
In the Budget, the Government found no more
money for the schools budget, but they did
find £320 million for the Prime Minister’s
special grammar schools vanity project. There
is no money for Eileen’s school, but £320
million for divisive grammar schools. What
kind of priority is that?
>> The Prime Minister:
First of all, what we have done in relation
to the funding formula is to address an issue
that Labour ignored for all its time in government.
Across this House there has generally been,
for many years, an accepted view that the
current formula for school funding is not
fair. I was saying this—I was calling for
a better funding formula—more than 15 years
ago when I was the shadow Education Secretary.
We have put forward a proposal, and we are
consulting on it. The consultation closes
today, and we will respond to that consultation.
The right hon. Gentleman talks about the sort
of system we want in schools. Yes, we want
diversity, and we want different sorts of
schools. We have put money into new school
places. But I say to him that his shadow Home
Secretary sent her child to a private school;
his shadow Attorney General sent her child
to a private school; he sent his child to
a grammar school; and he went to a grammar
school himself. Typical Labour—take the
advantage and pull up the ladder behind you.
>> Hon. Members:
More!
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
I want a decent, fair opportunity for every
child in every school. I want a staircase
for all, not a ladder for the few. The Prime
Minister has not been very good at convincing
the former Secretary of State for Education,
the right hon. Member for Loughborough (Nicky
Morgan), who wrote last week:
“All the evidence is clear that grammar
schools damage social mobility.” What evidence
has the Prime Minister got that the former
Secretary of State is wrong in that?
>> The Prime Minister:
The evidence is that for the poorest children,
the attainment gap in a selective school is
virtually zero. That tells us the quality
of the education that they are getting. What
I want is a diverse education system where
there are genuine opportunities for all to
have the education that is right for them.
That is why in the Budget, as well as dealing
with the issue of new school places, we have
put extra money into technical education for
young people for whom technical education
is right. The right hon. Gentleman says that
he wants opportunities for all children, and
he says that he wants good school places for
all children. He should jolly well support
the policies that we are putting forward.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
It is not just the former Education Secretary;
the Chair of the Education Committee also
says that grammar schools
“do little to help social mobility” and
are an “unnecessary distraction”. The
Prime Minister and her Government are betraying
a generation of young people by cutting the
funding for every child. Children will have
fewer teachers, larger classes and fewer subjects
to choose from, and all the Prime Minister
can do is to focus on her grammar school vanity
project, which can only ever benefit a few
children. Is the Prime Minister content for
the generation in our schools today to see
their schools decline, their subject choices
diminish and their life chances be held back
by decisions of her Government?
>> The Prime Minister:
Protected school funding, more teachers in
our schools, more teachers with first-class
degrees in our schools, more children in good
or outstanding schools—it is not a vanity
project to want every child in this country
to have a good school place. That is how they
will get on in life, and that is what this
party will deliver. But this shows that there
is a
difference between the right hon. Gentleman
and me. Earlier this week, he recorded a video
calling for unity. He called for Labour to
“think of our people first. Think of our
movement first. Think of the party first.”
That is the difference between him and me:
Labour puts the party first; we put the country
first.
>> Charlie Elphicke (Dover) (Con):
For centuries, Prime Ministers have taken
a close personal interest in the effectiveness
of Dover and the channel ports as gateways
to and guardians of the kingdom, so may I
ask my right hon. Friend to take a close interest
in making sure that Kent ports are ready for
Brexit on day one, and not just in terms of
customs, but with the M20 lorry park on schedule,
and the A2 upgrade and the lower Thames crossing
being taken forward? Mr Speaker, will you
join me and the Prime Minister in wishing
Dame Vera Lynn a happy 100th birthday this
week and thanking her for her service to the
white cliffs and to the nation?
>> Mr Speaker:
I am extremely grateful to the hon. Gentleman,
but I did do that a couple of days ago.
>> The Prime Minister:
I did not have that opportunity a couple of
days ago, so I am happy to join my hon. Friend
in wishing Dame Vera Lynn a very happy 100th
birthday this week. It is right that we recognise
the service that she gave to this country,
as many others did. My hon. Friend raises
the important issue of transport links in
Kent, which I have discussed with him and
other Kent MPs on a number of occasions. In
addition to the M20 lorry park, I assure him
that the Department for Transport is fully
committed to delivering a long-term solution
as quickly as possible. It is currently considering
the findings of the lower Thames crossing
consultation, and Highways England will be
doing more detailed work on the A2. The Home
Office will be looking very closely at what
measures need to be in place for Brexit for
those coming across the border into Dover.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP):
May I begin by extending condolences, as the
Prime Minister and the leader of the Labour
party have done, to the family, friends and
colleagues of the former Deputy First Minister
of Northern Ireland, Martin McGuinness? We
pay tribute to his contribution towards peace,
while never forgetting the terrible human
price during the troubles.
Last year, the Prime Minister promised that
she would secure a UK-wide agreement between
the Governments of Scotland, Wales and Northern
Ireland, and her Government, before triggering
article 50 on Brexit. Since then she has delayed,
she has blocked, she has been intransigent
and she has lectured—surprise, surprise;
she has no agreement. There is no agreement.
Will those be her negotiating tactics with
the European Union?
>> The Prime Minister:
Over the past few months, every effort has
been put in, at various ministerial and official
levels, to work with all the devolved Administrations
to identify their particular concerns and
interests, and to ensure that we are able
to take those into account throughout the
negotiating process. Discussions will continue
in the future. What we want to ensure is that
we get the best possible deal when we leave
the European Union for all the people of the
United Kingdom, including the people of Scotland,
because at heart we are one people.
>> Angus Robertson:
Viewers will note that the Prime Minister
totally glossed over the fact that she has
reached no agreement with the devolved Governments
of the United Kingdom. The Prime Minister
says that she wants article 50 negotiations
to lead to a deal and people to know the outcome
of that deal before it is approved. Will she
confirm that in the period for an agreement,
the House of Commons will have a choice, the
House of Lords will have a choice, the European
Parliament will have a choice and 27 member
states of the European Union will have a choice?
If it is right for all of them to have a choice
about Scotland’s future, why should the
people of Scotland not have a choice about
their own future?
>> The Prime Minister:
This is not a question about whether the people
of Scotland should have a choice about the
future—[Hon. Members: “Yes, it is.”]
The people of Scotland exercised their right
to self-determination and voted in 2014 to
remain a part of the United Kingdom. The people
of the United Kingdom voted last year to leave
the European Union. We are respecting both
those votes; the right hon. Gentleman is respecting
neither of them.
>> Sir Julian Brazier (Canterbury) (Con):
With her strong commitment to defence, does
my right hon. Friend agree that we must stem
the outflow from our shrinking forces? I urge
her to reconsider the policy that she inherited
of encouraging service families to get on
to the housing ladder on the one hand, while
on the other hand increasingly focusing the
Army in areas where there is no affordable
housing, and then applying the new landlord
tax arrangements to buy for let.
>> The Prime Minister:
I recognise the passion with which my hon.
Friend always raises issues about the armed
forces. He raises an important point, but
I can assure him that we are fully committed
to our goal of an 82,000-strong Army by 2020.
On his specific point about service accommodation,
we want is to ensure that people have a greater
choice in where they live by using private
accommodation and meeting their aspirations
for home ownership. That is why we set up
the £200 million forces Help to Buy scheme
and continue to support subsidised housing
for service personnel—the pot of money will
not be cut. The Ministry of Defence is working
with the Treasury on the issues my hon. Friend
raises, and I am sure that they will keep
him updated.
>> Mr Angus Brendan MacNeil (Na h-Eileanan
an Iar) (SNP):
The United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern
Ireland will be 95 years old in December.
In that UK, Scottish economic growth is a
quarter of that of independent Iceland and
a third of that of independent Ireland. Given
that the Prime Minister supports Irish independence
and the benefits that that has brought to
Ireland’s economy and population, why does
she oppose it for Scotland? Will she show
Scotland the respect that the EU showed the
UK in regard
to a referendum?
>> The Prime Minister:
If the hon. Gentleman is looking at issues
around economic growth—he cited figures
on growth—he should pay attention to the
most important market for Scotland: the market
of the United Kingdom. That is why Scotland
should remain part of it.
>> Simon Hoare (North Dorset) (Con):
Last week, with cross-party support, my hon.
Friend the Member for Chippenham (Michelle
Donelan) and I set up the all-party group
on Lyme disease. This debilitating disease
is a growing problem across the country, including
in my constituency, yet awareness of it among
the public and GPs is incredibly low. Will
my right hon. Friend ensure that her Government
do all they can to raise the profile of the
disease and to resolve the problems surrounding
both diagnosis and treatment?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend raises an important point,
and I commend him and my hon. Friend the Member
for Chippenham (Michelle Donelan) for the
attention that the House is now giving to
the issue. He is right that we need to raise
awareness, but we also need to ensure that
early diagnosis and treatment is available,
because that is the best way of limiting the
complications from this particular disease.
The Department of Health is already taking
steps. Clinical guidelines are being updated
and enhanced by the National Institute for
Health and Care Excellence, and NHS England
has undertaken robust reviews on diagnosis,
testing and treatment. However, there is more
that we can do, so Public Health England is
holding regular medical training days and
conducting outreach across the medical community
to raise awareness and ensure that that early
diagnosis is in place.
>> Alex Cunningham (Stockton North) (Lab):
During yesterday’s Adjournment debate, the
Minister of State, Department of Health, the
hon. Member for Ludlow (Mr Dunne), said that
the issue in hand was above his pay grade.
On the basis that the Prime Minister has the
top pay grade, can she give us a clue about
when we will see the long-awaited and very
late tobacco control plan?
>> The Prime Minister:
I can assure the hon. Gentleman that we are
working on the tobacco control plan and that
one will be issued in due course.
>> John Stevenson (Carlisle) (Con):
A substantial number of Ministers took the
opportunity to visit Cumbria recently and
saw for themselves not only its beauty, but
its industrial strengths and potential. If
the Government’s industrial strategy is
to succeed, places such as Cumbria need to
be part of that success. Will the Prime Minister
ensure that Cumbria gets the infrastructure
investment that it requires to ensure that
it really does fulfil its potential?
>> The Prime Minister:
My ministerial colleagues and I were delighted
to be able to take the opportunity to visit
the beautiful county of Cumbria, and we are
even happier now that Cumbria has another
strong voice in the form of my hon. Friend
the Member for Copeland (Trudy Harrison),
a Conservative MP. My hon. Friend the Member
for Carlisle (John Stevenson) is right: Cumbria
and the north-west have huge industrial potential.
That is why we are getting on with delivering
our investment plans throughout the country,
including the north-west. Let me give the
House some figures: £556 million has been
allocated from the local growth fund to boost
local productivity; and the north is getting
£147 million to tackle congestion and improve
local transport. However, it is our plan for
Britain that will deliver that stronger, fairer
economy and those higher-paid, higher-skilled
jobs for people throughout the country.
>> Lilian Greenwood (Nottingham South) (Lab):
The Prime Minister is in denial. Today’s
report from the Institute for Fiscal Studies
confirms that schools are already facing“the
largest cut in school spending per pupil over
a 4 year period since at least the early 1980s”,
and that, as a result of her new national
formula, funding is being diverted from schools
with very high levels of deprivation. Every
single school in my constituency will lose
an average of £584 per pupil. Has the Prime
Minister failed at maths, or failed to read
her own manifesto?
>> The Prime Minister:
I responded to that point earlier, but let
me just reiterate what I said. Across the
House, for many years, there has been a general
acceptance that the current funding formula
for schools is unfair, and that is why this
Government are seeking a fairer formula. A
consultation exercise is taking place, and
the Department for Education will respond
to it in due course. We are grasping this
issue, whereas Labour did nothing for 13 years.
>> Sir Edward Leigh (Gainsborough) (Con):
Can my right hon. Friend confirm that, following
the forthcoming debate on the restoration
and renewal of Parliament, all Members, including
Ministers, will have a completely free vote
on what is a House matter? Does she understand
that many of us believe that in these times
of austerity, we should not be frontloading
billions of pounds of expenditure on ourselves
at the expense of schools and hospitals, but
should carry on the work and stay in what
is the iconic image of the nation?
>> The Prime Minister:
The Palace of Westminster is world-renowned.
It is a very important part of our national
heritage, and it belongs to the United Kingdom.
Of course, we also have a responsibility to
our constituents to preserve this place as
the home of our democracy. It will be for
Parliament to make the final decision, but
I assure my hon. Friend that, as this will
be a House matter, there will be a free vote.
>> Chris Evans (Islwyn) (Lab/Co-op):
Air and road pollution, brought about mainly
by diesel engines, causes 40,000 early deaths
in this country, while also causing severe
lung diseases such as bronchitis and asthma
among young people and children. Hafodyrynys
Road in Crumlin, which is in my constituency,
is the most polluted road in the United Kingdom
outside London. It is an absolute disgrace.
Most of the pollution is caused by heavy goods
vehicles such as lorries and trucks, which
travel along the road spewing out noxious
gases on to residents. Will the Prime Minister
commit herself to ensuring that hauliers will
start using newer diesel engines, cleaner
technology and cleaner energy, so that everyone,
including young people, can enjoy a better
quality of life, especially on Hafodyrynys
Road?
>> The Prime Minister:
The hon. Gentleman speaks up well for his
constituents. We all recognise the problems
relating to air quality. The Government will
present further proposals, but some changes
have already taken place. We have invested
in green transport initiatives, and plans
to introduce clean zones around the country
will help to tackle the problem. In fact,
we have been at the forefront of action in
Europe in dealing with some aspects of it.
However, I accept that there is more to be
done, and, as I have said, we will present
further proposals in due course.
>> Huw Merriman (Bexhill and Battle) (Con):
The compensation paid by Network Rail to train
operators for delays far exceeds the amounts
that the passengers who experience the delays
are claiming because the ticket refund process
can be cumbersome. Will the Prime Minister
insist that train operators ring fence that
money, and spend it on automated smart ticketing
so that customers can tap on and tap off their
train, and receive money in their bank accounts
for the delays that they have been caused?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend raises an important point,
which I know is a source of much frustration
to many rail passengers. I thank him and others
for the way in which they have spoken up on
behalf of passengers, especially those using
lines such as Thameslink and Southern. The
best way to ensure that the operators do not
profit from unclaimed compensation is for
passengers to claim the compensation that
they are entitled to. The Department for Transport
is looking at how we can ensure that we publicise
compensation schemes and make claims easier.
We are rolling out improved Delay Repay compensation
to allow passengers to claim after a delay
of just 15 minutes. The Department is continuing
to look at this issue, and I am sure it will
pick up the points that my hon. Friend has
raised.
>> Pete Wishart (Perth and North Perthshire)
(SNP):
Last week the Electoral Commission imposed
on the Conservative party its largest ever
fine for breaking crucial election rules.
What did the Prime Minister, her Cabinet and
her aides know about any of this activity,
and who was responsible for designing and
signing off all this? Does she agree that
this was at best wilful negligence and at
worst pure electoral fraud?
>> The Prime Minister:
The hon. Gentleman asks me to respond to something
that is a party matter, but I can assure him
that the Conservative party did campaign in
2015 across the country for the return of
a Conservative Government, and we should be
clear that such campaigning would be part
of the party’s national return, not candidates’
local return, as the Electoral Commission
itself has said. The party accepted in April
2016 that it had made an administrative error
on its national spending. It brought that
to the attention of the Electoral Commission
in order to amend its national return. As
I have said, national electoral spending is
a question for the national party, not individual
Members. The Electoral Commission has looked
into these issues, as it has with issues for
the Liberal Democrats and the Labour party.
It has issued fines to all three parties,
and those fines will be paid.
>> Mr Ranil Jayawardena (North East Hampshire)
(Con):
The International Trade Committee has been
taking evidence about exports from chambers
of commerce this morning. Given the Prime
Minister’s commitment to a global Britain,
does she agree that we can maintain good relations
with our European friends as we leave the
European Union and also build on our long-standing
relationships with our Commonwealth friends
across the world to trade our way to greater
prosperity?
>> The Prime Minister:
One of the four pillars of our plan for Britain
is a global Britain—that more outward-looking
Britain. My hon. Friend is right that this
is not just a question of ensuring that we
get the right relationship with Europe when
we leave the EU. We do want to continue to
have a partnership—to be able to trade freely
across Europe, and for companies in EU member
states to trade with us—but we also want
to enhance and improve our arrangements for
trade with other parts of the world, including
members of the Commonwealth.
>> Siobhain McDonagh (Mitcham and Morden)
(Lab):
Last week, through no fault of her own, Amy
and her young daughter became homeless. After
months of looking for a flat, she finally
went to Merton Council, which told her that
it could only offer her temporary accommodation
in Birmingham, 140 miles away from her job,
her daughter’s school, and the friends and
family who make it possible for her to be
a working single mum. May I ask the Prime
Minister how it can be right that in one of
the richest cities in the world, where Russian
oligarchs and Chinese banks own scores of
properties and leave them empty, a London-born
working family like Amy’s have not a room
to live in?
>> The Prime Minister:
The issue of housing in the London Borough
of Merton is one that the hon. Lady and I
worked on many years ago when we were on the
borough’s housing committee together. I
recognise that she has raised a concern about
a particular constituent. Obviously I will
not comment on that individual case, but I
will say is that it is important that, overall,
the Government are dealing with the issue
of homelessness. We are ensuring that we are
building more homes and giving more support
to people to get into their own homes, but
this will take time as we make sure that those
properties are available and that we maintain
our record of providing housing support across
all types of housing in this country.
>> Nicky Morgan (Loughborough) (Con):
As the Prime Minister has already said, it
must be right that the same pupils with the
same characteristics should attract the same
amount of money. The unfairness in the system
was not challenged for 13 years under Labour.
Yes, there might need to be changes to the
current draft formula, but I hope that she
will commit to fulfilling our manifesto promise
to make school funding fairer. I think she
would agree that if the Labour Government
had carried on in office, their spending plans
would have led to what has happened in Greece
and Spain, where not just hundreds but tens
of thousands of teachers have had to be fired.
>> The Prime Minister:
My right hon. Friend is right. As I said earlier,
the issue of the funding formula for schools
was ducked for too long—it was certainly
ducked by the last Labour Government. We have
started to address it: we have been looking
at the formula, and we have brought forward
a proposal. We will look at the consultation
responses and respond in due course. She is
also absolutely right about the Labour party.
Its education policies would mean fewer opportunities
in schools, and its economic policy would
mean less funding for schools.
>> Jonathan Edwards (Carmarthen East and Dinefwr)
(PC):
Last week, the Prime Minister’s Government
confirmed that there had been no assessment
of the economic impact of a failure to strike
a trade deal with the EU before Brexit. Is
it not the case that, in triggering article
50 next week, she is the modern-day equivalent
of Lord Cardigan, the military commander responsible
for the charge of the Light Brigade? We all
know how that ended.
>> The Prime Minister:
In triggering article 50 next week, what I
am doing is responding to the wishes of the
British people.
Kevin Hollinrake (Thirsk and Malton) (Con):
Does the Prime Minister agree that we urgently
need to find a solution to the impact of the
national living wage on sleeping shifts in
the care sector? This, together with the policy
of Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs of
insisting on the payment of six years’ back
pay, plus penalties, could have a devastating
impact on this vitally important sector.
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend raises an important point.
Through the national living wage, we are giving
Britain a pay rise and making sure that pay
is fair in all sectors, including social care.
On his specific point, we are looking at that
issue carefully, including in the context
of funding pressures on social care. We are
working to ensure that enforcement protects
low-paid workers in a fair and proportionate
manner. As my right hon. Friend the Chancellor
announced in the Budget, £2 billion of extra
money is going into the social care sector,
but the specific issue that my hon. Friend
raises is being carefully looked at by the
Treasury.
>> Rosie Cooper (West Lancashire) (Lab):
Despite austerity, shocking pay increases
were awarded to the board of the Liverpool
clinical commissioning group, with a lay deputy
chair now being paid more than £100,000 following
a 43% increase. Will the Prime Minister agree
to investigate the failures of governance
within the CCG and the lack of scrutiny within
the wider Liverpool health economy, and ensure
that no mergers take place while those matters
are being investigated?
>> The Prime Minister:
I understand that my right hon. Friend the
Health Secretary has asked NHS England to
investigate the remuneration of non-executive
directors at Liverpool CCG, and I am sure
that he will keep the hon. Lady updated. We
want to make the NHS even more efficient so
that every possible penny can be spent on
frontline patient care, and I am pleased to
say that we are seeing results. The financial
position has improved by £1.3 billion compared
with this time last year, with 44 fewer trusts
in deficit. As I say, NHS England is investigating
the issue that the hon. Lady has raised.
>> Mrs Anne-Marie Trevelyan (Berwick-upon-Tweed)
(Con):
The Prime Minister will be aware that the
Jo Cox Commission on Loneliness is calling
us all to action to highlight and tackle loneliness.
In Northumberland, Forward Assist, a small
charity of which I am a patron, is taking
up this challenge, working with female military
veterans who are suffering from severe isolation
issues. Will the Prime Minister meet me and
some of those extraordinary women to learn
about how our Government can help to avoid
this outcome in the future?
>> The Prime Minister:
I commend the work that is being done by Forward
Assist in my hon. Friend’s constituency.
It sounds like a valuable project that is
doing important work. The Secretary of State
for Defence will be happy to meet her.
>> Jack Dromey (Birmingham, Erdington) (Lab):
The Schools Minister has been good enough
to agree to meet Erdington headteachers tomorrow.
The constituency is rich in talent, but it
is one of the poorest in the country. Some
96% of Birmingham’s schools will lose a
total of £20 million under the Government’s
fair funding formula, yet Surrey gains £17
million, Suffolk gains £10 million, and Windsor
and Maidenhead gains £300,000. How can that
possibly be fair?
>> The Prime Minister:
I note that the Schools Minister will be meeting
the hon. Gentleman and headteachers to discuss
the issue. The fair funding formula is about
trying to ensure that the unfair funding that
has existed up until now is actually dealt
with. There are some very, very stark differences.
There are schools in London, for example,
that get almost twice the funding of those
in other parts of the country. We need to
ensure that we address the unfairness in the
funding formula but, as I said earlier, there
is a consultation exercise and the Department
for Education will respond in due course.