>> Michael Fabricant (Lichfield) (Con):
What recent assessment she has made of the
(a) performance of the economy and (b) adequacy
of provision of public services
in the west midlands; and if she will make
a statement.
>> The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May):
The economy in the west midlands is performing
well. Businesses are continuing to invest,
and since 2010 employment in the
west midlands has risen by 180,000. That is
because the Conservatives in government have
safeguarded the economy. As a
result—my hon. Friend asks about public
services—there are more doctors and more
nurses in his hospitals, because you can
only have strong public services when you
have the strong and stable leadership that
delivers a strong economy.
>> Michael Fabricant:
I think what this nation needs is a strong
and stable Government. But is it not the case
that thanks to devolution, we
will not only have—I hope—strong and stable
government after the general election, but
strong and stable leadership in the
west midlands if the right choice is made
on 4 May?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend makes a powerful point, because
on 4 May, people in the west midlands have
the opportunity to elect a
strong local leader who will oversee £8 billion
of investment. In Andy Street, I think that
they have absolutely the man
who has the local knowledge, the business
experience, and the commitment to the west
midlands to deliver for the whole
west midlands. Of course, on 8 June, people
in the west midlands will then have the opportunity
to elect the strong and
stable leadership of a Conservative Government.
Working together, strong Conservative leadership
in the west midlands and
strong Conservative leadership in government
will deliver for the west midlands.
>> Richard Drax (South Dorset) (Con):
If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 26 April.
>> The Prime Minister:
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in this House, I shall have
further such meetings later today.
>> Richard Drax:
In 2015, a group called the Socialist Campaign
for a Labour Victory incredulously drew up
a plan to disband MI5, disarm
the police and scrap our nuclear deterrent.
Would my right hon. Friend allow anyone who
endorsed such a plan to write her
manifesto or, indeed, serve in her Cabinet?
>> The Prime Minister:
My answer to that is a resounding no, I would
not. I commend my hon. Friend, who has a proud
record of defending our
country. He raises an important point because,
of course, the Leader of the Opposition has
chosen just such a person. The
plan to disband MI5, disarm our police and
scrap our nuclear deterrent was endorsed by
the right hon. Gentleman’s policy
chief and even by his shadow Chancellor. At
the weekend, we saw the right hon. Gentleman
again refusing to say that he
would strike against terrorism, refusing to
commit to our nuclear deterrent and refusing
to control our borders. Keeping
our country safe is the first duty of a Prime
Minister. The right hon. Gentleman is simply
not up to the job.
>> Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab):
This is the last Prime Minister’s Question
Time of this Parliament, so I think it would
be appropriate if we all paid
tribute to those colleagues who have decided
to leave the House. I thank them for their
service to democracy in this
country. I also thank you, Mr Speaker, for
the way in which you have presided over this
House and sought to reach out to
the wider communities in this country.
When I became Leader of the Opposition 18
months ago—[Hon. Members: “More!”] If
Conservative Members wait a moment, I will
explain what I am about to say. When I became
Leader of the Opposition, I said that I wanted
people’s voices to be heard
in Parliament, so instead of just speaking
to hand-picked audiences who cannot ask questions,
I hope the Prime Minister
will not mind answering some questions from
the public today. I start with Christopher,
who wrote to me this week to say,
“In the last five years, my husband has
had only a 1% increase in his wages. The cost
of living has risen each year. We
now have at least 15% less buying power than
then.” Where is Christopher and his husband’s
share in the stronger economy?
>> The Prime Minister:
May I first join the right hon. Gentleman
in commending those colleagues who are leaving
the House for the service they
have shown to their constituents and to Parliament
over the years? I also say a huge thank you
to the staff of the House
of Commons and of Parliament who support us
in the work that we do in this Chamber and
elsewhere.
By the way, I note that the right hon. Gentleman
did not take the opportunity to stand up and
say how he would actually
stand up for the defence of our country. Once
again, he missed that opportunity. I note
what he is saying about wages
increasing. I see today that he is talking
about paying for extra wage increases in the
national health service. First of
all, we should recognise that around half
of staff working in the national health service,
because of progression and
basic pay increases, will actually see, on
average, a pay increase of 4%.
What we know, and what I can say to Christopher,
is that he will have a choice at the next
election between the strong and
stable leadership of the Conservatives, which
will secure our economy for the future, and
a Labour party that would crash
our economy, which would mean less money for
public services, with ordinary working families
paying the price.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Is not the truth that many people are being
held back by this Government, who have slashed
taxes for the rich, and held
back or cut the pay of dedicated public servants?
Andy, a parent, is concerned about how his
children are being held back. He asks why,
“despite the fact they have worked
consistently since leaving school, all three
of my children, who are now in their mid-20s,
cannot afford to move out of
the family home.” Is this not a crisis that
many people are facing all over the country?
Do we not need a housing
strategy that deals with it?
>> The Prime Minister:
First of all, let us look and see what happened
under a Labour Government on housing. Under
the last Labour Government,
house building starts fell by 45%. Under the
last Labour Government, house purchases in
England fell by 40%. The number of
social rented homes under a Labour Government
fell by 420,000. Under the Conservatives,
we have seen more than twice as
much council housing being built than under
the last Labour Government. That is the record
of a Conservative Government
delivering on housing and delivering for ordinary
working families.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
The last Labour Government delivered a decent
homes standard for every council home in the
whole country, and it is
something we are proud of—we are very proud
indeed of that achievement. Under the Prime
Minister’s Government, house
building has fallen to the lowest level since
the 1920s. More people homeless, more people
on waiting lists, more people
overcrowded, more people unable to pay the
rent—that is the record of the Tory Government.
Our children are being held back by Conservative
cuts. Laura, a young primary school teacher,
wrote to me this week to
say, “I’m seeing a decrease each year
in available cash to provide a quality education
to the children in my class and an
increase in reliance upon our parent teachers
association.” Is the Prime Minister still
denying the fact that funding for
each pupil is still being cut?
>> The Prime Minister:
What I would say to Laura is that we said
we would protect school budgets, and we have.
We have seen record levels of
funding going into schools in this country.
At the election on 8 June, people are going
to have a very clear choice. They
will have a choice between a Conservative
Government that have delivered 1.8 million
more good and outstanding school
places for children across this country, and
that believe in parents having choice with
a range of schools providing the
education that is right for every child and
a good school place for every child, and a
Labour party under the right hon.
Gentleman. He believes in “one size fits
all; take everybody down to the lowest common
denominator; take it or leave it”;
we believe in encouraging aspiration and helping
people to get on in their lives.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Labour is not slashing school budgets. Labour
is not putting money into pet projects. We
want every child—every child—to
have a decent chance in a decent school. We
do not want an education system that relies
on begging letters from schools to
maintain employment and books in the classroom.
Many people feel that the system is rigged
against them. Maureen wrote to me this week—[Interruption.]
I say to
Conservative Members that if I was you, I
would listen to what Maureen has to say—I
really would—because she writes, with
a heavy heart, “We have been treated disgustingly.
Most of us women born in the 1950s will not
be receiving our pension
until we are 66, with no notification of this
drastic change. We have worked for 45 years
and have accrued more than
enough to be paid our pension. People want
what is rightfully theirs.” Maureen asks,
“What can be done to help the
WASPI women?”
>> The Prime Minister:
What I would say on the issue that Maureen
has raised is that the Government have taken
steps to help these women. Extra
funding has been made available and we have
ensured that there is a limit to the period
of time that is affected in
relation to these changes. If the right hon.
Gentleman wants to talk about pensions and
pensioners looking to the future,
then once again there will be a very clear
choice at this election—a clear choice between
a Labour party that in
government saw an increase to the basic state
pension of 75p in one year, and a Conservative
Government whose changes to
pensions mean that basic state pensioners
are £1,250 better off. But you only get that
with a strong economy, and what do
we know about Labour? Only yesterday, we saw
that we had finally emerged from Labour’s
economic crash. What we now see is
a Labour party that would do it again: crash
the economy, more debt, more waste, higher
taxes, fewer jobs. That does
nothing for ordinary working families or for
pensioners.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Millions of WASPI women will have heard that
answer, as they will have heard the other
questions I have put that have not
been answered today. I simply say this: Labour
will guarantee the triple lock. Labour will
treat pensioners with respect
and we will not move the goalposts for people
looking forward to retirement.
Sybil, who witnessed the Labour founding of
the national health service, which made healthcare
available for the many, not
just the few, wrote to me this week, and she
says, “I am 88 and have had a wonderful
service from the national health
service, but nowadays I am scared at the thought
of going into hospital.” With more people
waiting more than four hours in
A&amp;E, more people waiting on trolleys in
corridors, and more delayed discharges thanks
to the Tory cuts, is not Sybil
right to be frightened about the future of
our NHS so long as this Government remain
in office?
>> The Prime Minister:
Let me just say to the right hon. Gentleman
that our national health service is now treating
more patients than ever
before. We are seeing more people having operations;
we are seeing more doctors, more nurses, more
midwives, more GPs, and
record levels of funding into our national
health service. But that is only possible
with a strong economy and only
possible with a strong and stable Government.
Of course, over the coming weeks we are all
going to be out there
campaigning across the country, as I will
be, on our record on the national health service.
I noted this week that the shadow Home Secretary
has been campaigning in her own personal way.
She has directed her
supporters—her followers—to a website
called “I Like Corbyn, But…” which asks:
“how will he pay for all this?”
“But”. It also says:
“I heard he wants to increase taxes”.
“But”.
“I’ve heard he’s a terrorist sympathiser”.
“his attitudes about defence worry me”.
“But”. They are right to be worried. Unable
to defend our country; determined to raise
tax on ordinary workers; no plan to
manage our economy: even his own supporters
know he is not fit to run this country.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
My question was about the national health
service and Sybil’s concerns. The NHS has
not got the money it needs; the Prime
Minister knows that. She knows that waiting
times and waiting lists are up; she knows
there is a crisis in almost every
A&amp;E department. Maybe she could go to
a hospital and allow the staff to ask her
a few questions.
Strong leadership is about standing up for
the many, not the few, but the Prime Minister
and the Conservatives only look
after the richest, not the rest. They are
strong against the weak and weak against the
strong. Far from building a strong
economy, schools and our NHS are being cut,
people cannot afford homes, and millions cannot
make ends meet. That does not
add up to a stronger economy for anyone. The
election on 8 June is a choice between a Conservative
Government for the few
and a Labour Government who will stand up
for all of our people.
>> The Prime Minister:
If the right hon. Gentleman wants to talk
about the NHS, perhaps he should talk about
Labour’s custodianship of the NHS in
Wales. There is somewhere that the NHS has
been cut, and that is in Wales under the Labour
party.
The right hon. Gentleman is right: in something
over six weeks we will be back at these Dispatch
Boxes. The only question
is: where will we be standing? Who will be
Prime Minister of this great country? He says
that the choice is clear, and it
is. Every vote for him is a vote for a chaotic
Brexit; every vote for me is a vote to strengthen
our hand in negotiating
the best deal for Britain. Every vote for
him is a vote to weaken our economy; every
vote for me is a vote for a strong
economy with the benefits felt by everyone
across the country. Every vote for him is
a vote for a coalition of chaos, a
weak leader propped up by the Liberal Democrats
and the Scottish nationalists; every vote
for me is a vote for strong and
stable leadership in the national interest,
building a stronger and more secure future
for this country.
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The exchanges between the Prime Minister
and the Leader of the Opposition have been
unprecedentedly comprehensive.
We wish to hear questions from Back Benchers.
>> Ben Howlett (Bath) (Con):
Thanks to this Conservative Government, the
west of England has received billions of pounds
of investment in transport
infrastructure. On frequent visits to Bath
by the Transport Secretary and the Prime Minister,
I have raised with them the
issues of congestion and air pollution, as
well as the need for a feasibility study on
the long overdue A36-46 link road
to the east of Bath. Does the Prime Minister
agree that the only way to secure that vital
infrastructure project is for
Bath residents to give me a renewed mandate
on 8 June?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right. I know
that he has been campaigning tirelessly on
that issue on behalf of his
constituents. I understand that Highways England
is already considering a number of options
to divert traffic away from
Bath, as he suggests. Of course, it is this
Conservative Government who have increased
annual Government infrastructure
investment, but that is only possible with
a strong economy, which is only possible with
a strong and stable Conservative
leadership. A vote for any other party is
a vote for wrecking our economy and for a
coalition of chaos, which would do
nothing for my hon. Friend’s constituents,
for whom I hope he will continue to be able
to work tirelessly.
>> Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP):
Will the Prime Minister give a clear and unambiguous
commitment to maintaining the triple lock
on the state pension?
>> The Prime Minister:
I have been very clear that under this Conservative
Government we have seen pensioners benefit
to the tune of £1,250 a
year, as a result of what we have done to
the basic state pension, and I am clear that
under a Conservative Government
pensions and incomes will continue to increase.
>> Angus Robertson:
I asked the Prime Minister a pretty simple
yes/no question and she failed to answer it,
so pensioners right across this
land are right to conclude that this Tory
Prime Minister plans to ditch the triple lock
on the state pension. Too many
women already face pensions inequality, and
the Tories will not even guarantee the pensions
triple lock. The only reason
they will not do so is that they want to cut
pensions. Is not the message to pensioners:
you cannot trust this Prime
Minister or the Tories with your pension?
>> The Prime Minister:
I say to everybody, as I have just said, that
the party that has, in government, improved
the lot of pensioners across
this country is the Conservative party. Under
a Conservative Government, pensioner incomes
would continue to increase. The
right hon. Gentleman talks about inequality
for women. The change in the structure of
the state pension introduced by this
Government is going to improve the lot of
female pensioners in the future; it is going
to be much better for them. One
thing that pensioners in Scotland will know,
as will other voters in Scotland, is that
if they believe in the Union, there
is only one way to vote, and that is Conservative.
>> Jason McCartney (Colne Valley) (Con):
My local clinical commissioning group is planning
to downgrade the A&amp;E at Huddersfield Royal
infirmary and move it to
Halifax. That has been dictated by a disastrous
private finance initiative deal. I have been
fighting these appalling
plans alongside the community campaign group
Hands Off HRI, which is led by Karl Deitch.
Will the Prime Minister join me
in praising the community campaigners, led
by Karl? Does she agree that patients should
not be suffering as a result of
the catastrophic PFI deals signed by the last
Labour Government, and will she ensure that
communities such as mine have
their voices listened to properly?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend has raised this issue with
me previously, and I know that he has been
a tireless campaigner on it. He has
been a strong voice for his local constituency
and he has put his case persuasively to Ministers.
He is absolutely right:
Labour’s disastrous PFI deals are costing
the NHS more than £1 billion every year.
The choice at the election will be
clear. Do the people of Colne Valley want
his strong voice for their local A&amp;E,
and the ear of a strong Conservative
Government who are continuing to keep our
economy strong and investing in our national
health service, or do they want the
Leader of the Opposition and his coalition
of chaos—less money for our public services,
less money for our national health
service, fewer doctors, fewer nurses and worse
healthcare for our constituents?
>> Tom Blenkinsop (Middlesbrough South and
East Cleveland) (Lab):
My hon. Friends the Members for Redcar (Anna
Turley), for Scunthorpe (Nic Dakin), for Newport
East (Jessica Morden), for
Alyn and Deeside (Mark Tami), for Penistone
and Stocksbridge (Angela Smith), for Cardiff
South and Penarth (Stephen
Doughty) and for Llanelli (Nia Griffith) are
all proven champions for their local steel
communities. Does the Prime
Minister agree that their ongoing presence
in this place is vital for the future of our
British steel industry?
>> The Prime Minister:
I believe that the hon. Gentleman is standing
down at the election, and he has said that
that is due to his “significant
and irreconcilable differences” with the
leadership of his party. [Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. I am trying to help Back Benchers to
be heard. Please help the Chair to help Back-Bench
Members.
>> The Prime Minister:
What is important for the steel industry in
this country is that this Government have
taken action to support it. I was
very pleased, when I visited Wales yesterday,
to be able to visit a company that works with
the steel industry galvanising
steel products. The company talked about the
greater amount of work that it is seeing and
the improvements in the steel
industry. This Conservative Government have
taken steps to support the steel industry
and will continue to do so.
>> Mary Robinson (Cheadle) (Con):
With the consultation on the Greater Manchester
spatial framework now closed, I would like
to thank the 3,600 Cheadle
residents who signed my petition. It called
for the green belt in Cheadle Hulme, Heald
Green and Woodford to be protected
and for much-needed homes to be built on brownfield
land instead. Does my right hon. Friend the
Prime Minister agree that
we must press for brownfield sites to be identified
and redeveloped, and that protections for
our precious green spaces
can only be maintained under a strong Conservative
Government?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right on this
issue. I know that she has been a strong campaigner
and a strong champion for
her constituents in Cheadle. I can assure
her that we are very clear that the green
belt must be protected. What we have
set out in the White Paper is that boundaries
should be altered only when local authorities
have fully examined all other
reasonable options, such as making use of
brownfield sites, as she herself has suggested.
I know there was a great deal of
interest in the consultation on the Greater
Manchester spatial framework. I commend my
hon. Friend for the work she did to
gather the views of her constituents in Cheadle,
and I am sure that those views will be taken
into account as the response
is developed.
>> Rachael Maskell (York Central) (Lab/Co-op):
Over the past six months, it has been announced
that 2,000 jobs will be lost in York. Yesterday,
Nestlé announced 300 job
losses, 156 of them in my constituency, which
is devastating for workers, their families
and the community. Jobs, not
products, are being exported to the EU, and
as ever, York’s skilled jobs are being replaced
by low-wage, insecure work. In
the light of the special deal at Nissan in
Sunderland, will the Prime Minister meet me,
trade unions and the company to
strike a special deal to save these jobs and
avert the losses both now and in the future?
>> The Prime Minister:
First, the hon. Lady is right to raise this
issue of the announcement from Nestlé, which
arose, as she says, only
yesterday. We should be clear that Nestlé
has itself been clear that this is not a decision
that was affected by leaving
the European Union—it says it has made it
irrespective of that—but of course it is
a worrying time for the workers and
their families at Nestlé in both York and
Newcastle. I can assure her that we are already
in contact with the company to
understand its plans and the next steps. My
right hon. Friend the Business Secretary will
speak with senior Nestlé
representatives later today. The Department
for Work and Pensions of course stands ready
to put in place its rapid
response service to support any workers made
redundant by helping them back into employment
as quickly as possible, and
there are various ways in which Jobcentre
Plus can help. What is important is that we
ensure that the support is there,
and as I have said, the Business Secretary
will be speaking to Nestlé representatives
later today.
>> Byron Davies (Gower) (Con):
Record employment, the national living wage,
strong national defences and keeping our promises
on Europe—these are just
some of the achievements that we can be proud
that this Government have delivered. Does
my right hon. Friend agree that
only a vote for strong and stable Conservative
leadership in the national interest on 8 June
will continue to deliver on
the economy, defence and a deal with Europe,
and that the only way to enable businesses,
such as the Gower Brewery, and
residents in Gower to continue to thrive is
by re-electing a Conservative MP for the second
time?
>> The Prime Minister:
I thank my hon. Friend for his question. He
has of course, since his fantastic, historic
election in Gower, been a really
powerful voice for his constituents, but also,
indeed, for the needs of Wales more generally.
I have already referred to
the fact that I was in Wales yesterday, and
had the opportunity to speak to people in
business and to meet voters and hear
their concerns, but my hon. Friend goes absolutely
to the heart of the matter when he says that
what is necessary is a
good Brexit deal. That is crucial for businesses,
it is crucial for jobs and it is only achievable
by a strong and stable
Government. Every vote for me and the Conservatives,
and for Conservative candidates at local level,
will strengthen our
hand in those negotiations.
>> Chris Stephens (Glasgow South West) (SNP):
Q7. Yesterday, the Scottish Tories’ shameful
defence of the rape clause failed because
their claim that third-party
reporting is in place is not true. Will the
Prime Minister confirm that no organisation
in Scotland has yet signed up to
help women fill in an eight-page “Why my
child is a product of rape” form, and with
DWP staff not trained either, is the
Prime Minister seriously going into this UK-wide
election with this unworkable and immoral
policy?
>> The Prime Minister:
This is an incredibly sensitive issue, and
that is why we have looked at it very carefully.
We consulted very carefully on
it, and we have put in place a series of sensitive
measures for when such cases arise. I think
it is important, however,
that we look at what lies behind this, because
underpinning this policy is a principle of
fairness, and we know that what
the SNP want to do is actually to scrap the
policy in its entirety. We believe that people
who are in work have to make
the same decisions as those people who are
out of work, so that people who are on benefits
should have to decide whether
they can afford more children, just as people
in work have to make such a decision.
>> Julian Sturdy (York Outer) (Con):
York is a fantastic place to live, work and
start a business, but transport infrastructure
is key if the city is to fulfil
its economic potential. Dualling the northern
ring road, a new railway station at Haxby
and upgrading the A64 will all
help to secure York’s future, so will the
Prime Minister continue to improve infrastructure,
secure a strong economy and
deliver for regions such as Yorkshire?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend raises a very important point.
We have been able to invest in York, with
£1.6 million this year for
transport improvements, £2.2 million for
highways maintenance and £1.3 million to
support the sustainable i-Travel York
initiative, but we can invest in infrastructure
only if we have the strong and stable leadership
that secures a strong
economy. That is what the choice in June will
be. It is very clear: a strong economy, guaranteeing
investment in York and
across the country under the Conservatives,
or bankruptcy and chaos with Labour.
>> Stephen Timms (East Ham) (Lab):
As the Prime Minister knows, fixed odds betting
terminals cause immense harm in communities.
On taking office, she
authorised a review of maximum stakes and
all the evidence was collected by the end
of last year. Why do we still not have
a result? Will she today show some leadership
and reduce the maximum stake on these appalling
machines to £2?
>> The Prime Minister:
I recognise that a number of hon. Members
have raised concerns about this issue. We
did indeed have the consultation and
there will be a Government response to it.
Of course, that response—[Interruption.]
“Get on with it,” we are told. We are
now in a situation where these things will
be published after the purdah period and after
the general election, so the
right hon. Gentleman will have to wait for
that response. Obviously we recognise the
concern over this issue and we will
respond in due course.
>> Iain Stewart (Milton Keynes South) (Con):
Should the Prime Minister find herself in
the vicinity of Milton Keynes over the next
few weeks, may I suggest a visit to
Milton Keynes university hospital, where she
will find rising clinical standards and investment
going in, with a new ward,
a new medical school and a new cancer treatment
centre?
>> The Prime Minister:
I thank my hon. Friend. I think I will be
visiting communities around the whole country
over the next few weeks. I
congratulate the staff at Milton Keynes university
hospital on achieving that rating. As my hon.
Friend said, it was
backed up by considerable investment. As we
know, between 2015 and 2020 more than half
a trillion pounds is being spent on
the NHS in England. That is only possible
because we have safeguarded the economy over
the past seven years. As I have
said previously today, that will only be possible
in the future if we secure the strong and
stable leadership our country
needs. As I said, in Wales Labour has been
cutting the health budget.
>> Dr Alan Whitehead (Southampton, Test) (Lab):
I invite the Prime Minister, instead of going
to Milton Keynes, to visit me in Southampton
and take a tour of
Southampton’s schools. If she does, she
will find that those schools are in despair
about the cut in pupil funding of 10%
in Southampton, which is £475 per pupil or
equivalent to the loss of almost 400 teaching
jobs across the city. She will
also find one school that is inviting parents
to clean the school toilets—
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The hon. Gentleman has got his point
across with considerable force.
>> The Prime Minister:
It is perfectly possible that I will find
myself in Southampton over the coming weeks.
As I have said before in this
House, there is general agreement that the
current funding formula is not fair. Labour
did nothing in 13 years of
government to address that. It is important
that we get it right and we will respond to
the consultation in due course.
What is good news for schools in the hon.
Gentleman’s constituency is that 7,000 more
children are now in good or
outstanding schools in his constituency. Under
our proposed reforms, overall funding for
schools in his constituency would
rise.
>> Mr Speaker:
As he steps down after 44 years’ service
in the House, I call Sir Alan Haselhurst.
>> Sir Alan Haselhurst (Saffron Walden) (Con):
Will my right hon. Friend assure me that her
second Government will have high regard for
matters of great concern to the
Saffron Walden constituency, namely improved
railways with extra track capacity, in line
with the West Anglia and Great
Eastern taskforce reports; the spread of fast
broadband to rural communities; and an airspace
regime that prioritises
noise reduction?
>> The Prime Minister:
May I first pay tribute to my right hon. Friend
not just for his service to his constituents
over the years, but for his
service to the House when he took the Chair
as Deputy Speaker? He has been a stalwart
and a champion of the people of
Saffron Walden over the years—for 40 years,
as you said, Mr Speaker.
My right hon. Friend is right to raise issues
of infrastructure spending. We included £40
million for the east of England
in the Budget, but, as I think he implied
in his question, such spending is only possible
with the strong economy that
comes from a strong and stable Government,
and for Saffron Walden that will mean the
election of a Conservative Government
on 8 June.
>> Steven Paterson (Stirling) (SNP):
My constituent, Mr Buchanan, has suffered
several serious strokes and requires extensive
care. He was deemed to have
missed his appointment for an Atos assessment
when Atos arrived early for the appointment
and his carers had not yet
helped him to get up. As a result, his benefits
were stopped. Why is the Government’s welfare
regime punishing vulnerable
people like my constituent?
>> The Prime Minister:
We want to ensure that we have a system that
properly assesses people who apply for benefits.
As the hon. Gentleman has
said, and as other Members will know, there
have been issues relating to the way in which
the system has operated. The
Department for Work and Pensions has been
looking very carefully at it to ensure that
it makes proper assessments and
delivers the right results for people.
>> Mr Peter Lilley (Hitchin and Harpenden)
(Con):
Does my right hon. Friend realise that I am
standing down after 34 years because of her?
I am standing down because I am
confident that the country will be safe after
the election under her strong and stable leadership.
Does she agree that
seizing the opportunities presented by regaining
control over our laws, our money, our borders
and our trade will be more
important than the terms of any exit deal
and that, if we are to secure a reasonable
deal, we must accept that no deal is
indeed better than a bad deal? To deny this
signals that no price is too high, no concession
too grovelling to accept—a
recipe for the worst possible deal.
I wish my right hon. Friend, all hon. Members
and this House I love Godspeed.
>> The Prime Minister:
I thank my right hon. Friend for the tremendous
contribution that he has made throughout his
years as a Member of the
House, not only on behalf of his constituents
but during his time as a valued Minister in
a Conservative Government. He
has rightly highlighted the importance of
the decision that was made last year by the
people of the United Kingdom, and I
commend him for the role that he played in
the referendum campaign.
It is right that we get on with the job of
delivering Brexit and making a success of
it, which means having a strong hand
in negotiations. The only way to ensure that
that is the case—for the people of Hitchin
and Harpenden and for the whole
UK—is to ensure that a Conservative Government
is elected on 8 June.
>> Sir Jeffrey M. Donaldson (Lagan Valley)
(DUP):
We do need a strong Prime Minister to lead
this nation, but we need the countries of
this nation to have a strong voice as
well. Does the Prime Minister agree that those
who abstain from taking their seats in the
House—those who are denying the
people of Northern Ireland the formation of
a Government—are denying their constituents
a say in the future of this
country? We, however, will not allow that
to happen.
>> The Prime Minister:
The right hon. Gentleman is absolutely right.
It is, of course, important for the constituents
who elect Members of
Parliament to feel that those Members of Parliament
are able to do their job—to bring their
concerns to the House and to
play a full part in the Chamber. The right
hon. Gentleman is also right to stress that
we want to ensure that every part
of the United Kingdom has a strong voice,
which is why it is so important that we continue
to work for the restoration of
the devolved Administration of Northern Ireland.
>> Sir Eric Pickles (Brentwood and Ongar)
(Con):
The Prime Minister has shown considerable
leadership in adopting the International Holocaust
Remembrance Alliance
definition of anti-Semitism. Does she believe
that it is the duty of all party leaders in
the house not just to pay lip
service to it, but to do something about it,
and does she share my disgust that a former
Member of this House, criticised
by the Home Affairs Committee for his anti-Semitic
utterances, is now the official candidate
in Bradford East—for the
Liberal Democrats?
>> The Prime Minister:
May I first pay tribute to my right hon. Friend—my
chum in this House—for all the service he
has given, and not just for
his service in this House: he had a considerable
record in local government before he came
into this House? He has also in
his time and the work he has done on anti-Semitism
performed a very important role: he has had
a relentless drive to stamp
out anti-Semitism and, indeed, intolerance
in all its forms in our communities, and he
should be proud of his record and
the work that I know he will continue to do
as a champion on this issue.
My right hon. Friend is right to highlight
Bradford—of course, he has a particular
knowledge of that city—and I think that
people will be rightly disappointed to see
the Liberal Democrats readopt a candidate
with a questionable record on anti-
Semitism. It is important that all parties
maintain the strongest possible censure of
all forms of intolerance and send
that message to our communities.
>> Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
In the nine months that the Prime Minister
has held office, she has closed the door on
desperate child refugees and
ignored the plight of those suffering under
the crisis in health and social care, and
she is responsible for the shameful
rape clause. Twenty years ago, she berated
the Conservative party for being the “nasty
party”, but her party has never
been nastier. The legacy of this Parliament—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. Whatever the strength of feeling, the
hon. Gentleman must be heard.
>> Tim Farron:
The legacy of this Parliament is the utter,
abject failure of Her Majesty’s official
Opposition to effectively hold her
Government account for any of this. Is it
not time that Britain had a strong, decent,
new Opposition?
>> The Prime Minister:
First, let me pick up the point the hon. Gentleman
made on child refugees. This Government have
a proud record on
supporting refugees from Syria. We have been
the second biggest bilateral donor to the
region, to support millions of
refugees and educate children, as I saw when
I visited Jordan recently, and of course we
have also supported some of the
most vulnerable refugees, including children,
by bringing them here to make a new life in
the United Kingdom. The hon.
Gentleman talks about a decent Opposition;
I find it difficult to hear those words coming
from his mouth when we have just
heard that his party has selected a candidate
with questionable views on anti-Semitism.
>> Sir Gerald Howarth (Aldershot) (Con):
It has been an immense privilege to serve
the people of Cannock and Burntwood and of
Aldershot for the past 34 years. I
arrived here in 1983, when one formidable
and determined female Conservative Prime Minister
was transforming the country’s
economic fortunes, and I depart as another
is determined to restore to this country the
status of a sovereign nation state
embracing the rest of the world. As I, too,
bid my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister
Godspeed for a resounding victory
on 8 June, may Aldershot make one final plea
in these troubled times: please will she ensure
that Her Majesty’s armed
forces are properly funded, manned, equipped
and housed to defend and protect the people
of this glorious sceptred isle,
the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern
Ireland?
>> The Prime Minister:
Once again, may I pay tribute to my hon. Friend
for the work he has done in this House representing
two different
constituencies over 34 years? One of the underlying
themes of his time in this House has been
his passionate championing
of, and consideration for, our armed forces,
and I can assure him that on 8 June people
will have a very clear choice
between the Leader of the Opposition, who
refuses to defend our country, and a Conservative
Government who will continue
to support our armed forces.
>> Grahame M. Morris (Easington) (Lab):
May I ask the Prime Minister why she is running
scared of the televised leadership debates?
May I suggest that she hold a
televised debate in the Easington colliery
miners welfare centre, where she can see the
consequences of seven years of her
policies on housing, of the cuts to policing
and of 500 people at Walker’s losing their
jobs. Perhaps she could then
explain to the people there, if that is possible,
why she has any mandate to seek their support
for re-election.
>> The Prime Minister:
I have been in televised debates with the
Leader of the Opposition week in and week
out since I took over as Prime
Minister, and I will be taking the fine record
of this Conservative Government across all
parts of this country. The hon.
Gentleman talks about housing. Twice the number
of council houses were built under the Conservatives
as were built under
Labour. There has been record funding into
our national health service and our schools,
and pensioners on the basic state
pension are £1,250 a year better off. That
is the proud record of the Conservatives and
a record that we will continue
after 8 June.
>> Mike Wood (Dudley South) (Con):
It is good to be back—[Hon. Members: “Hear,
hear.”] To be honest, it is good to be anywhere.
Doctors and nurses at
Russells Hall hospital saved my life in January,
but each year in the UK, 44,000 people are
less lucky. Will my right hon.
Friend look at what measures we can take to
reduce deaths from sepsis, including awareness
raising, a national registry to
properly record the burden of sepsis and effective
commissioning levers to incentivise best practice?
The UK Sepsis Trust
estimates that such measures would save 50,000
lives over the next Parliament.
>> The Prime Minister:
It is fantastic to see my hon. Friend back
in his place. I hope that he will have noted
the welcome that he got from
across the House. He is absolutely right to
bring our focus on to the devastating condition
of sepsis. Every death from it
is a tragedy, but as we know, something like
10,000 deaths a year could be avoided through
prevention, early diagnosis and
treatment. So we need to get better at spotting
sepsis across the NHS, and the Department
of Health is already beginning
work on a new sepsis action plan. We are having
a new public awareness campaign and we expect
a NICE quality standard to
be published later this year. With the passion
that my hon. Friend now brings to this campaign,
I am sure that he will
continue to make his voice heard on this important
issue.
>> Mr George Howarth (Knowsley) (Lab):
Yesterday, my right hon. Friend the Member
for Leigh (Andy Burnham)—who will be much
missed in this House—had a debate on
contaminated blood, in which he called for
an independent, Hillsborough-style panel to
get to the truth. The Prime
Minister has praised the independent panel
approach as a way to open up the door to justice,
so will she join Labour and
the Scottish National party in committing
to setting up such a process in her party’s
manifesto?
>> The Prime Minister:
Last July, we committed £125 million of extra
funding for those affected by the contaminated
blood tragedy of the ’70s and
’80s. That is more than any previous Government
have provided. We published some proposed
reforms last year, and we are
now consulting on a new measure to allow the
people affected to benefit from higher annual
payments, but I can reassure
everybody that everyone will receive, at a
minimum, what they receive now as a result
of the proposed changes. The
Department of Health will respond to the consultation
in due course.
>> Dame Angela Watkinson (Hornchurch and Upminster)
(Con):
It was a privilege to win back the seat of
Upminster in 2001 for the Conservatives. Will
my right hon. Friend tell the
House why the good people of Hornchurch and
Upminster should continue to vote Conservative
at the coming election?
>> The Prime Minister:
First, I should like to pay tribute to my
hon. Friend for the contribution that she
has made, not just for her
constituents but in the time she served in
the Whips Office in this House, for example.
I am happy to tell the voters of
Hornchurch and Upminster that every vote for
me and the local Conservative candidate will
strengthen our hand in the
Brexit negotiations to get the best deal for
this country, every vote for me and the local
Conservative candidate will be
a vote for a stronger economy and every vote
for me and the local Conservative candidate
will be a vote for a strong and
stable leadership in the national interest,
compared with the coalition of chaos that
we would see under the Labour party.
>> Mr Douglas Carswell (Clacton) (UKIP):
What assurances can the Prime Minister give
to the 3.8 million people who voted UKIP at
the last election that if she is
Prime Minister after 8 June, the United Kingdom
will become a sovereign country again, living
under our own Parliament and
making our own laws?
>> The Prime Minister:
I will give an assurance to all those people
who voted for the United Kingdom to leave
the European Union—and to all
people across the country, regardless of how
they voted, who now want to see this Government
getting on with the job of
Brexit and making a success of it—that we
want to see control of our borders, control
of our laws and control of our
money, and that that is what we will deliver.
>> Mr Speaker:
In wishing the right hon. Gentleman all the
best for the future, I call Sir Simon Burns.
>> Sir Simon Burns (Chelmsford) (Con):
Mr Speaker, may I thank you for that? May
I tell my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister
that, for 30 years, I have had
the privilege and the honour to represent
the great people of Chelmsford? May I tell
her that the great people of
Chelmsford are perspicacious and that they
have always wanted a Government who provide
strong defences, a strong economy
and strong leadership? May I also tell her
that it is the Conservative party under her
strong leadership that will deliver
for this country for the next five years?
>> The Prime Minister:
I thank my right hon. Friend for the significant
contribution that he has made for his constituents
in Chelmsford, in this
House and in government over his period of
time here. He is absolutely right to say that
his constituents will be looking
for strong defences, a strong economy and
the strong leadership that will build a more
secure future for this country, and
it is only a Conservative Government that
can provide that.
>> Alex Salmond (Gordon) (SNP):
In this Brexit world, the Prime Minister is
desperate to obtain trade deals with anybody
or nobody, so the International
Trade Secretary went to the Philippines this
month, where he appeared with the President
and said that he wanted a strong
relationship based on “shared values”.
Can the Prime Minister identify for the House
what shared values she has in common
with President Rodrigo Duterte?
>> The Prime Minister:
The right hon. Gentleman is right to say that,
as we leave the European Union, we want to
ensure that we are a truly
global Britain and that we have trade deals
around the rest of the world. The reason that
we want those trade deals—as
well as the strong, secure, deep and special
partnership with the European Union on trade—is
so that we can ensure
prosperity across the whole of this country
and jobs for ordinary working families.