>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
am sure that the whole House will join me
in offering our condolences to the families
and friends of those who lost their lives
and were injured in the gun attack in Quebec
City on Sunday, and in paying tribute to our
former colleague Tam Dalyell, who died last
Friday. He was an outstanding parliamentarian,
and I am sure that all our thoughts are with
his friends and family.
This morning, I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in the House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Peter Heaton-Jones (North Devon) (Con):
I associate myself with the remarks made by
the Prime Minister and the tribute paid to
the victims in Canada and to the family of
Tam Dalyell.
North Devon is quite rightly concerned that
the current review of health services across
the county may result in the loss of some
acute services at our hospital in Barnstaple.
For some residents, the nearest alternative
could be three hours away. Will my right hon.
Friend assure me that she will listen carefully
to those concerns, because I want to be able
to say to North Devon that we are the party
of the NHS?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for his question. I can reassure him that
this Government are absolutely committed to
ensuring the best possible healthcare for
patients right across the country. I recognise
that concerns have been expressed locally
about the North Devon district hospital. I
understand that there are no specific proposals
at the moment, but I know that the input of
local communities will remain crucial throughout
the process, and I can assure him that of
course it is this party in government that
is putting the extra funding into the NHS
and showing how we value it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): I
join the Prime Minister in offering condolences
to all those who died in the horrific attack,
fuelled by hate, in Quebec, and we should
send our solidarity to everyone in Canada
on this sad occasion.
May I also associate myself with the Prime
Minister’s tribute to the former Member
for West Lothian, and later Linlithgow, Tam
Dalyell? A Labour MP and former Father of
the House, he doggedly fought to expose official
wrongdoing and cover-ups, from the miners
strike to Iraq. I am sure the Prime Minister
would agree that Tam’s scrutiny and contributions
made this House a better place, and may I
recommend to all Members his autobiography
“The Importance of Being Awkward”? [Interruption.]
And I am quite happy to offer my copy to the
Secretary of State for Brexit to have a good
read of it. I am sure that he has probably
already read it.
At last week’s Prime Minister Question Time,
the Prime Minister told the House:
“I am not afraid to speak frankly to a President
of the United States”. What happened?
>>The Prime Minister: First, let me say that
I was not aware of Tam Dalyell’s book “The
Importance of Being Awkward”, but given
the number of resignations that the right
hon. Gentleman has had from his Front Bench,
I suspect that some of his colleagues have
indeed read it.
I am pleased to say to the right hon. Gentleman
that when I visited the United States, I was
able to build on the relationship that we
have with our most important ally and get
some very significant commitments from President
Trump. Crucial among those was a 100% commitment
to NATO—NATO which keeps us safe and keeps
Europe safe too.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Downing Street has not denied
that the Prime Minister was told by the White
House that the Executive order on travel to
the US was imminent, so let us be clear: was
the Prime Minister told about the ban during
her visit, and did she try to persuade President
Trump otherwise?
>>The Prime Minister: On the policy that President
Trump has introduced, this Government are
clear that it is wrong. We would not do it.
In six years as Home Secretary, I never introduced
such a policy. We believe it is divisive and
wrong. If the right hon. Gentleman is asking
me whether I had advance notice of the ban
on refugees, the answer is no. If he is asking
me if I had advance notice that the Executive
order could affect British citizens, the answer
is no. If he is asking if I had advance notice
of the travel restrictions, the answer is,
we all did, because President Trump said in
his election campaign that he was going to
do this. The question is how you respond.
The job of Government is not to chase the
headlines; the job of Government is not to
take to the streets in protest; the job of
Government is to protect the interests of
British citizens, and that is exactly what
we did.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: On the day after the Executive
order was made to ban refugees and visitors
from seven predominantly Muslim countries,
why did the Prime Minister three times refuse
to condemn the ban?
>>The Prime Minister: I have made it very
clear that we believe that this policy is
divisive and wrong, and that it is not a policy
that we would introduce. I have also made
it very clear when asked about this that this
Government have a very different approach
to these issues. On refugees, this Government
have a proud record of the support that we
have given to them, and long may it continue.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Prime Minister said:
“The United States is responsible for the
United States’ policy on refugees.”
But surely it is the responsibility of all
of us to defend the 1951 refugee convention,
which commits this country, the United States
and 142 other states to accept refugees without
regard to their
“race, religion or country of origin.”
President Trump has breached that convention.
Why did she not speak out?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I have made absolutely
clear what the Government’s view on this
policy is. Secondly, as I have just said,
this Government and this country have a proud
record on how we welcome refugees. In recent
years, we have introduced a very particular
scheme to ensure that particularly vulnerable
refugees in Syria can be brought to this country,
and something like 10,000 Syrian refugees
have come to this country since the conflict
began. We are also the second biggest bilateral
donor, helping and supporting refugees in
the region. That is what we are doing. I have
said that the US policy is wrong. We will
take a different view, and we will continue
to welcome refugees to this country.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I also wrote to the Prime
Minister on this issue and received her reply
this morning. I hold in my hand her piece
of paper. She makes no mention of the refugee
convention and does not condemn US action
in that respect.
Last week, I asked the Prime Minister to assure
the House that she would not offer up our
national health service as a “bargaining
chip” in any US trade deal. She gave no
answer. She also refused to rule it out when
asked in the US, so let me ask her a third
time: will she rule out opening up our national
health service to private US healthcare companies—yes
or no?
>>The Prime Minister: I could give a detailed
answer to the right hon. Gentleman’s question,
but a simple and straightforward reply is
what is required: the NHS is not for sale
and it never will be.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I hope that that includes
not having US healthcare companies coming
in to run any part of our national health
service.
President Trump has torn up international
agreements on refugees. He has threatened
to dump international agreements on climate
change. He has praised the use of torture.
He has incited hatred against Muslims. He
has directly attacked women’s rights. Just
what more does he have to do before the Prime
Minister will listen to the 1.8 million people
who have already called for his state visit
invitation to be withdrawn?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman’s
foreign policy is to object to and insult
the democratically elected Head of State of
our most important ally. Let us see what he
would have achieved in the last week. Would
he have been able to protect British citizens
from the impact of the Executive order? No.
Would he have been able to lay the foundations
of a trade deal? No. Would he have got a 100%
commitment to NATO? No. That is what Labour
has to offer this country—less protection
for British citizens, less prosperity, less
safety. He can lead a protest; I am leading
a country.
>>Stuart Andrew (Pudsey) (Con): Today it is
inconceivable that somebody would be prosecuted
based on who and what they are. Will my right
hon. Friend join me in welcoming the posthumous
pardon of some 49,000 men thanks to the Government’s
Turing Bill which was enacted yesterday? Will
she also encourage those who are still alive
to come forward so that their injustices can
be overturned?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to join
my hon. Friend in welcoming an extremely important
change in the law. We committed to it in our
manifesto and have now delivered on it. Passing
Turing’s law has been a long-standing commitment
for the Government. It is momentous and takes
action to right the wrongs of the past. Like
my hon. Friend, I certainly encourage those
still alive to apply to the Home Office to
have their offences disregarded.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): We on the
SNP Benches associate ourselves with all the
comments thus far about the tragic deaths
in Quebec City and about the passing of Tam
Dalyell. Respect for him was held across the
political parties and he served with great
distinction for more than 40 years.
The Prime Minister had a successful international
visit this last week—to Ireland. She spoke
publicly about her commitment—this is important—not
to have a hard border on these islands, to
the continuation of free movement of peoples
on these islands and to protect and enhance
trade. Given that people will be watching
this not just in Britain but in Ireland, will
she take this opportunity to explain how she
will deliver those sensible, important outcomes?
>>The Prime Minister: Those are absolutely
the outcomes that we want to see. I was very
pleased to meet the Taoiseach and to discuss
with him the joint intent that both his Government
and mine have to ensure that we do not see
a return to the borders of the past in Northern
Ireland. We focus on the land border that
is between Northern Ireland and the Republic
of Ireland. Of course, the issue of movements
from Ireland affects other places as well;
it affects ports in Wales and Stranraer. Therefore,
it is an important issue for us and we have
agreed the work that we are going to do together
to deliver what I believe will be as frictionless
a border as possible. Also, one of the objectives
that I set out in my plan for our negotiating
objectives is to retain the common travel
area.
>>Angus Robertson: We on the SNP Benches very
much welcome what the Prime Minister has just
said on all those issues. Of course, we also
welcome the intensifying of negotiations between
the UK Government and the devolved Administrations
ahead of triggering article 50. The Prime
Minister has very helpfully explained that
it is perfectly possible for parts of these
islands to be in the single market, without
hard borders, with free movement of people,
while at the same time protecting and enhancing
trade with one another. That is very, very
welcome, so will she give a commitment to
work with the Irish Government and a commitment
to work with the Scottish Government to deliver
all those things—or will we just have to
get on with it ourselves?
>>The Prime Minister: First, the right hon.
Gentleman is right that following the meeting
of the Joint Ministerial Committee plenary
on Monday morning, we agreed to intensify
discussion on issues related to the bringing
back of powers from Brussels and where those
powers should lie within the UK—to intensify
that in the run-up to the triggering of article
50 and beyond the triggering of article 50.
On the other question, the right hon. Gentleman
really should listen to the answers that are
given, because he is trying to imply something
that is not there. [Hon. Members: “Oh!”]
Yes. We are very clear that we want to see
a frictionless border between Northern Ireland
and the Republic of Ireland, but I am also
clear that one of the objectives of our negotiation
is to see as frictionless a border as possible
between the UK and the rest of the European
Union. Of course, if he is so worried about
having a frictionless border between Scotland
and countries in the EU, he should not want
to take Scotland out of the EU by wanting
to see it independent. [Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. We should not have to
allow for the reaction from the SNP Benches
to every answer before we proceed to the next
question.
>>Mrs Maria Miller (Basingstoke) (Con): EU
nationals provide a vital and expert service
in my local hospital in Basingstoke and, along
with thousands of others, they face an uncertain
future. I know that this is something that
the Prime Minister wants to give priority
to and to sort out. Will we be hearing more
about it in the forthcoming White Paper?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
makes an important point about EU nationals.
I would like to confirm my intention and expectation
that we will be able to offer that reassurance
to EU nationals living in the UK, but I also
want to see reassurance offered to UK nationals
living in the EU. I hope and will be working
to try to ensure that this is an issue we
can deal with at a very early stage in the
negotiations. It was one of the objectives
I set out in the plan. It will be referenced
in the White Paper and I can inform my right
hon. Friend and the House that that White
Paper will be published tomorrow.
>>Jonathan Reynolds (Stalybridge and Hyde)
(Lab/Co-op): Prime Minister, your responses
today have been deeply unsatisfactory. The
President of the United States has advocated
torture, misogyny, racial discrimination,
sexual assault and isolationism. The leaders
of Canada and Germany were able to respond
robustly, but your response was to jump on
a plane as soon as possible to hold his hand.
Does this country not deserve a leader who
is willing to stand up for British values?
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I have issued no response
and the hon. Gentleman not only should not
breach parliamentary protocol but should not
tempt me.
>>The Prime Minister: I will tell you what
standing up for British values is. I and this
Government introduced the first Modern Slavery
Act in this country. I have ensured that stop
and search has reduced, because I do not believe
that anyone on the streets of this country
should be stopped and searched because of
the colour of their skin, and I ensured justice
for the families of Hillsborough.
>>Mrs Theresa Villiers (Chipping Barnet) (Con):
In light of the fact that most of the countries
covered by the Trump ban have a total bar
on the admission of Israeli citizens, should
the protestors not be calling for that ban
to be lifted as well?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my right hon.
Friend for pointing that out. It is absolutely
right that the House should be aware of the
discrimination around the world and of that
ban, particularly for those who are Israeli
citizens. We are consistent: we do not agree
with that approach and it is not one that
we will take. I wait for the day when the
right hon. Member for Islington North (Jeremy
Corbyn) stands up and condemns it too.
>>Chris Elmore (Ogmore) (Lab/Co-op): My constituent
Dianah Kendall suffered a bleed on the brain
in 2012 and has struggled to work since, but
was due to retire in September. Government
changes to her state pension retirement age
mean that she will now not retire until 2022.
This injustice has short-changed 2.6 million
WASPI women and brings shame on this Government.
Will the Prime Minister think again and support
Dianah and the millions of women who deserve
fairness in retirement?
>>The Prime Minister: On the issue of those
who are known as the WASPI campaign, I refer
the hon. Gentleman to the fact that, as I
am sure he knows, we committed more than £1
billion to lessen the impact on those worst
affected, so no one will see their pension
age change by more than 18 months. There is
a wider point: we need to be realistic when
considering pension ages about the fact that
people are living longer. If we want to carry
on having an affordable and sustainable pension
system, we need to equalise the state pension
age for men and women faster and to bring
forward the rise.
>>Will Quince (Colchester) (Con): I welcome
the £450 million announced in the autumn
statement to fund a trial of the digital railway.
Given the new fleet of trains on order and
the economic growth opportunity for our region,
does the Prime Minister agree that the great
eastern main line has the most compelling
case for that pilot?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right about the importance of transport links
for economic growth. I understand that digital
signalling could increase capacity on commuter
trains by up to 40%, hence the investment
of £450 million for trials over the coming
years to which he rightly refers. I know that
the Department for Transport is considering
where those trials should take place, but
we certainly recognise that the great eastern
main line is one area that could benefit from
those improvements.
>>John Nicolson (East Dunbartonshire) (SNP):
A few moments ago, the Prime Minister tried
to claim credit for passing Stonewall’s
Turing Bill. She did not; the Turing Bill
pardons all gay men found guilty of crimes
no longer on the statute book. When will the
Prime Minister follow the Scottish Government
and automatically pardon the living as well
as the dead?
>>The Prime Minister: It was during my time
as Home Secretary that the legislation was
introduced that gives those who are alive
the opportunity to apply to the Home Office
to have those offences that are no longer
on the statute book expunged from their record—
>>John Nicolson: They are not doing it.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman says
that they are not doing it. In this Chamber
today my hon. Friend the Member for Pudsey
(Stuart Andrew) and I have both encouraged
people to come forward and make that application,
and that is a message that we should all put
out.
>>James Duddridge (Rochford and Southend East)
(Con): At the White House, my right hon. Friend
gained some assurances from President Trump
about his commitment to NATO, an achievement
that was welcomed by the Governments of the
Czech Republic, Latvia and Lithuania. Does
my right hon. Friend agree that the way to
engage with President Trump and to win such
agreements is not by insulting our close ally
but by bringing him close, rather than doing
as the Leader of the Opposition demands? If
we reject our closest ally, would that not
leave Britain and our European partners less
safe and less secure?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right. We should never forget that America
is our most important ally. Our relationship
is long standing and American men and women
served and died alongside UK men and women
in two world wars to protect our security
and the security of Europe. If we were not
able to have that relationship and to see
that commitment to NATO, in particular, we
would leave this country and Europe less safe.
>>Deidre Brock (Edinburgh North and Leith)
(SNP): Many were surprised that immediately
after those cosy images with Donald Trump
were taken the Prime Minister chose to meet
the Turkish President, who has been running
an increasingly repressive regime since the
failed coup last summer. Will she confirm
whether she raised any human rights concerns
with President Erdoğan, or, as we turn our
face from Europe, will it be the policy of
post-Brexit Britain to put arms deals before
human rights abuses?
>>The Prime Minister: First, the hon. Lady
should recognise that Turkey is an important
country in relation both to our security and
the issue of migration into Turkey and potentially
into Europe. She will also recognise that
Turkey has, and continues to host, 3 million
refugees from Syria, and I commended the Turkish
Government on the welcome they have given
them. I suggest that she should just have
looked at the press conference I gave after
my discussions with President Erdoğan and
Prime Minister Yildirim, in which I made it
clear that we had condemned the coup but expected
the Turkish Government to support their democratic
institutions, international human rights and
the rule of law.
>>Alec Shelbrooke (Elmet and Rothwell) (Con):
I wholeheartedly congratulate my right hon.
Friend on securing 100% for NATO from the
new US Administration. Will she outline what
she is doing to persuade our other NATO allies
of the importance of achieving what was agreed
at the NATO Wales summit on their obligations?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I thank my hon.
Friend for the work that he does on the NATO
Parliamentary Assembly. I know he is fully
engaged with that. He is right that commitments
were made at the NATO summit in Wales in 2014,
when all our NATO allies committed to spending
2% of their GDP on defence within a decade.
We have seen progress, but I agree with President
Trump that many allies need to go further.
I can assure my hon. Friend that I and other
Ministers across Government raise the issue
regularly with our allies and partners and
will continue to do so.
>>Ruth Cadbury (Brentford and Isleworth) (Lab):
Last week, air pollution in London was worse
than in Beijing. Will the Prime Minister therefore
assure me and my constituents in Osterley,
Brentford and Chiswick that the hugely expensive
proposal to double the capacity of the M4
as it arrives in London will be shelved forthwith?
>>The Prime Minister: I can assure the hon.
Lady that this Government take the issue of
air quality very seriously. A lot of work
has been done. Since 2011 more than £2 billion
has been committed to enable, for example,
bus operators to upgrade their fleets, and
to ensure that changes are made to reduce
pollution from vehicles such as refuse trucks
and fire engines. We do recognise, however,
that more needs to be done. We have seen a
reduction in nitrous oxide from some 17% in
recent years, but we will bring forward proposals
to ensure that we can maintain the air quality
that we all want to see.
>>Richard Benyon (Newbury) (Con): Will my
right hon. Friend show her support for “Brighter
Berkshire”, the campaign as part of the
2017 year of mental health? Will she give
her continued commitment to ensuring that
we have parity between mental health and physical
health in this country?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to endorse
the campaign to which my hon. Friend refers.
It is important that we continue to raise
awareness of the issues around mental health.
The fact the Government have committed to
the parity of esteem between mental and physical
health is important. There is more for us
to do on mental health, and I have already
set out some steps that we want to take. I
commend all those, however, who are working
to raise the issue of mental health and provide
support to those with mental health problems.
>>Mr Stephen Hepburn (Jarrow) (Lab): The Association
of Directors of Adult Social Services has
said that £4.6 billion has been cut from
social care budgets since 2010. Does the Prime
Minister take any responsibility for the pain
and the distress that the Tories have inflicted
on poor, vulnerable old people being denied
their rightful care? Yes or no?
>>The Prime Minister: The Government have
taken a number of steps to increase the funding
available for local authorities to provide
for social care. It is also important that
we ensure that best practice is developed
and put into place across the country. In
some parts of the country the record on social
care and the interaction with hospitals is
better than in others, but the longer-term
issue is for us to ensure that we have a sustainable
system for delivering social care for people
in this country. The Labour party ducked that
issue for 13 years. We are addressing it.
>>Andrea Jenkyns (Morley and Outwood) (Con):
Will my right hon. Friend join me in congratulating
Morley Academy on its recently awarded World
Class Schools quality mark and say how such
awards drive pupil excellence?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to join my
hon. Friend in congratulating the whole team
at Morley Academy on receiving the award,
which I think shows the work that the GORSE
Academies Trust is doing to drive up excellence
and improve outcomes for pupils. We are determined
to drive up standards in schools to ensure
that more children have good school places—a
good school place for every child—so that
they can all reach the sort of level we see
at Morley Academy.
>>Mr David Winnick (Walsall North) (Lab):
How will the thousands of people who lost
their jobs at British Home Stores feel about
the fact that it may take years before the
case of Philip Green, the totally discredited
and disgraced businessperson, results in his
knighthood being taken away or otherwise?
Is it not remarkable? People lose their jobs
and suffer all the consequences, but this
man keeps his billions and his knighthood.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
an important issue. Many Members of this House
have expressed concern about what happened
at BHS and the attitude and approach taken
by Philip Green. Whether a knighthood should
be taken away from someone is a matter for
the relevant committee—I have forgotten
the name—which will be examining the case;
I understand that it is waiting for the investigations
to be completed. This is a matter for an independent
committee and it is up to the committee how
it looks into it.
>>Mr Peter Bone (Wellingborough) (Con): Tonight,
there will be an historic vote in this place,
a vote that I thought I would not see in my
political lifetime: the British Parliament
voting to withdraw from the European Union
under the excellent leadership of the Prime
Minister. Is my right hon. Friend surprised
that Opposition Members who demand time to
discuss the matter and debate it—namely,
the Liberal Democrats—did not even bother
to turn up last night? The Government Benches
were packed, the Scottish National party Benches
were packed, the Democratic Unionist party
Members were here, and there were some Labour
Members. Is that not surprising?
>>The Prime Minister: Throughout my political
career I have fought Liberal Democrats, and
nothing that they do ever surprises me, but
I join my hon. Friend in commending the Bill
before the House. This House has a very simple
decision to take. We gave the right of judgment
on this matter to the British people, and
they made their choice: they want to leave
the EU. The question every Member must ask
themselves as they go through the Lobby tonight
is: do they trust the people?
>>Mr Speaker: Well, the right hon. Gentleman
is here now, so let us hear the fellow—Tim
Farron.
>>Hon. Members: Hear, hear!
>>Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
Who would have guessed it, Mr Speaker? We
are here now, asking the questions—[Interruption]—asking
the
questions about the future of our country
and Brexit that a strong Leader of the Opposition
should be asking—
>>Hon. Members: Where were you?
>>Mr Speaker: Order. [Interruption.] Mr Knight,
I am very worried about you. You recently
suffered from a bad leg. With all that shouting,
you will be suffering from a bad head. Calm
yourself man!
>>Tim Farron: The Prime Minister will return
at some point with a deal with Europe that
our people will have to live with for decades
to come, especially our young people, 73%
of whom voted to remain. Nobody knows what
that deal will look like, but someone will
get to agree it. Should it be her Government,
should it be this Parliament, or should it
be—as I believe it should—the British
people?
>>The Prime Minister: I have already said
that there will be a vote on the deal in this
Parliament. [Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Mr Shelbrooke, calm yourself.
You are in a state of excessive excitement,
even by your standards.
>>Nigel Adams (Selby and Ainsty) (Con): It
is quite difficult to follow that, Mr Speaker,
but back in the real world—[Laughter.]
In December 2015, my constituency suffered
terrible flooding, especially in the town
of Tadcaster. The damage became worse when
the bridge collapsed, separating the town.
Thankfully, the bridge will be reopened, hopefully
this week. Will the Prime Minister join me
in thanking all those who were involved in
the restoration of the bridge and, most importantly,
the residents of Tadcaster, who have had a
terrible year?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to join my
hon. Friend in commending and thanking not
only all those who worked so hard to restore
the bridge at Tadcaster, but the people of
Tadcaster, who have had to put up with disruption
and inconvenience for such a long time. I
am sure that those people will all welcome
the return of the bridge, and we commend all
those who have ensured that that has happened.
>>John Woodcock (Barrow and Furness) (Lab/Co-op):
The news revealed yesterday that Toshiba is
reviewing its investment in the Moorside nuclear
power plant, which puts a huge question mark
over not only 21,000 jobs in Cumbria but the
future of our nation’s energy security.
What will the Prime Minister do personally
to ensure that the deal stays on track?
>>The Prime Minister: I assure the hon. Gentleman
that both the Business Secretary and I have
involvement in a number of deals and possible
deals around the nuclear industry. We are
keen to ensure that those jobs are brought
to the United Kingdom and that such deals
are kept on track. I assure him of the Government’s
commitment.
>>Jo Churchill (Bury St Edmunds) (Con): This
week the Danish drug firm Novo Nordisk invested
£115 million in the UK to further research
into type 2 diabetes. Will the Prime Minister
join me in welcoming that investment as well
as the academics and scientists involved,
many of whom are from the EU and around the
world and will appreciate the assurance she
gave earlier? Will she also work with me to
ensure that any innovations and new treatments
get to patients as quickly as possible?
>>The Prime Minister: As my hon. Friend will
probably understand, I recognise this issue
particularly personally, although I am a type
1 diabetic rather than type 2. Any investment
in diabetes research is to be welcomed, and
when new solutions and support for diabetics
are found, it is important that they get to
people as quickly as possible. A significant
number of people in this country suffer from
type 2 diabetes, and the figures show that
there is a great risk that the number will
increase significantly in the coming years.
We need to do all that we can not only to
prevent people from becoming type 2 diabetics
in the first place, but to support those who
have that condition so that people suffer
from fewer complications and are able to manage
their lives.
>>Ms Tasmina Ahmed-Sheikh (Ochil and South
Perthshire) (SNP): Today is World Hijab Day.
Will the Prime Minister join me in recognising
the right of Muslim women to wear the hijab
if they wish, without fear, and indeed the
right of all women everywhere to wear what
they want, when they want? Will she also commit
to standing up for the right to refuge for
men, women and children wherever they may
be, regardless of their religion?
>>The Prime Minister: On the hon. Lady’s
second point, it is absolutely the case that
this country welcomes refuges to the United
Kingdom, and we do so regardless of their
religion—there is no question of discriminating
on religion.
I am absolutely in line with the hon. Lady
on her point about wearing the hijab. I believe
that what a woman wears is a woman’s choice.
>>Sir Julian Brazier (Canterbury) (Con): Russian
armed forces regularly carry out large-scale
exercises, including with nuclear-capable
equipment, on the borders of eastern Europe.
Does my right hon. Friend agree that the American
commitment to NATO is absolutely pivotal to
protect the countries of eastern Europe from
going the same way as eastern Ukraine?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely agree with
my hon. Friend. The 100% commitment to NATO
that President Trump has given is crucial
to ensuring that we can provide for the security
of this country and others in Europe, especially
those in eastern Europe on the border with
Russia. I noted that my hon. Friend the Member
for Rochford and Southend East (James Duddridge)
referred to the fact that the Governments
of the Czech Republic, Latvia and Lithuania
had welcomed that 100% commitment. I am pleased
to say that we are playing our part, as about
800 troops will be going to Poland and Estonia
this year as a sign of NATO’s strength and
our belief in keeping those countries free
and democratic.
>>Naz Shah (Bradford West) (Lab): In 2015,
my constituent Samia Shahid was lured to her
death in Pakistan, where she was brutally
raped and murdered. Will the Prime Minister
join me in reiterating the commitment of this
House and this country that we will not tolerate
violence against women, and encourage the
Pakistani Government to continue in their
efforts to get justice for our British girl,
Samia Shahid?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady raises
a very tragic case, and our deepest sympathies
are with Samia’s husband following her tragic
death last year. We do not interfere in the
legal processes of another country, but I
understand from the Foreign Office that the
Pakistani police have arrested two people
and charged them with murder. The Foreign
Office has provided assistance to Samia’s
husband and will continue to do so. I am sure
it will keep the hon. Lady informed, and I
understand that the Home Secretary will meet
the hon. Lady soon to discuss this issue.