>>Kelvin Hopkins (Luton North) (Lab): If she
will list her official engagements for Wednesday
18 January.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): This
morning I had meetings with ministerial colleagues
and others. In addition to my duties in this
House I will have further such meetings later
today.
>>Kelvin Hopkins: Thousands of babies who
are born each year are damaged for life by
alcohol consumed in pregnancy. Patients affected
by alcohol put immense pressure on the national
health service, and alcohol is a primary factor
in domestic violence and attacks on women.
Does the Prime Minister recognise the seriousness
of the country’s alcohol problems—the
damage to lives and the billions in costs
to the public purse—and will she instruct
her Government now to address these problems
effectively and as a matter of urgency?
>>The Prime Minister: I can certainly say
to the hon. Gentleman that I recognise the
problems that alcohol causes. He particularly
referenced not just problems for pregnant
women, but the part that alcohol often plays
in domestic violence and abuse. That was why,
when I was Home Secretary, we produced an
alcohol strategy and worked on the issue of
alcohol. The Government continue to recognise
the importance of this issue and to work on
it.
>>Mr Laurence Robertson (Tewkesbury) (Con):
Will the Prime Minister join me in paying
tribute to the NHS staff who provide us with
such magnificent treatment day in, day out?
Does she agree that people who miss NHS appointments
without cancelling them cost the NHS a great
deal of money and also take up slots that
would otherwise be used by other patients?
Will she consider how she might let those
people know about the inconvenience that they
are causing to the NHS?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend makes
two important points. First, I am very pleased
to join him in paying tribute to the dedication
and hard work of all those who work in our
national health service. Secondly, he is right
to point out that if somebody misses an appointment,
that is a cost to the NHS. There are a number
of ways in which this is being dealt with.
Some hospitals send out text messages that
not only remind people of their appointment,
but tell them how much it costs if they miss
it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): Yesterday
the Prime Minister snubbed Parliament and
snubbed the Brexit Committee’s recommendation
to bring forward a White Paper, while at the
same time describing the referendum as
“a vote to restore…our parliamentary democracy”.
This is about our jobs, living standards and
future prosperity; why will it not be scrutinised
by this House?
>>The Prime Minister: What I did yesterday
was to set out a plan for a global Britain.
I set out a plan that will put the divisions
of last year behind us, and that shows a vision
for a stronger, fairer, more united, more
outward-looking, prosperous, tolerant, independent
and truly global Britain. It was a vision
that will shape a stronger future and build
a better Britain.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Restoring parliamentary democracy
while sidelining Parliament—it is not so
much the Iron Lady as the Irony Lady.
Yesterday the Prime Minister finally provided
some detail. May I urge her to stop her threats
of a bargain basement Brexit—a low-pay tax
haven on the shores of Europe? It would not
necessarily damage the EU, but it would certainly
damage this country, businesses, jobs and
public services. She demeans herself, her
office and our country’s standing by making
such threats.
>>The Prime Minister: What I set out yesterday
was a plan for a global Britain, bringing
prosperity to this country and jobs to people,
and spreading economic growth across the country.
Yesterday we learned a little more of the
right hon. Gentleman’s thinking on this
issue. He said:
“She has said, ‘leave the single market,’
but at the same time says she wants to have
access to the single market. I’m not quite
sure how that’s going to go down in Europe.
I think we have to have a deal that ensures
we have access to the market.”
I’ve got a plan; he doesn’t have a clue.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Prime Minister was the
one who made the threat about slashing corporation
tax. If we reduce corporation tax to the lowest
common denominator, this country loses £120
billion in revenue. How, then, do we fund
public services?
Last year the Prime Minister said that leaving
the single market could make trade deals “considerably
harder” and that
“while we could certainly negotiate our
own trade agreements, there would be no guarantee
that they would be on terms as good as those
we enjoy now”,
but yesterday she offered us only vague guarantees.
Does she now disagree with herself?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
might also have noticed that when I spoke
in the remain campaign, I said that if we
voted to leave the European Union, the sky
would not fall in. Look at what has happened
to our economic situation since we voted to
leave the European Union.
The right hon. Gentleman talks about the future
of the economy. I want us to be an outward-looking
nation trading around the world, and bringing
prosperity and jobs into the United Kingdom.
The one thing that would be bad for the economy
is the answers that the right hon. Gentleman
has. He wants a cap on wages, no control on
immigration and to borrow an extra £500 billion.
That would not lead to prosperity; it would
lead to no jobs, no wages and no skills.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Chancellor said after
the referendum that to lose single market
access would be “catastrophic”. A few
days later, the Health Secretary said:
“The first part of the plan must be clarity
that we will remain in the single market”.
The Prime Minister said something about “frictionless”
access to the single market and a bespoke
customs union deal. Could she give us a little
bit of certainty and clarity about this? Has
she ruled out paying any kind of fee to achieve
access to what she describes as a “frictionless”
market?
>>The Prime Minister: Access to the single
market was exactly what I was talking about
yesterday in my speech. One of the key objectives
is that we negotiate a free trade agreement
with the European Union that gives us the
widest possible access for trading with, and
operating within, the European Union.
The right hon. Gentleman talks about frictionless
access. Actually, this was a separate point
about frictionless borders in relation to
the customs issue—a very important issue
for us regarding the relationship between
Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland.
The Taoiseach and I, and all parties, are
absolutely on a single page about this. We
want to ensure that we have the best possible
arrangement that does not lead to the borders
of the past for Northern Ireland.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The question was: will we
have to pay for access to the market or not?
The Prime Minister has not given an answer
to that.
Yesterday the Prime Minister set out a wish
list on immigration, referring to skills shortages
and high-skill migration. Does she now disagree
with the Secretary of State for Environment,
Food and Rural Affairs, who told an employers’
conference, “Don’t worry. You can still
have cheap EU labour after we leave the European
Union”?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
talks about access. Yes, the whole point is
that we will negotiate a free trade agreement
with the European Union that is about the
best possible access for British business
to operate in European Union member states
and for European businesses to operate here
in the United Kingdom. It is about sitting
down and negotiating the best possible deal
for the United Kingdom. That is what I am
committed to, and it is what the Government
are going to deliver.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was about how
much we are going to have to pay to have access
to the market—still no answer.
Yesterday the Prime Minister talked about
the pressure put on public services by migration.
May I just remind her—the hon. Member for
Tewkesbury (Mr Robertson) referred to this
earlier—that at the moment there are 55,000
EU citizens working in our national health
service, helping to treat all the people of
this country? There are 80,000 care workers
helping our—mainly elderly—people and
there are 5,000 teachers educating our children.
The real pressure on public services comes
from a Government who slashed billions from
the social care budget, who are cutting the
schools budget, and who are closing A&E departments,
walk-in centres and Sure Start centres. Instead
of threatening to turn Britain into an offshore
tax haven, let us welcome those who contribute
to our public services and fund those public
services properly so that we have the fully
functioning NHS that we all need and deserve.
>>The Prime Minister: I made it clear yesterday
that we value those who have come to the United
Kingdom and contribute to our economy and
society. There will still be people coming
to the United Kingdom from the European Union
when we leave the EU. The crucial issue is
that it is this Government who will be making
decisions about our immigration system for
people from the European Union. Yet again,
I say to the right hon. Gentleman that there
is indeed a difference between us—it is
very simple. When I look at the issue of Brexit—or,
indeed, at any other issue, such as the national
health service or social care—I consider
the issue, I set out my plan and I stick to
it. It is called leadership; he should try
it sometime.
>>Karl MᶜCartney (Lincoln) (Con): Yesterday
was a day for being bold and ambitious, and
I am sure that my right hon. Friend noted
during her busy day that Lincoln City football
club followed her lead last night, progressing
to the fourth round of the FA cup. While I
warmly welcome the PM’s speech yesterday,
I also note her recent comments about white
working-class boys and university. In the
past 10 years, half a million fewer males
than females have gone to university, males’
exam results have been lower at all levels,
and fewer males than females have started
apprenticeships. Despite my raising this issue
in a Westminster Hall debate with Education
Ministers four months ago, nothing has happened.
When can we expect to see practical action
on closing the gender education gap?
>>The Prime Minister: I join my hon. Friend
in congratulating Lincoln City on their victory
last night. I think it was a fitting tribute
to Graham Taylor that they won that match.
My hon. Friend raises an important point.
I have indeed highlighted the issue of particularly
white working-class boys, who are the group
in society least likely to go to university.
We are committed to making sure that every
child gets the opportunity to fulfil their
potential. That is about ensuring that apprenticeships
are accessible as possible. I am pleased to
tell my hon. Friend that the proportion of
apprenticeships started by males has increased
this year to almost 50%, and also that universities
expect to spend more than £800 million this
year on improving access and success for disadvantaged
students. We want everybody to achieve their
potential, whatever their background and whatever
their gender.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): Shortly after
the Prime Minister confirmed that she wants
to take the UK out of the single European
market, the Scottish Parliament voted by a
large cross-party majority to remain in the
single European market, just as a large majority
of people in Scotland voted to remain in the
European Union. The Prime Minister said that
Scotland is an equal partner in the United
Kingdom. Does she still believe this is true
or is she just stringing the people of Scotland
along?
>>The Prime Minister: I refer the right hon.
Gentleman to my speech yesterday, in which
I reiterated my commitment to work with the
devolved Administrations to ensure their voice
is heard and their interests are taken into
account as we proceed along the path of negotiating
our exit from the European Union. I specifically
referenced the Scotland plan. I understand
that the Welsh Government will be producing
a plan for Wales for us to look at, too. The
Scotland plan will, I believe, be considered
tomorrow by the Joint Ministerial Committee
on European negotiations. We will be looking
at it seriously and working with the Scottish
Government on the proposals they bring forward.
>>Angus Robertson: Scotland’s leading economic
forecaster says that real wages will fall—[Interruption.]
We have Tories jeering and cheering when the
forecast for people’s income is that it
is likely to drop by £2,000 and that 80,000
people may lose their jobs in Scotland as
a result of the Prime Minister’s hard Tory
Brexit plan. Does the Prime Minister believe
that this is a price worth paying for her
“Little Britain” Brexit?
>>The Prime Minister: I repeat what I said
earlier: we will work to ensure we get the
best possible deal in terms of access to the
single market, and continue to co-operate
in partnership with the remaining 27 member
states of the European Union. The right hon.
Gentleman once again talks about the possibility
of a negative impact on Scotland if Scotland
were not part of the single market. His party
is dedicated to taking Scotland out of the
single market by taking it out of the United
Kingdom.
>>Richard Fuller (Bedford) (Con): This week,
directors of our larger companies have been
told by investors to rein in senior executive
pay, which is too often distorted by long-term
incentive plans that are too complex to manage
and too excessive in their rewards. Will my
right hon. Friend look at such schemes as
part of her corporate governance review?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important issue. I am pleased to say that
the Government have already taken some action
on executive pay: giving shareholders the
power to veto pay policies, forcing companies
to disclose the pay of their board directors
and introducing tough transparency measures
for banks. I want to build on that, which
is why we published a Green Paper on how to
strengthen shareholders’ influence over
executive pay and introduced greater transparency.
I look forward to receiving representations
from my hon. Friend on this issue.
>>Kirsty Blackman (Aberdeen North) (SNP):
Will the Prime Minister provide a commitment
today that no part of the great repeal Bill
will be subject to English votes for English
laws?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady might
recognise that the great repeal Bill will
deal with a number of complex issues. At its
heart will be the repeal of the European Communities
Act 1972. As we look at the Bill and at negotiating
our way out of the European Union, we will
need to look at the whole issue of reserved
matters and devolved matters, but there are
many aspects—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. Members of the Scottish
National party, led by the right hon. Member
for Moray (Angus Robertson) on the Front Bench,
who is supposed to be a statesmanlike figure,
should demonstrate some calm and reserve while
they are being answered by the Prime Minister.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady knows
full well that if any part of proposed legislation
brought before this House applies only to
England, it will be subject to English votes
for English laws.
>>Nadine Dorries (Mid Bedfordshire) (Con):
May I congratulate the Prime Minister on her
delivery yesterday of an historic, definitive,
pragmatic, outward-looking speech that saw
the pound rise to its highest level in two
years and the FTSE up today? Does she agree
that the strong and prosperous UK she has
planned would be a nightmare for the Leader
of the Opposition and the EU ruling class?
>>The Prime Minister: I agree with my hon.
Friend. A strong and prosperous Britain is
exactly what we want to build as we leave
the EU. It is only a pity that the Labour
party seems uninterested in doing that, but
wants to do the exact opposite and bring this
economy down.
>>Chris Bryant (Rhondda) (Lab): If she will
visit the Rhondda.
>>The Prime Minister: I always enjoy my visits
to Wales, and I hope to visit Wales in the
future.
>>Chris Bryant: That is not quite an answer
to whether she will visit the Rhondda. I hope
she will; I am happy to accommodate her—I
can do bacon and eggs. More importantly, I
could take her to see the best brass band
in the world, the Cory band, or, for that
matter, I could take her to the local food
bank, based in the closed-down Conservative
club. Since 2010, the Government have closed
the local courts, tax office, Department for
Work and Pensions office and driving centre,
and now they intend to close all the tax offices
in Wales and centralise them in Cardiff. We
in the valleys feel ignored by the Government.
May I beg her to change direction and start
putting Government offices in the small towns,
villages and valleys of this country?
>>The Prime Minister: The last time I looked,
Cardiff was actually in Wales—the hon. Gentleman
says we are taking offices out of Wales and
putting them in Cardiff. The whole point of
what Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs is
doing is to move from outdated offices to
large, modern regional centres, which will
make it possible to modernise its ways of
working, make tax collection more efficient
and actually improve its customer service.
>>Chris Green (Bolton West) (Con): I welcome
my right hon. Friend’s speech setting out
a plan for global Britain. It clearly shows
that those on the Government Benches are listening
to the British people. Will she commend this
approach to the council leaders now considering
the Greater Manchester spatial framework consultation
responses, as they need to listen to the people,
give us better infrastructure and protect
our green spaces?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for his comments and for raising this issue.
I understand that the consultation on the
spatial framework closed earlier this week
and that there has been huge interest among
local people. I echo his comment that it is
absolutely right that local leaders should
take into account all the representations
made.
>>Ian Blackford (Ross, Skye and Lochaber)
(SNP): In the UK, we have 14 regional markets
for electricity distribution, and highlanders
and islanders are facing higher prices because
of where we live. Electricity distribution
charges for the north of Scotland are an eye-watering
84% higher than those for London. The Prime
Minister talks about fairness. Will she introduce
a universal market for electricity pricing
and stop penalising highlanders and islanders?
Those of us who live in the coldest, windiest
places are discriminated against by her Government,
and it must end.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman draws
attention to the fact that geography of course
has an impact on these matters. He talks about
living in the coldest and windiest places,
and obviously one interesting issue in Scotland
is the opportunity for renewables there. I
can tell him, however, that we are looking
at making sure that energy markets in the
UK are indeed working properly.
>>Andrew Selous (South West Bedfordshire)
(Con): I am pleased that the Prime Minister
has said that she will take the necessary
action on air quality to deal with the 40,000
premature deaths it causes across our country
every year. I know she believes in her Government
leading by example, so will she make sure
that all diesel cars are removed from the
Government Car Service as soon as possible?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right that improving air quality is a priority
for the Government. We are determined to cut
harmful emissions and have committed money
since 2011 to supporting the take-up of low-emission
vehicles. The Government Car Service is working
to remove diesel vehicles from its fleet.
It has so far replaced a quarter of its vehicles
with petrol hybrid cars, and of course its
work continues to remove those diesel vehicles.
>>Mr Barry Sheerman (Huddersfield) (Lab/Co-op):
Is the Prime Minister aware that I totally
agree with what she said yesterday—[Interruption.]
Wait for it. I agree that we in this House
have a real responsibility to ensure that
our children and grandchildren have a bright
future, but is she aware that dark clouds
are looming on the horizon—intolerance,
racism across Europe and the foundering and
flux of many of our great institutions that
have kept peace and prosperity since the last
world war? I speak here of the United Nations,
NATO and, indeed, the European Union. Are
we fit for purpose in keeping this country
safe and secure in that world?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely recognise
the important issue that the hon. Gentleman
has raised. It is precisely as we move out
of the European Union that the United Kingdom
will be more outward looking. We will look
globally. We want to ensure that we continue
to play our part in the United Nations and
that the UN is able to do the job that everybody
wants it to do. NATO has obviously been the
most important bulwark when it comes to maintaining
safety and security across the European continent.
That is why we are continuing to support NATO.
British troops are in Estonia, and British
forces are in Poland and Romania, which shows
our continuing commitment to NATO. The thrust
of my speech yesterday was that we want a
strong strategic partnership with the European
Union. We want access to the single market
through a free trade agreement, but we also
want to continue to work with the EU on justice
and security matters. Now is not a time to
co-operate less; it is a time to co-operate
more.
>>Paul Scully (Sutton and Cheam) (Con): I
am delighted at the third-round FA cup replay,
in which Sutton United won 3-1 against Wimbledon.
However, the pressing issue—what would make
us really happy—is being able to get to
work on a day-to-day basis. Does the Prime
Minister share my cautious optimism that a
return to talks by ASLEF and Southern can
provide a long-lasting solution for hard-pressed
commuters?
>>The Prime Minister: As a former Wimbledon
councillor, I am not sure that I quite share
the enthusiasm of my hon. Friend for the defeat
of AFC Wimbledon. On the point about the train
strikes, yes, I do; and I hope that those
sitting around the table are going to ensure
that an agreement will be reached to enable
passengers to be able to get on with their
lives and their jobs, and not suffer the misery
that was brought about by the strike in the
first place.
>>Siobhain McDonagh (Mitcham and Morden) (Lab):
I agree with the Prime Minister and disagree
with the hon. Member for Sutton and Cheam
(Paul Scully) about last night’s AFC Wimbledon
result. If the Prime Minister really believes
that GP surgeries should be open seven days
a week, 12 hours a day, will she be my guest
at a residents’ meeting against a Department
of Health diktat that will close the 6,000-strong
Mitcham Wilson surgery? Even better, will
she just tell her Government to stop cuts
to GP services, which force thousands to attend
hard-pressed A&amp;Es such as those at St
George’s and St Helier, or is she just happy
to oversee the possible collapse of the NHS
on her watch?
>>The Prime Minister: I might remind the hon.
Lady that she and I sat on a council together
where we tried to keep Wimbledon actually
playing in Wimbledon, or at least in the borough
of Merton rather than moving elsewhere.
On the point about GP services, GPs are part
of the solution for the NHS in the future.
That is why we have seen more GPs coming into
the NHS and 5,000 more are being trained and
will be in place by 2020. We want to ensure
that GPs are open and providing services at
times when the patients want to access them.
>>Anna Soubry (Broxtowe) (Con): It was quite
clear from the Prime Minister’s speech yesterday
that she seeks to build a Brexit consensus
and to bring our country back together. I
thank her for that. To that end, and indeed
to strengthen the Prime Minister’s negotiating
hand, before article 50 is triggered, will
she please at least consider publishing all
those 12 objectives in a White Paper so that
we can debate them here in this place on behalf
of all our constituents?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely understand
my right hon. Friend’s point about Parliament’s
desire to be able to debate the objectives
that I set out very clearly in my plan yesterday.
One of the objectives and principles I set
was about certainty and clarity. It continues
to be the Government’s intention that we
will provide clarity whenever it is possible,
and we will ensure that, at appropriate times,
both the public and Parliament are kept informed
and are able properly to consider and scrutinise
these issues.
>>Mrs Louise Ellman (Liverpool, Riverside)
(Lab/Co-op): While dedicated and talented
staff at Royal Liverpool University hospital’s
accident and emergency department struggle
to find beds for sick people, about 135 patients
cannot be discharged solely because of Government
cuts in social care budgets. When will the
Government recognise their responsibilities,
and not try to blame GPs for a problem of
their Government’s own making?
>>The Prime Minister: There is pressure on
social care. I have accepted and recognised
that in the House. The Government have recognised
it, and have provided additional funding through
the Better Care Fund and the social care precept.
This year Liverpool raised £2.8 million from
the precept, and it will receive more than
£48 million on top of that from the improved
Better Care Fund by 2019-20. However, this
is not just a question of money; it is a question
of ensuring that we have a sustainable social
care system for the future, and that is what
the Government are working on.
>>Alistair Burt (North East Bedfordshire)
(Con): May I commend my right hon. Friend
for what she said yesterday, and not least
for her constructive tone and constructive
approach to the European Union and its future?
That was in marked contrast to what we have
heard from others over the years, from many
different quarters in the United Kingdom.
Will my right hon. Friend confirm that that
constructive tone will remain, as the best
base for securing an agreement between us
and the EU that is in our mutual interest?
Will she also confirm that the default position
of “no deal” will remain a default position,
and that the Government will not be persuaded
to make it their preferred option?
>>The Prime Minister: Absolutely. We want
to get that good deal and we expect to be
able to get that good deal, and, as my right
hon. Friend says, it is through good will
and a positive approach on both sides of the
negotiations that we will achieve it.
I am very clear about the fact that the United
Kingdom wants to see a continuing, strong
European Union of 27 member states. We want
a strong strategic partnership with that European
Union, and, of course, we want to continue
to work bilaterally with individual member
states. I made that point to a number of European
leaders yesterday when I spoke to them after
my speech. I said that we wanted to approach
this in a positive and optimistic fashion,
because I believe that a deal that is good
for the UK will be a deal that is good for
the European Union.
>>Louise Haigh (Sheffield, Heeley) (Lab):
This week the national auditor revealed the
abject failures in the Concentrix fiasco which
had resulted in thousands of people being
wrongly denied their tax credit. That was
not one rogue contractor, but a system designed
by the Government to pursue and chase down
claimants for profit. Does the Prime Minister
agree with the chief executive of HMRC that
payment by results has no place in our welfare
system? Will she review this model, or will
she wait for the next scandal to hit vulnerable
people?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise that many
people received a poor service from Concentrix.
This is not the first time that that has been
highlighted in the Chamber. It was not acceptable,
and I apologise for the worry and distress
that was caused to people. We have been very
clear about the service operated by Concentrix.
HMRC will learn the lessons from that contract,
and it remains committed to providing a high-quality
service. It will not use a private sector
supplier to undertake tax credit error and
fraud checks again.
>>Mr Kenneth Clarke (Rushcliffe) (Con): My
right hon. Friend the Member for Broxtowe
(Anna Soubry) mentioned the speech that the
Prime Minister made yesterday. In that speech,
she confirmed her commitment to parliamentary
democracy, and I assume that she therefore
accepts the long-standing convention that
the Executive—the Government—are continuously
accountable to the House for the policies
that they are pursuing. Will she clarify whether
she intends to make any further statements
of policy intentions to the House, and whether
she expects the House to have an opportunity
to vote its approval for those policies earlier
than two years from now, when the whole negotiation
has been completed?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. and learned
Friend has raised a matter that has also been
raised not only by our right hon. Friend the
Member for Broxtowe (Anna Soubry), but by
others as well. Yesterday my right hon. Friend
the Secretary of State for Exiting the European
Union spent two hours answering questions
in the House, and there will be a further
debate on matters relating to exiting the
European Union later today. There have been
a number of such debates already, dealing
with issues that are part of the objectives
that we have set.
We shall have to consider the result of the
decision of the Supreme Court, which may,
if it goes against the Government, require
legislation. There will be an opportunity
in the great repeal Bill to consider a number
of issues relating to exiting the EU, but
as for voting on the actual deal that we have,
we cannot do so until we know what it is.
That is why I said yesterday that Parliament
would have a vote when we knew what the deal
was.
>>Dr Eilidh Whiteford (Banff and Buchan) (SNP):
The Prime Minister’s passing reference to
the interests of Spanish fishermen in her
speech yesterday rather let the cat out of
the bag that our fishing opportunities are
already on the table as a bargaining chip
before the Brexit negotiations have even started,
so what exactly does the Prime Minister want
to offer the Spanish fishermen?
>>The Prime Minister: I made the very simple
point yesterday that this negotiation is not
just about the United Kingdom; there will
be others in the European Union who will be
looking to ensure that the deal we get is
good for the UK and good for the EU. But I
have to say to the hon. Lady that if she in
any sense thinks that continued membership
of the common fisheries policy is what we
should be looking for, that is certainly not
the case, and it is certainly one of the things
people voted against.
>>Jeremy Lefroy (Stafford) (Con): The people
of Staffordshire and Stoke-on-Trent are again
being confronted with the possible loss of
emergency services in Stafford or Burton,
when our acute hospitals are constantly under
intense pressure. Does the Prime Minister
agree with me, our hon. Friend the Member
for Burton (Andrew Griffiths) and other local
MPs that closing A&Es is no way to deal with
increased real—not imagined—need?
>>The Prime Minister: The important issue
is the level of service that is available
to people in any particular local area. That
is why the sustainability and transformation
plans that are being considered and have been
published are being taken into account and
being considered at a local level, so that
local clinicians and local people will be
able to agree what is best in their particular
area.
>>Gordon Marsden (Blackpool South) (Lab):
Last Friday I went to Blackpool Victoria hospital
where the number of people waiting 12 hours
or more in A&amp;E doubled last year, with
100 of them aged 90 or over. Trust managers
told me that the biggest factor in delays
is discharging patients who cannot get community
care, and my local paper said that Government
cuts have eroded support for them. Will the
Prime Minister stop waffling about her shared
society, listen to her own budget watchdog
saying that we will need £30 billion for
older people in the next 10 years, and put
that money not into corporation tax cuts but
into local adult care and the NHS?
>>The Prime Minister: Just looking at the
figures on what has happened in health in
the hon. Gentleman’s area, I see that there
are more doctors in his NHS foundation trust
and significantly more nurses, but the—[Interruption.]
I know what the hon. Gentleman is talking
about and I am about to comment on it, but
the hon. Member for Ashton-under-Lyne (Angela
Rayner), who is shouting from a sedentary
position, might have recognised that he started
off talking about the NHS, which is what I
am also commenting on. [Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I am not going to allow
an exchange across the Dispatch Box or across
the House at this point. The Prime Minister
was asked a question [Interruption.] Order.
I require no help from the hon. Member for
Birmingham, Perry Barr (Mr Mahmood), which
is of zilch value. The Prime Minister will
answer, and she will be heard with courtesy,
including by the hon. Gentleman.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Member for
Blackpool South (Gordon Marsden) asked me
about pressures on the national health service.
We are seeing more doctors and nurses in his
Blackpool Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation
Trust, and health funding in the hon. Gentleman’s
area will be £3 billion this year, and that
will be rising with a further £450 million
by 2020-21.
As I have said in this House before, we are
putting extra money into social care. We are
giving local authorities the opportunity to
raise more money and spend it on social care.
But this is not just about more money; it
is about ensuring best practice is spread
throughout the country and it is about a long-term
solution to sustainable social care for the
future, an issue that has been ducked by Governments,
including a Labour Government for 13 years.
>>Matt Warman (Boston and Skegness) (Con):
On Friday the east coast of England faced
the threat of a tidal surge that endangered
tens of thousands of homes and thousands of
lives. A simple change in the weather meant
that flooding was averted, but will the Prime
Minister join me in praising the response
of the emergency services in planning ahead,
involving the Army, the Coastguard, the fire
and ambulance services and the police, to
make sure that the best possible plans were
made? Will she further join me in making sure
that the public know that in future these
warnings should always be taken seriously?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important point, and I am happy to join
him in commending the action of all those
in the emergency services, in our armed forces
and in local authorities who worked so hard
to ensure that this problem was dealt with.
As he said, a change in the weather took place,
but it is crucial that when these warnings
are given, people recognise that they are
given for the very good reason that there
is concern about the danger that could take
place. The efforts that were put in protected
tens of thousands of properties, and I am
pleased to see that we have learned from the
work done on previous flooding incidents.
The work between the emergency services, local
services and the armed forces was much better
co-ordinated than has perhaps been the case
in the past, so we have been able to learn
from the flooding in the past.
>>Meg Hillier (Hackney South and Shoreditch)
(Lab/Co-op): In response to the right hon.
Member for Broxtowe (Anna Soubry), the Prime
Minister talked about her desire to give clarity
around our exit from the EU. Many of my constituents
are European citizens who are paying tax and
bringing up their families here. What assurance
can she give them about their future, particularly
if they change employer or are freelancers?
>>The Prime Minister: One of the objectives
I set out in my speech yesterday was something
I have said before about the guaranteeing
of rights for EU citizens living here in the
UK, but I also want to see the rights of UK
citizens living in the 27 member states being
guaranteed. I remain open, and I encourage
others across Europe to agree with me that
this is an issue we should look at as early
as possible in order to give people the confidence
and reassurance that the hon. Lady is looking
for .
>>Simon Hoare (North Dorset) (Con): In supporting
my right hon. Friend’s endeavours in facing
the difficult challenges in social care and
the national health service, may I invite
her to endorse the concept and continuance
of community hospitals in our market towns
across the country? Those hospitals, including
the Westminster Memorial hospital in Shaftesbury
in my constituency, provide a vital piece
of the jigsaw in our national health service.
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure that the Westminster
Memorial hospital in Shaftesbury is providing
good services for local people. The structure
of local services is of course a matter for
discussion at local level, and it is crucial
that local clinicians and others agree that
we have a safe and secure service for people
and that they are provided with the NHS services
that they need at the most appropriate level.
I fully accept my hon. Friend’s point that
we often think only about the major district
general hospitals and acute hospitals when
actually the NHS is made up of many different
parts. We need to ensure that patients are
being treated at the most appropriate level
for their needs.
>>Hywel Williams (Arfon) (PC): How can abandoning
membership of a customs union that takes 68%
of Wales’s exports—including, crucially,
90% of our food and drink exports—and that
supports 200,000 jobs cause anything other
than “calamitous…self-harm”?
>>The Prime Minister: What we will be doing
is negotiating a free trade agreement with
the European Union to get the best possible
access for trade with the EU, but we also
want to be able to negotiate trade agreements
with other countries around the world. A number
of countries have already expressed interest
in doing that with us. We want to do that
to open up new export markets being delivered
for businesses here in the United Kingdom,
including the sort of trade in Wales that
the hon. Gentleman is talking about. On the
question of customs with the European Union,
we want an arrangement that will involve the
most frictionless borders possible.