>>Toby Perkins (Chesterfield) (Lab): If she
will list her official engagements for Wednesday
8 February.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): This
morning, I had meetings with ministerial colleagues
and others. In addition to my duties in this
House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Toby Perkins: The Government chose to launch
the pupil premium at Spire Junior School in
Chesterfield, where 70% of pupils receive
free school meals. The headteacher, Dave Shaw,
was going to run the great north run for a
cancer charity. However, the Prime Minister’s
new schools funding formula means that Spire
Junior School now faces the biggest cuts in
all of Derbyshire. Running for cash is now
the only alternative to sacking staff. Will
she go to the finish line and tell Dave Shaw
how this is a fairer funding formula?
>>The Prime Minister
I am pleased to say that, in the local authority
that covers the hon. Gentleman’s constituency,
we have seen an increase of over 17,000 children
at good or outstanding schools since 2010.
That is down to Government changes and the
hard work of teachers and other staff in the
schools. For a very long time, it has been
the general view—I have campaigned on this
for a long time—that we need to see a fairer
funding formula for schools. What the Government
have brought forward is a consultation on
a fairer funding formula. We will look at
the results of that fairer funding formula
and will bring forward our firm proposals
in due course.
>>Johnny Mercer (Plymouth, Moor View) (Con):
Over the last 12 months, as a member of the
Defence Committee, I have had the opportunity
to look into the Iraq Historic Allegations
Team and how we as a country more broadly
deal with historical allegations against our
servicemen and women. This has been a deeply
disturbing experience not only for those of
us who have served, but for many Members across
the House. I know that the Prime Minister
gets this, but will she commit to redouble
her and her Government’s efforts to get
a grip on this historical allegations process
so that never again will our servicemen and
women be exposed to the likes of Phil Shiner?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure the whole
House will want to join me in praising the
bravery and commitment of all those who serve
in our armed forces. I thank my hon. Friend
for the work that he is doing on the Defence
Committee, because, of course, he brings personal
expertise to that work. Those who serve on
the frontline deserve our support when they
get home, and I can assure him of the Government’s
commitment to that. All troops facing allegations
receive legal aid from the Government, with
the guarantee that it will not be claimed
back. In relation to IHAT, which he specifically
referred to, we are committed to reducing
its case load to a small number of credible
cases as quickly as possible. On the action
that has been taken in relation to the individual
he has referred to, I think it is absolutely
appalling when people try to make a business
out of chasing after our brave troops.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): Nine
out of 10 NHS trusts say their hospitals have
been at unsafe levels of overcrowding. One
in six accident and emergency units in England
is set to be closed or downgraded. Could the
Prime Minister please explain how closing
A&E departments will tackle overcrowding and
ever-growing waiting lists?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I extend my thanks
and, I am sure, those of the whole House to
the hard-working staff in the NHS, who do
a great job day in and day out treating patients.
Yes, we recognise there are heavy pressures
on the NHS. That is why, this year, we are
funding the NHS at £1.3 billion more than
the Labour party promised at the last election.
The right hon. Gentleman refers specifically
to accident and emergency. What is our response
in accident and emergency? We see 600 more
A&E consultants, 1,500 more A&amp;E doctors
and 2,000 more paramedics. It is not about
standing up, making a soundbite and asking
a question; it is about delivering results,
and that is what this Conservative Government
are doing.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Congratulating A&E staff
is one thing; paying them properly is another.
I hope the Prime Minister managed to see the
BBC report on the Royal Blackburn A&E department,
which showed that people had to wait up to
13 hours and 52 minutes to be seen. A major
cause of the pressure on A&amp;Es is the £4.6
billion cut in the social care budget since
2010. Earlier this week, Liverpool’s very
esteemed adult social
care director, Samih Kalakeche, resigned,
saying:
“Frankly I can’t see social services surviving
after two years. That’s the absolute maximum...
people are suffering, and we are really only
seeing the tip of the iceberg.”
What advice do the Government have for the
people of Liverpool in this situation?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon.—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. It is bad enough when
Members who are within the curtilage of the
Chamber shout; those who are not absolutely
should not do so. It is a discourtesy to the
House of Commons—nothing more, nothing less.
Please do not do it.
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
referred at an early stage of his question
to Blackburn. I am happy to say that compared
to 2010 there are 129 more hospital doctors
and 413 more nurses in Blackburn’s East
Lancashire Hospitals NHS Trust. He then went
on to talk about waiting times. Waiting times
can be an issue. Where is it that you wait
a week longer for pneumonia treatment, a week
longer for heart disease treatment, seven
weeks longer for cataract treatment, 11 weeks
longer for hernia treatment, and 21 weeks
longer for a hip operation? It is not in England—it
is in Wales. Who is in power in Wales? Labour.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was about the
comments from Samih Kalakeche in Liverpool
and why the people of Liverpool are having
to suffer these great cuts. Liverpool has
asked to meet the Government on four occasions.
The crisis is so bad that until yesterday
David Hodge, the Conservative leader of Surrey
County Council, planned to hold a referendum
for a 15% increase in council tax. At the
last minute, it was called off. Can the Prime
Minister tell the House whether or not a special
deal was done for Surrey?
>>The Prime Minister: The decision as to whether
or not to hold a referendum in Surrey is entirely
a matter for the local authority in Surrey—Surrey
County Council.
The right hon. Gentleman raised the issue
of social care, which we have exchanged on
across this Dispatch Box before. As I have
said before, we do need to find a long-term,
sustainable solution for social care in this
country. I recognise the short-term pressures.
That is why we have enabled local authorities
to put more money into social care. We have
provided more money. Over the next two years,
£900 million more will be available for social
care. But we also need to look at ensuring
that good practice is spread across the whole
country. We can look at places such as Barnsley,
North Tyneside, St Helens and Rutland. Towards
the end of last year, there were virtually
no delayed discharges attributable to social
care in those councils. But we also need to
look long term. That is why the Cabinet Office
is driving a review, with the relevant Departments,
to find a sustainable solution, which the
Labour party ducked for far too long.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was whether there
had been a special deal done for Surrey. The
leader said that they had had many conversations
with the Government. We know they have, because
I have been leaked copies of texts sent by
the Tory leader, David Hodge, intended for
somebody called “Nick” who works for Ministers
in the Department for Communities and Local
Government. One of the texts reads:
“I am advised that DCLG officials have been
working on a solution and you will be contacting
me to agree a memorandum of understanding.”
Will the Government now publish this memorandum
of understanding, and while they are about
it, will all councils be offered the same
deal?
>>The Prime Minister: What we have given all
councils is the opportunity to raise a 3%
precept on council tax, to go into social
care. The right hon. Gentleman talks about
understanding. What the Labour party fails
to understand—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. There is far too much
noise. Mr Pound, calm yourself—you are supposed
to be a senior statesman—and Mr Rotheram,
you should reserve your shouting for the stands
at Anfield.
>>The Prime Minister: As I say, all councils
have the opportunity to raise the 3% precept,
to put that funding into the provision of
social care. What the Labour party fails to
understand is that this is not just a question
of looking at money; it is a question of looking
at spreading best practice and finding a sustainable
solution. I have to say to the right hon.
Gentleman that if we look at social care provision
across the entire country, we will see that
the last thing that social care providers
need is another one of Labour’s bouncing
cheques.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I wonder if this has anything
to do with the fact that the Chancellor and
the Health Secretary both represent Surrey
constituencies.
There was a second text from the Surrey County
Council leader to “Nick”. It says:
“The numbers you indicated are the numbers
I understand are acceptable for me to accept
and call off the R”.
I have been reading a bit of John le Carré
and apparently “R” means “referendum”—it
is very subtle, all this. He goes on to say
in his text to “Nick”:
“If it is possible for that info to be sent
to myself I can then revert back soonest,
really want to kill this off”.
So, how much did the Government offer Surrey
to “kill this off”, and is the same sweetheart
deal on offer to every council facing the
social care crisis created by this Government?
>>The Prime Minister: I have made clear to
the right hon. Gentleman what has been made
available to every council, which is the ability
to raise the precept. I have to say to him—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. As colleagues know, I
never mind how long Prime Minister’s questions
take. The questions and the answers must be
heard.
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
comes to the Dispatch Box making all sorts
of claims. Yet again, what we get from Labour
is alternative facts; what it really needs
is an alternative leader.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was, what deal
was offered to Surrey that got it to call
off a referendum, and will the same deal be
offered to every other council going through
a social care crisis?
Hospital wards are overcrowded, a million
people are not getting the care they need,
and family members, mostly women, are having
to give up work to care for loved ones. Every
day that the Prime Minister fails to act,
this crisis gets worse. Will she finally come
clean and provide local authorities with the
funding they need to fund social care properly,
so that our often elderly and vulnerable people
can be treated with the support and dignity
that they deserve in a civilised society?
>>The Prime Minister: The deal that is on
offer to all councils is the one that I have
already set out. Let me be very clear with
the right hon. Gentleman. As ever, he stands
up and consistently asks for more spending,
more money, more funding. What he always fails
to recognise is that you can spend money on
social care and the national health service
only if you have a strong economy to deliver
the wealth that you need. There is a fundamental
difference between us. When I talk—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. I am sorry, but there
is still too much noise in the Chamber. People
observing our proceedings, both here and outside,
want the questions heard and the answers heard,
and they will be.
>>The Prime Minister: There is a difference
between us. When I talk about half a trillion
pounds, it is about the money we will be spending
on the NHS this Parliament. When Labour Members
talk about half a trillion pounds, it is about
the money they want to borrow: Conservatives
investing in the NHS; Labour bankrupting Britain.
>>Scott Mann (North Cornwall) (Con): Significant
challenges face this great nation of ours,
Prime Minister, one of which is tackling mental
health, particularly for young people. The
pressures of juggling school life and family
life, and of staying safe and feeling valued
online, are more difficult than ever. Will
the Prime Minister meet me and my team to
discuss the mental health app we have been
working on and developing to give young people
a toolbox to help them in their times of crisis?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very interested
to hear of the important work my hon. Friend
is doing in that important area. As he knows,
I think we need to put more of a focus on
mental health and make progress. I am pleased
to say that something like 1,400 more people
are accessing mental health services every
day. That is an advance, but more needs to
be done. We are putting more money—£68
million—into improving mental healthcare
through digital innovation, which sounds as
if it fits right into what he is looking at.
There will be a focus on that with children’s
and young people’s mental health in mind.
He might want to look out for the Department
of Health and Department for Education joint
Green Paper on that, which they will publish
in October.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): Last night,
parliamentarians from across the Chamber and
across the parties voted overwhelmingly against
the UK Government’s Brexit plans—in the
Scottish Parliament. If the United Kingdom
is a partnership of equals, will the Prime
Minister compromise like the Scottish Government
and reach a negotiated agreement before invoking
article 50, or will she just carry on regardless?
>>The Prime Minister: As the right hon. Gentleman
knows, when the UK Government negotiate, we
will negotiate as the Government for the whole
United Kingdom. We have put in place the Joint
Ministerial Committee arrangements through
various committees, which enable us to work
closely with the devolved Administrations
to identify the particular issues they want
represented as we put our views together.
We have said that we will intensify the discussions
within that JMC arrangement, and that is exactly
what we will be doing.
>>Angus Robertson: When the Prime Minister
was in Edinburgh on 15 July last year, she
pledged that she would not trigger article
50 until she had an agreed UK-wide approach.
Given that the Scottish Parliament has voted
overwhelmingly against her approach, and that
all bar one MP representing a Scottish constituency
in the House of Commons has voted against
her approach, she does not have an agreed
UK-wide approach. As the Prime Minister knows,
a lot of people in Scotland watch Prime Minister’s
questions. Will she tell those viewers in
Scotland whether she intends to keep her word
to Scotland or not?
>>The Prime Minister: We are ensuring that
we are working closely with the Scottish Government,
and indeed with the other devolved Administrations,
as we take this matter forward. I would just
remind the right hon. Gentleman of two things.
First, the Supreme Court was very clear that
the Scottish Parliament does not have a veto
on the triggering of article 50—the European
Union (Notification of Withdrawal) Bill, which
is going through the House, obviously gives
the power to the Government to trigger article
50. I would also remind him of this point,
because he constantly refers to the interests
of Scotland inside the European Union: an
independent Scotland would not be in the European
Union.
>>Jake Berry (Rossendale and Darwen) (Con):
The people of Rossendale and Darwen warmly
welcome the Government’s housing White Paper.
Will my right hon. Friend confirm that, when
it comes to providing more security for renters,
building more affordable homes and helping
people to buy their own home, this party—the
Conservative party—is fixing our broken
housing market?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to agree
with my hon. Friend. Our broken housing market
is one of the greatest barriers to progress
in Britain today, and the excellent housing
White Paper brought out by my right hon. Friend
the Secretary of State for Communities and
Local Government sets out the steps we will
take to fix it. My hon. Friend is right: it
is the Conservatives in government who will
support local authorities to deliver more
of the right homes in the right places, to
encourage faster build-out of developments—I
am sure everybody recognises the problem of
planning permissions that are given and then
not built out—and to create the conditions
for a more competitive and diverse housing
market. We are calling for action and we are
setting out the responsibilities of all parties
in building the homes that Britain needs.
>>Patrick Grady (Glasgow North) (SNP): Does
the Prime Minister agree that in a 21st-century
Parliament the rules should not enable any
Member to speak for 58 minutes in a three-hour
debate? Does she agree that the rules of the
House should be changed to prevent filibustering
and ensure that Members on both sides of the
House get a fair share of the time available?
>>The Prime Minister: I find that a rather
curious question from the hon. Gentleman.
As it happens, last night I was out of the
House between the two votes. I switched on
the BBC parliamentary channel and I saw the
hon. Gentleman speaking. I turned over to
something else. I switched back to the parliamentary
channel and he was still speaking. I switched
over to something else. I switched back and
he was still speaking. He is the last person
to complain about filibustering in this House.
[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. Mr Docherty-Hughes, you
seem to be in a state of permanent over-excitement.
Calm yourself, man. Take some sort of medicament
and it will soothe you. We must hear Mrs Villiers.
>>Mrs Theresa Villiers (Chipping Barnet) (Con):
As we prepare in this House to take back control
over our laws on agriculture, will the Prime
Minister agree to use Brexit as an opportunity
to strengthen, not weaken, the rules that
safeguard the welfare of animals?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
raises an important point that is, I know,
of concern to many people in the House and
outside. We should be proud that in the UK
we have some of the highest animal welfare
standards in the world—indeed, one of the
highest scores for animal protection in the
world. Leaving the EU will not change that.
I can assure her that we are committed to
maintaining and, where possible, improving
standards of welfare in the UK, while ensuring
of course that our industry is not put at
a competitive disadvantage.
>>Gavin Newlands (Paisley and Renfrewshire
North) (SNP): Last week, the Russian Duma
shamefully decriminalised domestic violence
committed against women and children. Given
the Prime Minister’s new global Britain
approach, I trust that the Government will
encourage Russia to rethink that regressive
approach, which trivialises domestic violence.
Does she agree that ratifying the Istanbul
convention would send a message to Russia
and the world about the priority that should
be placed on ending gender-based violence?
>>The Prime Minister: I am proud that in this
country we have strengthened the law on domestic
violence and violence against women and girls.
We see this as a retrograde step by the Russian
Government. Repealing existing legislation
sends out the wrong message on what is a global
problem. We have joined others in the Council
of Europe and the Organisation for Security
and Co-operation in Europe in criticising
that decision.
>>Iain Stewart (Milton Keynes South) (Con):
Each year, the NHS reportedly spends £80
million more than it needs to on prescriptions
for basic painkillers that can be sourced
much more cheaply, but at the same time secondary
breast cancer patients face being denied life-extending
drugs such as Kadcyla by the National Institute
for Health and Care Excellence. Will my right
hon. Friend review that poor allocation of
resources and give breast cancer sufferers
the hope that they deserve?
>>The Prime Minister: This is obviously a
very important issue that my hon. Friend has
raised. I understand that on the point of
basic medication it is not the fact that the
NHS pays more for basic painkillers than on
the high street: in fact, its prices are lower.
In the case of Kadcyla and similar drugs,
it is right that difficult decisions are made
on the basis of clinical evidence. I understand
that NICE is undertaking a comprehensive assessment
before making a final recommendation, and
in the meantime Kadcyla is still available
to patients.
>>Tom Elliott (Fermanagh and South Tyrone)
(UUP): Last month, Sir Anthony Hart published
his report on historical institutional abuse
in Northern Ireland. Given the uncertain political
situation with the Northern Ireland political
institutions, if the Executive is not up and
running within a month, will the Prime Minister
commit to implementing the report in full?
>>The Prime Minister: This was obviously an
important review. We have our own inquiry
into historic child abuse in England and Wales.
I recognise the hon. Gentleman’s point about
looking ahead to the future. The elections
in Northern Ireland will take place on 2 March.
There will then be a limited period for an
Executive to be put together. I fervently
hope an Executive can be put together to maintain
the devolved institutions, and I encourage
all parties to work very hard to ensure that.
I do not want the benefits of progress to
be undone, but I am sure, looking ahead, that
whatever is necessary will be done to ensure
that the findings of the report are taken
into account and acted on.
>>James Morris (Halesowen and Rowley Regis)
(Con): The Prime Minister has been crystal
clear on her negotiating objectives as we
prepare to leave the European Union. Does
she agree that regions like the west midlands,
part of which I represent, need a voice in
the negotiations to ensure we take the opportunities
presented by Brexit to raise investment in
education, skills and infrastructure and to
ensure that her vision of a global Britain
represents the interests of all the regions
of England, as well as the broader United
Kingdom?
>>The Prime Minister: I agree with my hon.
Friend. When we negotiate as a United Kingdom,
we will be negotiating for the whole of the
United Kingdom and taking account of all parts
of the United Kingdom. We have a real ambition
to make the west midlands an engine for growth.
That is about growing the region’s economy
and more jobs. Money has been put into growth
deal funding and, for example, the Birmingham
rail hub. The west midlands will of course
be getting a strong voice nationally with
a directly elected Mayor in May. I believe
Andy Street, with both local expertise and
business experience, will be a very good Mayor
for the west midlands.
>>Mr Speaker: I welcome the hon. Gentleman
back again to the Chamber.
>>Mr Ronnie Campbell (Blyth Valley) (Lab)
I’m looking pretty slim as well, Mr Speaker!
I had five months of NHS treatment at the
Newcastle Royal Victoria infirmary under the
auspices of Professor Griffin, a marvellous
surgeon. Seeing as I might have come out with
palliative care, I think he has just about
saved my life. That is the best side of the
NHS. The service I received was absolutely
wonderful, but there is a flip side. What
we have today is what are called “corridor
nurses”, who look after patients on trolleys
in corridors. Quite honestly, Prime Minister,
that is not the way we want the health service
to be run. We want it to be run in the way
it saved me. Get your purse open and give
them the money they want.
>>The Prime Minister: As Mr Speaker said,
I welcome the hon. Gentleman back to his place
in the Chamber. I commend the surgeon and
all those in the national health service who
treated him and enabled him to be here today
and continue his duties. There are, as we
know, surgeons, doctors, nurses and other
staff up and down the NHS day in, day out
saving lives. We should commend them for all
they do. The north-east is a very good example
of some of the really good practice in the
NHS. I want to see that good practice spread
across the NHS in the whole country.
>>Dr Sarah Wollaston (Totnes) (Con): I am
not alone in hearing from families long-settled
here in Britain who are deeply worried that
they could be separated after we leave the
European Union. I know the Prime Minister
will not want that to happen. Will she reassure
all our constituents today that those who
were born elsewhere in the European Union
but settled here in the UK, married or in
partnerships with British citizens will have
the right to remain?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend obviously
raises an issue that is of concern all across
this House. As she says, it is of concern
to many individuals outside the House who
want reassurance about their future. As I
have said, I want to be able to give, and
I expect to be able to give, that reassurance,
but I want to see the same reassurance for
UK citizens living in the EU. What I can say
to her is that when I trigger article 50,
I intend to make it clear that I want this
to be a priority for an early stage of the
negotiations, so we can address this issue
and give reassurance to the people concerned.
>>Dawn Butler (Brent Central) (Lab): Just
two weeks ago, Quamari Serunkuma-Barnes, 15
years old, left school, was stabbed four times
and died. Three days earlier, Djodjo Nsaka,
19 years old, was stabbed to death in Wembley.
Just a few months earlier, two of my young
constituents, James Owusu-Ajyekum, 22 years
old, and Oliver Tetlow, 27 years old, were
killed in what the police say was a case of
mistaken identity. Next week, I am meeting
the deputy Mayor of London to discuss this
and other issues. Will the Prime Minister
meet me, fellow MPs and my borough commander
to talk about this issue and the Sycamore
project, which we would like rolled out in
London and beyond?
>>The Prime Minister: First, may I send the
condolences of the whole House to the families
and friends of all those the hon. Lady refers
to who were brutally stabbed and attacked
in knife attacks? This is obviously an important
issue, particularly in London, and we want
it addressed. A lot of good work has been
done. I am not aware of the Sycamore project,
but I would be happy to hear more details
of it.
>>James Berry (Kingston and Surbiton) (Con):
From medics at Kingston hospital to researchers
at Kingston University and the staff at growing
electronics businesses such as Genuine Solutions,
Kingston’s workforce is enriched by highly
skilled workers from abroad, so will my right
hon. Friend confirm that, after we leave the
EU, we will continue to welcome highly skilled
workers from the EU and beyond?
>>The Prime Minister: We have been very clear
that we want to bring the net migration numbers
down, but we also want to ensure that the
brightest and the best are still welcome here
in the UK. That is why people want to see
the UK Government making decisions about people
coming here from the EU. We are clear, however,
as I said in my Lancaster House speech, that
there will still be immigration from the EU
into the UK. We want to ensure that the brightest
and the best can come here.
>>Liz Kendall (Leicester West) (Lab): Yesterday,
the Brexit Minister claimed that Parliament
would have a meaningful vote on the final
EU deal. Will the Prime Minister confirm that,
under her plans, Parliament will either have
to accept what the Government offer or fall
back on World Trade Organisation rules and
that, in the event of no deal, there will
be no vote at all? In reality, is this not
just a case of take it or leave it? It is
not a meaningful concession; it is a con.
>>The Prime Minister: We have been clear on
this, but I am happy to reiterate what the
Minister said yesterday. We have looked at
this matter. I said in my Lancaster House
speech that there would be a vote on the final
deal, but there were a number of questions
about what exactly that meant. We will bring
forward a motion; the motion will be on the
final agreement; it will be for approval by
both Houses of Parliament; it will be before
the final agreement is concluded, and we expect—I
know that this has been an issue for several
right hon. and hon. Members—and intend that
that will happen before the European Parliament
debates and votes on the final agreement.
>>Mr Graham Brady (Altrincham and Sale West)
(Con): The Prime Minister knows that Trafford
schools are the best in the country, but they
are also in one of f40’s worst-funded areas.
Perversely, the draft funding formula would
actually cut funding to Trafford schools,
not increase it. When she reviews the draft
proposals, will she please look for a new
formula that guarantees that all the worst-funded
areas see an increase in funding, not a cut?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important matter that is on the minds of
a number of right hon. and hon. Friends. As
I said earlier, the current system of funding
is unfair, not transparent and out of date.
I want a system that supports our aspiration
to ensure that every child has a good school
place. In looking at these reforms, I can
assure my hon. Friend that we want to get
this right, which is why we are consulting
and why we will look closely at the responses
to the consultation.
>>Caroline Flint (Don Valley) (Lab): Npower
has announced a 9.8% increase on dual fuel
bills, which even the former boss of Npower,
Paul Massara, has described as “shocking”.
EDF has announced an 8.4% electricity hike,
and it is reported that British Gas is preparing
its 11 million customers for a 9% increase.
Ofgem has moved to protect those who are on
prepayment meters with a cap on their energy
bills, so why does the Prime Minister not
demand similar protection for the majority
of customers, who are being ripped off, as
the Competition and Markets Authority has
said, to the sum of £1.4 billion a year?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Lady
may have missed the fact that we have said
that where we think markets are not working,
we will look at any measures that are needed—and
the energy market is one of those we are looking
at the moment.
>>Karl MᶜCartney (Lincoln) (Con): In the
spirit of neutrality, the Prime Minister’s
Lancaster House speech last month was a rallying
call to put the divisions of the referendum
behind us and to unite behind a bold vision
for a stronger, fairer more global Britain.
Does my right hon. Friend agree with me that
this is a vision that every Member should
support, because the more united we are, the
stronger our negotiating hand will be—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order, I apologise for interrupting,
but the hon. Gentleman must be heard.
>>Karl MᶜCartney: Thank you, Mr Speaker.
Finally, does my right hon. Friend share my
surprise that certain Opposition Front Benchers
have not learned that disagreeing with their
current party leader can cause headaches?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right, and I think all of us and everybody
in the country wants to unite behind the Government’s
work to ensure that we get the best possible
deal for the United Kingdom as we leave the
European Union, and I believe that we can
get a deal that will be in the interests of
both the UK and the EU. I had hoped that I
would be able to welcome the shadow Home Secretary
to the Front Bench in time for the vote that
is going to take place later tonight. Perhaps
Labour Members are starting to realise that
their only real headache is their leader.
>>Owen Smith (Pontypridd) (Lab): Does the
Prime Minister agree with the director general
of the World Trade Organisation that if Britain
were to leave the EU on WTO terms, it would
cost £9 billion in lost trade each year?
>>The Prime Minister: What we want to do is
to ensure that we negotiate a deal with the
European Union that enables us to have the
best possible deal in trading with and operating
within the European Union single market in
goods and services. I believe that is possible
precisely because, as I have just said in
response to my hon. Friend the Member for
Lincoln (Karl MᶜCartney), such a deal would
be good not just for us, but for the EU as
well.
>>Julian Sturdy (York Outer) (Con): The Prime
Minister rightly argues for true parity of
esteem between mental and physical health,
but parents in York have been told that their
children must wait up to a year for an assessment
by child and adolescent mental health services.
The Department of Health does not currently
record these figures, so will my right hon.
Friend consider making the monitoring of CAMHS
waiting times a requirement?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important point. As I set out a few weeks
ago, the Government will be reviewing the
operation of CAMHS across the country, because
I recognise some of the concerns that hon.
Members have raised about it. We want to ensure
that children and young people have easy access
to mental health at the right time, because
of the evidence that a significant proportion
of mental health problems that arise later
in life actually start at the age of childhood
and adolescence. We have made more money available
to support transformation in children’s
and young people’s mental health, but the
shadow Health Secretary—sorry, I mean the
Health Secretary is on—[Interruption.] The
hon. Gentleman is in his place, as well. I
hope the shadow Health Secretary will agree
with me that we need to review CAMHS and ensure
that we give the right to support to children,
young people and adolescents with mental health
problems. We will look at the issue that my
hon. Friend has raised.
>>Sue Hayman (Workington) (Lab): Many hon.
Members have recently made the long journey
up to west Cumbria for the Copeland by-election,
and will all have experienced the parlous
state of our roads and our local railways.
In fact, it has taken a by-election for Transport
Ministers to look seriously at, and show any
real interest in, the situation. Is the Prime
Minister planning a trip herself, so that
she, too, can experience why we need proper
investment from this Government into the transport
infrastructure in west Cumbria?
>>The Prime Minister: The Government are putting
more money into infrastructure throughout
the country. The Labour party had 13 years
in which to improve transport in west Cumbria,
and did not do anything about it.
>>Chris Green (Bolton West) (Con): I recently
visited the headquarters of Woodall Nicholson,
a world-class coachbuilding company based
in my constituency, and heard about its exciting
plans for the future. Will my right hon. Friend
join me in emphasising the importance of skills
and manufacturing to our economy, especially
as we look to leave the European Union?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for drawing our attention to the example of
Woodall Nicholson. We are pleased to hear
that it has those good plans for the future.
As we leave the EU, we will be doing so from
a position of strength, and my hon. Friend
is right to say that skills and manufacturing
are important parts of our economy for the
future. That is why, in the industrial strategy,
we are looking into how we can develop the
excellence that we have in the United Kingdom
to ensure that we have a prosperous, growing
economy for the future.
>>Ms Angela Eagle (Wallasey) (Lab): Last week,
the right hon. and learned Member for Rushcliffe
(Mr Clarke) pointed out that the Prime Minister’s
aspiration to achieve barrier-free, tariff-free
trade with the single market, getting all
the benefits but paying none of the costs,
was akin to disappearing down the rabbit hole
to Wonderland. I think that the Prime Minister
makes a very interesting choice for Alice,
but if she does not manage to achieve that
high ambition, will she produce an analysis
of what trading on the basis of WTO rules
would mean for our economy, so that we, too,
can make a proper choice?
>>The Prime Minister: I commend my right hon.
and learned Friend the Member for Rushcliffe
(Mr Clarke) for the significant service that
he has given to the House and his constituents
over the years. He and I have worked well
over a number of years—although I should
add that, when I was Home Secretary, I used
to say, “I locked ’em up and he let ’em
out.”
The Government believe that it is possible,
within the two-year time frame, to secure
agreement not just on our withdrawal from
the European Union, but on the trade arrangements
that will ensure that we have a strong strategic
partnership with the European Union in the
future.
>>Sir Eric Pickles (Brentwood and Ongar) (Con):
When my right hon. Friend met Mr Netanyahu
earlier this week, did she impress on him
that a lasting peace settlement can only be
secured if young Palestinians and young Israelis
can look forward to a job, a share in prosperity
and a life without fear? Does she agree that
that can only be achieved through face-to-face
negotiations, and will she join the Israeli
Prime Minister in pressing the Prime Minister
of the Palestinian National Authority to engage
in such negotiations?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
has made an important point. We continue,
as a Conservative Government, to believe that
the two-state solution is the right one. It
means a viable Palestinian state, but also
a safe and secure Israel. Of course, it is
for the parties to negotiate: obviously, there
are others in the international arena who
are doing their work to facilitate an agreement
in the middle east, but ultimately it is for
the two parties to agree on a way forward.