>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May):
I am sure that Members across the House will
wish to join me in offering our condolences
to the families and friends of Andreea Christie,
who died following the London attack, and
of Chris Bevington, who was among those killed
in the terrorist attack in Sweden. Our thoughts
are also with the family and friends of Hannah
Bladon, who was murdered in Jerusalem last
week.
This morning, I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in this House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>> Alberto Costa:
I would also like to join the Prime Minister
in offering the condolences of the people
of South Leicestershire and myself to the
families of those individuals.
Strong countries need strong economies. Strong
countries need strong defences. Strong countries
need strong leaders. As the nation prepares
to go to the polls, who else in this House,
apart from my right hon. Friend, can provide
the leadership that is needed at this time?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right. There
are three things that a country needs: a strong
economy, strong defence, and strong, stable
leadership. That is what our plans for Brexit
and our plans for a stronger Britain will
deliver. That is what the Conservative party
will be offering at this election, and we
will be out there fighting for every vote.
The right hon. Member for Islington North
(Jeremy Corbyn) would bankrupt our economy
and weaken our defences and is simply not
fit to lead.
>> Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab):
I concur with the condolences that the Prime
Minister just sent to the families of the
three people who so sadly and needlessly died.
It is important that we recognise that as
a cross-party proposal today, and I thank
the Prime Minister for it.
We welcome the general election, but this
is a Prime Minister who promised that there
would not be one—a Prime Minister who cannot
be trusted. She says that it is about leadership,
yet she refuses to defend her record in television
debates. It is not hard to see why. The Prime
Minister says that we have a stronger economy,
yet she cannot explain why people’s wages
are lower today than they were 10 years ago
or why more households are in debt. Six million
people are earning less than the living wage,
child poverty is up, and pensioner poverty
is up. Why are so many people getting poorer?
>> The Prime Minister:
I point out to the right hon. Gentleman that
I have been answering his questions and debating
these matters every Wednesday that Parliament
has been sitting since I became Prime Minister.
I will be taking out to the country in this
campaign a proud record of a Conservative
Government: a stronger economy, with the deficit
nearly two thirds down, a tax cut for 30 million
people, with 4 million people taken out of
income tax altogether, record levels of employment,
and £1,250 more a year for pensioners. That
is a record we can proud of.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
If the Prime Minister is so proud of her record,
why will she not debate it? Wages are falling
and more children are in poverty. Page 28
of the Tories’ last manifesto said:
“We will work to eliminate child poverty”.
They only eliminated the child poverty target,
not child poverty. In 2010, they promised
to eradicate the deficit by 2015. In 2015,
they promised to eradicate the deficit by
2020. Austerity has failed, so does the Prime
Minister know by which year the deficit will
now be eradicated?
>> The Prime Minister:
I know that it has taken the right hon. Gentleman
a little time to get the hang of Prime Minister’s
questions, but he stands up week in, week
out and asks me questions and I respond to
those questions. With a stronger—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The Leader of the Opposition must be
heard, and the Prime Minister must be heard.
>> The Prime Minister:
We have a stronger economy, with the deficit
two thirds down, but people will have a real
choice at this election. They will have a
choice between a Conservative Government who
have shown that we can build a stronger economy
and a Labour party with an economic policy
that would bankrupt this country. What voters
know is that under Labour it is ordinary working
people who pay the price of the Labour party.
They pay it with their taxes, they pay it
with their jobs, and they pay it with their
children’s futures.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Only this year the new Chancellor pledged
to eradicate the deficit by 2022. I admire
Tory consistency: it is always five years
in the future. Another Tory broken promise.
The Prime Minister leads a Government who
have increased national debt by £700 billion,
more than every Labour Government in history
put together. Debt has risen every year they
have been in office. We know their economic
plan was long term. Does she want to tell
us how far into the long term it will be before
we get the debt falling?
>> The Prime Minister:
The right hon. Gentleman stands up and talks
about debt. This is a Labour party that will
be going into the election pledged to borrow
an extra £500 billion. What does that mean
for ordinary working people? Well, I will
tell him what it means. We know what Labour’s
plans would entail because we have been told
by the former Labour shadow Chancellor. He
said that if Labour were in power,
“you’d have to double income tax, double
National Insurance, double council tax and
you’d have to double VAT as well.”
That is Labour’s plan for the economy.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
All her Government have delivered is more
debt and less funding for schools and hospitals.
Schools funding is being cut for the first
time in a generation. The Prime Minister is
cutting £3 billion a year from school budgets
by 2020. She says that the Government have
created a stronger economy, so why are there
tax giveaways to the richest corporations
while our children’s schools are starved
of the resources they need to educate our
children for the future?
>> The Prime Minister:
The right hon. Gentleman talks about levels
of funding for schools and the NHS. There
are record levels of funding going into schools
and record levels of funding going into the
NHS, but let us just talk about schools. It
is not just a question of funding; it is actually
a question of the quality of education provided
in schools. Some 1.8 million more children
are in good or outstanding schools under this
Conservative Government, which is 1.8 million
more children with a better chance for their
future. What would Labour give us? It would
be the same old one-size-fits-all, local authority-run
schools: “No choice, good or bad, trust
your luck.” We do not trust to luck, and
we will not trust the Labour party. We will
provide a good school place for every child.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Many parents taking their children back to
school for the summer term will receive a
letter begging for funds to buy books and
fund the school. The Conservative manifesto
promised
“the amount of money following your child
into school will be protected.”
It is not. It is another Tory broken promise.
For the first time in its history, NHS funding
per patient will fall this year. The NHS has
been put into an all-year-round crisis by
this Government. Why are more people waiting
in pain, with millions of elderly people not
getting the care and dignity they deserve?
>> The Prime Minister:
I am proud of our record on the NHS. We saw
more doctors, more nurses, more midwives,
more general practitioners and more people
being treated in our national health service
last year than ever before, with record levels
of funding going into our national health
service. We can only do that with a strong
economy. What do we know we would get from
the Labour party? Bankruptcy and chaos.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
That is a very good reason for why we should
have a debate about it, because it is another
Tory broken promise. A broken promise of the
Tory manifesto, which said that they would
continue to
“spend more on the NHS, in real terms”.
Say that to those waiting in A&amp;E departments
and to those who cannot leave hospital because
social care is not available.
Is it not the truth that, over the last seven
years, the Tories have broken every promise
on living standards, the deficit, debt, the
national health service and school funding?
Why should anyone believe a word they say
over the next seven weeks?
>> The Prime Minister:
I can assure the right hon. Gentleman that
I will be out campaigning and taking to voters
the message of not only the record of this
Conservative Government, but, crucially, of
our plans to make Brexit a success and to
build a stronger Britain for the future. Every
vote for the Conservatives will make it harder
for those who want to stop me getting the
job done. Every vote for the Conservatives
will make me stronger when I negotiate for
Britain with the European Union. And every
vote for the Conservatives will mean we can
stick to our plan for a stronger Britain and
take the right long-term decisions for a more
secure future for this country.
>> Michelle Donelan (Chippenham) (Con):
For years I have been campaigning for fairer
funding in Wiltshire schools. Will the Prime
Minister please reaffirm her commitment to
this and to a review of the pupil premium
to encompass other forms of key disadvantage,
such as being a young carer, having mental
health problems and dealing with bereavement?
In this way, we can create a country that
will work for everyone.
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend raises a very important point,
and I know she has campaigned long and hard
in her constituency and worked hard for her
constituents on this and other issues. We
want to ensure that young people, irrespective
of their background, have the opportunity
to make the most of their talents, and the
point of our reforms is to try to end the
postcode lottery in school funding and to
support our plan for a fairer society, where
success is based on merit and not on privilege.
She refers to the pupil premium, and that
is of course worth £2.5 billion a year. It
is an important part of our policy because
it gives schools extra support for pupils
from disadvantaged backgrounds, but I think
it is right that schools are best placed to
prioritise the needs of their pupils and can
use their funding to ensure that they are
supporting any pupil facing disadvantage,
financial or otherwise.
>> Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP):
May I join in the condolences extended by
the Prime Minister and the leader of the Labour
party?
The tone and content of democratic debates,
including in a general election, are very
important to all of us, so does the Prime
Minister agree that political opponents are
not “saboteurs”, and that all elected
mainstream parties and parliamentarians have
a mandate and that that should be respected?
>> The Prime Minister:
In this House and in this Parliament it is
right that we have proper debate and scrutiny
of proposals put forward by the Government,
and that arguments on both sides of the House
are rightly challenged and those discussions
take place. But I say to the right hon. Gentleman
that what the British people—what the people
of the United Kingdom—voted for last year
was for the UK to leave the European Union.
We have set that process in motion; there
is no turning back. But it is clear from statements
made by the Scottish nationalists and others
that they want to use this House to try to
frustrate that process. I will be asking the
British people for a mandate to complete Brexit
and to make a success of it.
>> Angus Robertson:
It is disappointing that the Prime Minister
did not take the opportunity to condemn intemperate
language in describing other democratic politicians
as—[Interruption.] There is heckling from
the Government side, and I think the Prime
Minister should take the opportunity to underline
something that we should all agree on: that
describing people in the way we have seen
them described in some daily newspapers by
some leading politicians is not acceptable.
Most people know that the reason we are having
a general election is because of the woeful
state of the Labour party. If the Prime Minister
is so confident that her hard Brexit, pro-austerity,
anti-immigration case is right, she should
debate it with Opposition leaders during the
campaign. We look forward to the straight
fight between the Scottish National party
and the Tories. Will the Prime Minister tell
the people why she is running scared of a
televised debate with Nicola Sturgeon?
>> The Prime Minister:
First, may I say to the right hon. Gentleman
that one of the crucial things we have in
this country that underpins our democracy
is a free press? I believe that is important
and I believe that people in this Chamber
should stand up for the freedom of the press.
As to the TV debates, I can assure him that
I will be out there campaigning in every part
of the United Kingdom, taking out there our
proud record of a Conservative Government
that has delivered for every part of the United
Kingdom.
I might also suggest to the Scottish nationalists
that now is the time for them to put aside—[Interruption.]
Wait for it: now is the time for them to put
aside their tunnel vision on independence
and actually explain to the Scottish people
why the SNP Government are not putting as
much money into the health service as they
have been given from the UK, they are not
exercising the powers they have been given
and Scottish education is getting worse. It
is time they got back to the day job.
>> Mary Robinson (Cheadle) (Con):
I too welcome the announcement from the Prime
Minister yesterday, and I look forward to
the general election and to taking my positive
message to my constituents in Cheadle in June.
Over the past two years, I have pressed for
first-class transport infrastructure for Cheadle,
and this week I launched my transport survey
so my constituents can have their say on what
is needed to keep Cheadle moving and be at
the heart of the northern powerhouse. Does
my right hon. Friend agree that residents
in Cheadle need to vote Conservative on 8
June to ensure that we get continued investment
in transport and infrastructure, not only
in Cheadle but across the north-west?
>> The Prime Minister:
I absolutely agree with my hon. Friend on
that point. I know she has been working very
hard for her constituents in Cheadle on transport
and other issues. Of course, it is under this
Government that the Department for Transport
is investing £290 million to improve transport
links to Manchester airport through Cheadle,
and £2.1 million has been committed to improving
walking and cycling routes around the Cheadle
Hulme district centre. That is why the choice
is so clear. As my hon. Friend says, if she
wants to see that funding for infrastructure,
we need a strong economy, which only the Conservatives
can deliver.
>> Jeff Smith (Manchester, Withington) (Lab):
Because of the Prime Minister’s changes
to education funding, every school in the
country will face real- terms cuts. Manchester
will be hit harder than anywhere outside London—[Interruption.]
It’s true. Chorlton High School and Parrs
Wood High School in my constituency will each
lose the equivalent of more than 30 teachers.
I ask the Prime Minister the same question
a headteacher asked me: what would she cut
to balance the books and what subjects would
she choose to sack teachers from?
>> The Prime Minister:
As the hon. Gentleman knows, record levels
of funding are going into our schools. Everybody
across this House has recognised for many
years that the current funding formula is
not fair across the country, and it is necessary
for us to look for a fairer funding formula.
We have consulted on that and will obviously
be responding to that consultation. As the
hon. Gentleman faces up to the election, I
note that last year he failed to back—he
opposed—the leader of his party. If the
hon. Gentleman was not willing to support
him as leader of his party then, why should
his voters support him as leader of the country?
>> David Mackintosh (Northampton South) (Con):
The only way to fund crucial infrastructure
is with a strong economy. To that end, does
my right hon. Friend agree that the St James
Mill link road in Northampton would help with
traffic flow in the town and unlock development
in the enterprise zone? Will the next Conservative
Government continue to support me, as the
MP, in backing the scheme?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right that we
need to have a strong economy if we are to
be able to fund that crucial infrastructure.
That is why, since 2015, we have increased
our annual investment in economic infrastructure
by almost 60% to £22 billion per year by
2021, including £2.6 billion for improvements
in transport projects. I am happy to see the
link road proposal being put forward by his
local enterprise partnership; it will improve
access to business and unlock development
in the area. My hon. Friend has worked hard
to see it happen, and I am sure he will continue
to campaign on issues like that which matter
so much to his constituents.
>> Gerald Jones (Merthyr Tydfil and Rhymney)
(Lab):
Recent changes to housing benefit entitlement
for 18 to 21-year-olds will affect 195 young
people in Merthyr Tydfil and Rhymney. The
Government are constantly challenging young
people to train and leave benefits for the
world of work, but homelessness charities
such as Llamau are concerned that the changes
will be a major barrier to learning and training
for youngsters who do not have a safe and
secure environment at home. Does the Prime
Minister agree that we should be doing everything
we can to help young people in the job market,
including by offering financial support for
housing? Will she pledge to strengthen the
guidelines so that no more young people risk
falling through the net and ending up on the
streets?
>> The Prime Minister:
The principle behind the changing of housing
benefit is the right one, which is to say
that it is only fair that people are not able
to make decisions when they are on benefit
that they would not be able to make if they
are actually in work. However, it is right
that we ensure that those young people who
have a particular difficulty with staying
at home are supported through the system,
which is why significant exemptions are in
place. We recognise that need and have taken
it on board.
>> Mr Speaker:
The next question is a closed question.
>> Mr Philip Hollobone (Kettering) (Con):
If she will visit Kettering constituency.
>> The Prime Minister:
I would be happy to visit the Kettering constituency
in the future if my diary allows. In fact,
I suspect that I will be visiting quite a
few constituencies across the country in the
next few weeks.
>> Mr Hollobone:
Life for ordinary working families is harder
than many people at Westminster realise: “You
have a job, but not necessarily job security.
You are just about managing, but you are worried
about the cost of living and getting your
kids into a good school. You are doing your
best, and a Conservative Government will do
all it can to make sure that you have more
control over your life.” These were the
inspiring words of the Prime Minister when
she took office last July. Will she come to
Kettering, Britain’s most average town,
and repeat these, her core beliefs? If she
does so, I know she will be warmly and widely
acclaimed as the Prime Minister this country
needs for the next five years.
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right to highlight
ordinary working families who do rely on the
Government to provide stability and certainty
for them, and that is what this Conservative
Government have done. Looking at what we have
done, we see that we have supported jobs through
significant new investment in skills, we have
invested in public services such as childcare
and the NHS, and we have enhanced consumer
protections. I am happy to repeat the words
that I said outside Downing Street on 13 July
last year, but it is Conservatives in government
who have delivered strong and stable leadership,
and that is the message I will be taking out
to the country during this election.
>> Jenny Chapman (Darlington) (Lab):
Does the Prime Minister support the people
of Darlington who oppose the downgrading of
their A&amp;E and maternity services? They
want an answer they can trust, Prime Minister.
Is it yes or no?
>> The Prime Minister:
The proposals for the configuration of health
services in local areas is a matter that is
being determined by local commissions in the
best interests of services in the local area.
I am interested that the hon. Lady refers
to the views of her constituents in Darlington.
She has said of the Leader of the Opposition,
the leader of her party:
“My constituents in Darlington have made
it clear to me that they cannot support the
Labour party under your leadership.”
How can they possibly support him as leader
of the country?
>> Maria Caulfield (Lewes) (Con):
May I welcome the fact that, because the Conservatives
have managed the economy so well, there is
record school funding this year? East Sussex,
for example, has some of the best performing
schools in the country, and they are set to
receive an increase of 3%. However, in Lewes,
in my constituency, many of my small rural
primary schools are set to see a reduction.
Will the Prime Minister guarantee that she
will look at the issue of rural primary school
funding so that we can even out the distribution
of money?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right to point
out the record levels of funding that are
going into schools. It is also the case, as
I said earlier, that over the years there
has been a general acceptance across this
House that the current system of funding is
not fair in certain parts of the country.
That is why we want to end that postcode lottery
and look at a system that is fairer and more
up to date and that will support our plan
for a society where progress is based on merit
and not on privilege. I am very happy to look
at her concerns. I recognise that small rural
schools have particular issues, and I am happy
to look at them to ensure that we get the
funding formula right and that we can spread
the money as fairly as possible.
>> Graham Jones (Hyndburn) (Lab):
Every school in Hyndburn is facing a massive
budget cut. Why is a child in Hyndburn worth
less than a child in Tory heartlands in the
south?
>> The Prime Minister:
Currently, significant sums of money are going
to children in certain schools, sometimes
double the amount going to a child in another
school. We need to find a fairer system. We
have consulted on that system and we will
be responding to that consultation.
I note what the hon. Gentleman has said about
the Leader of the Opposition, the leader of
his party. He said:
“He’s not fit to rule. The public see
this is a man who doesn’t take responsibility
seriously and that he can’t take the party
forward other than in a divisive way.”
If he cannot take the party forward, how can
he hope to take the country forward?
>> Derek Thomas (St Ives) (Con):
Small businesses provide the lion’s share
of jobs in Cornwall and on the Isles of Scilly.
The difficulties of attracting credit, rising
operational costs and red tape make running
a small business an increasingly difficult
task. What can my right hon. Friend the Prime
Minister do to help small businesses so that
they can continue to be the engine of rural
economies like West Cornwall’s?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right that small
businesses are the engine of the economy.
I know that he has been a champion of small
businesses in his constituency. He recognises
that if we are to ensure that we can create
those jobs, we have to encourage small businesses.
That is why in the Budget my right hon. Friend
the Chancellor provided £435 million to support
businesses in England facing the steepest
business rate increases, why we will cut business
rates by nearly £9 billion over the next
five years, and why we have listened to small
businesses and given more than 3 million of
them an extra year to prepare for Making Tax
Digital. I recognise the importance of small
businesses in Cornwall, and I look forward
to visiting in the next few weeks and being
able to talk my hon. Friend and others about
the importance of small businesses in the
county.
>> Tim Farron (Westmorland and Lonsdale) (LD):
I join the Prime Minister in the expressions
of condolence that she led earlier.
This election can change the direction of
our country, from the consequences of a potential
hard Brexit outside the single market to the
future of our NHS and social care, our schools
and our environment. The British public deserve
to hear the party leaders set out their plans
and debate them publicly, but the Prime Minister
has refused to take part in televised leaders
debates. Back in 1992, when she and I were
both candidates, we debated publicly, forcefully
and amicably. Indeed, she called out the then
incumbent for not showing up for some of those
debates. Why will she not debate those issues
publicly now? What is she scared of?
>> The Prime Minister:
I can assure the hon. Gentleman that I will
be debating these issues publicly across the
country, as will every single member of the
Conservative team. We will be taking out there
the proud record of a Conservative Government,
but, more than that, we will be taking our
plans for the future of this country, for
making Brexit a success and delivering a stronger
Britain. He talks about the possibility of
changing the future of this country. What
do we know that the leader of the Labour party,
the leader of the Liberal Democrats and the
leader of the Scottish nationalists have in
common? Corbyn, Farron and Sturgeon want to
unite together to divide our country, and
we will not let them do it.
>> John Stevenson (Carlisle) (Con):
The Government wish to pursue a national industrial
strategy. Cumbria has some specific strengths,
such as tourism, agriculture and nuclear,
but it also has some weaknesses. Will the
Prime Minister agree that any industrial strategy
in the next Parliament must take into account
regional and sub-regional factors, and will
she be receptive to a Cumbrian industrial
strategy that works within a national one?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend points to a very important
part of our plans for a stronger Britain for
the future, which is the modern industrial
strategy that we are developing, because we
want an economy that works for everyone, delivers
good, high-skilled, high-paid jobs and creates
conditions for competitive world-leading businesses
to prosper here in the United Kingdom. But
he is right to say that as we look at that
industrial strategy we also need to look at
particular factors in particular parts of
the country. He has long been a champion not
just for Carlisle but for Cumbria. I recognise
the need, as does the Business Department,
to tailor the industrial strategy according
to the needs of particular areas of the country.
>> Yvette Cooper (Normanton, Pontefract and
Castleford) (Lab):
The Prime Minister yesterday said that she
was calling a general election because Parliament
was blocking Brexit, but three quarters of
MPs and two thirds of the Lords voted for
article 50, so that’s not true, is it? A
month ago, she told her official spokesman
to rule out an early general election, and
that wasn’t true either, was it? She wants
us to believe that she is a woman of her word.
Isn’t the truth that we cannot believe a
single word she says?
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The House is rather over-excited. The
question has been heard. The answer will be
heard.
>> The Prime Minister:
This House and this Parliament voted to trigger
article 50, but the Labour party made it clear
that it was thinking of voting against the
final deal, the Scottish nationalists have
said that they will vote against the legislation
necessary to leave the European Union, the
Liberal Democrats say that they are going
to grind Government to a standstill, and the
House of Lords has threatened to stop us every
inch of the way. I think it is right now to
ask the British people to put their trust
in me and the Conservative party to deliver
on their vote last year—a Brexit plan that
will make a success for this country and deliver
a stronger, fairer, global Britain in the
future.
>> Paul Scully (Sutton and Cheam) (Con):
I have seen rats and fly-tipping as a result
of bins not having been emptied for up to
three weeks across Lib Dem-run Sutton following
a shambolic change to refuse collections.
[Interruption.]When bin collections get into
the national headlines, you know something
has gone wrong. Does my right hon. Friend
agree that, in accepting greater delegated
powers, elected councillors must consult residents
properly, plan major changes carefully and
take full responsibility as accountable representatives
when things go wrong?
>> The Prime Minister:
I do not know why there are howls of derision
from the Opposition Benches, because my hon.
Friend raises an important point about an
issue that actually matters to people up and
down the country. It is our goal to reduce
littering and litter in England to ensure
that our high streets, villages and parks
are the cleanest and most pleasant places
that they can be. We have published the first
ever national litter strategy for England,
and we are supporting comprehensive and frequent
bin collections. But what my hon. Friend says
the Liberal Democrat-run Sutton Council is
doing shows not only that the Liberal Democrats
charge the highest council taxes, which we
already knew, but that under the Liberal Democrats
you pay more and get less.
>> Patricia Gibson (North Ayrshire and Arran)
(SNP):
Will the Prime Minister join the Scottish
Government, North Ayrshire Council and all
Ayrshire local authorities by today pledging
to support the Ayrshire growth deal, which
requires £350 million of targeted investment
to regenerate Ayrshire and improve the lives
and prospects of all its people?
>> The Prime Minister:
As the hon. Lady will know, we have already
shown our commitment to growth deals in Scotland
with the deals that have already been agreed.
I understand that my right hon. Friend the
Secretary of State for Scotland has met the
Scottish Government to discuss the growth
deal for Ayrshire. We are in discussions about
that deal, but we have shown our commitment
through the deals that have already been struck—for
example, for Aberdeen.
>> Sir David Amess (Southend West) (Con):
As part of Southend’s celebrations as the
alternative city of culture, stilt walkers
will walk non-stop from Southend to No. 10
Downing Street on the morning of Monday 1
May to raise money for the Music Man Project
to help people with learning difficulties,
and for a charity for child refugees. Will
my right hon. Friend arrange, on the morning
of Tuesday 2 May, for someone on her behalf
to receive the stilt walkers and accept from
Southend’s town crier the proclamation that
in this, the 125th anniversary of the founding
of the borough, Southend be declared a city?
>> The Prime Minister:
When I first heard about the stilt walkers,
I thought it sounded a bit of a tall order,
but I am sure they will be making great strides
as they approach Downing Street. I am pleased
to hear what my hon. Friend says about the
Southend celebrations, but also about the
efforts that are being made to raise funds
for very, very important causes. We will certainly
look very carefully at what can be done in
Downing Street when the stilt walkers arrive.
>> Mr Dennis Skinner (Bolsover) (Lab):
Will the Prime Minister give a guarantee that
no Tory MP who is under investigation by the
police and the legal authorities over election
expenses in the last general election will
be a candidate in this election? If she will
not accept that, this is the most squalid
election campaign that has happened in my
lifetime.
>> The Prime Minister:
I stand by all the Conservative MPs who are
in this House and who will be out there standing
again, campaigning for a Conservative Government
who will give a brighter and better future
for this country.
>> Richard Benyon (Newbury) (Con):
I am proud that my party in government has
ensured that in this country we fulfil our
commitment to NATO to spend 2% of GDP on defence
and our commitment to the UN to spend 0.7%
of GNI on overseas aid. Will my right hon.
Friend please commit the future Conservative
Government to do the same?
>> The Prime Minister:
My right hon. Friend is absolutely correct.
Obviously we have committed to meet our NATO
pledge of 2% of GDP being spent on defence
every year of this decade. We are delivering
on that. We have got a £36 billion defence
budget that will rise to almost £40 billion
by 2020-21—the biggest in Europe and second
largest in NATO. We are meeting our UN commitment
to spend 0.7% of GNI on overseas development
assistance. I can assure him that we remain
committed, as a Conservative party, to ensuring
the defence and security of this country and
to working for a stronger world.
>> Mr Speaker:
Finally, Christian Matheson.
>> Christian Matheson (City of Chester) (Lab):
Schools in Cheshire West and Chester were
already underfunded by about £400 per pupil
on average before the new national fair funding
formula came in, and now every school in Chester
is cutting staff and raising class sizes.
That is how the Government have protected
the education budget, so will the Prime Minister
explain to the House why the national funding
fair formula provides neither fairness nor
funding?
>> The Prime Minister:
As I have said in this Chamber before, we
need to look at the funding formula. We have
published proposals for fair funding, we have
consulted on those proposals, and in due course
the Government will respond to those proposals.
I was very interested to see the hon. Gentleman
being interviewed yesterday and being asked
whether he would put a photograph of the Leader
of the Opposition on his election literature.
Sadly, he said that the only photographs he
wanted on his election literature were his
own; he was not prepared to support the leader
of his own party.