>>Andrew Bridgen (North West Leicestershire)
(Con): If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 1 March.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): I
am sure that the whole House will want to
join me in wishing people in the UK, and across
the world, a happy St David’s day. I am
also sure that the whole House will want to
join me in paying tribute to our former colleague,
Sir Gerald Kaufman, who died over the weekend.
He was an outstanding parliamentarian and
a committed MP who dedicated his life to the
service of his constituents. As Father of
the House, his wisdom and experience will
be very much missed right across this House.
I am sure that our thoughts are with his friends
and family.
This morning, I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others. In addition to my duties
in this House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Andrew Bridgen: I associate myself with
the Prime Minister’s remarks, and assure
the many relatives and friends of our former
colleague that they are very much in our thoughts
and prayers at this difficult time.
Does my right hon. Friend believe that last
week’s historic by-election victory in Copeland
was an endorsement of her Government’s plans
to maintain a strong economy, bring our society
together and ensure that we make a huge success
of leaving the European Union?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for his question. First, I wish to congratulate
my hon. Friend, the new Member for Copeland,
and look forward to welcoming her to this
House very shortly. My hon. Friend the Member
for North West Leicestershire (Andrew Bridgen)
is absolutely right that last week’s historic
result in Copeland was an endorsement of our
plans to keep the economy strong and to ensure
that places such as Copeland share in the
economic success after years of Labour neglect.
It was also an endorsement of our plans to
unite communities where Labour seeks to sow
division and of offering strong, competent
leadership in the face of Labour’s chaos.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): May
I join the Prime Minister in wishing everyone
in Wales, and all Welsh people around the
world, a very happy St David’s day. May
I also express the hope that, today, the workers
at the Ford plant in Bridgend get the assurances
that they need about their job security and
their futures.
I echo the Prime Minister’s tribute to Gerald
Kaufman who served in this House since 1970
and was the longest serving Member. He started
in political life as an adviser to Harold
Wilson in the 1960s. He was an iconic, irascible
figure in the Labour party and in British
politics. He was a champion for peace and
justice in the middle east and around the
world. Yesterday at his funeral, Mr Speaker,
the rabbi who conducted the service conveyed
your message on behalf of the House to his
family, which was very much appreciated. Afterwards,
I spoke to his family and to his great nephews
and great nieces and asked them how they would
describe Gerald, and they said that he was
an “awesome uncle”. We should remember
Gerald as that, and convey our condolences
to all of his family.
Just after the last Budget, the then Work
and Pensions Secretary resigned, accusing
the Government of
“balancing the books on the backs of the
poor and vulnerable.”
Last week, the Government sneaked out a decision
to overrule a court decision to extend personal
independence payments to people with severe
mental health conditions. A Government who
found £1 billion in inheritance tax cuts
to benefit 26,000 families seem unable to
find the money to support 160,000 people with
debilitating mental health conditions. Will
the Prime Minister change her mind?
>>The Prime Minister: Let me be very clear
about what is being proposed in relation to
personal independence payments. This is not
a policy change—[Interruption.] This is
not a cut in the amount spent on disability
benefits, and no one is going to see a reduction
in their benefits from that previously awarded
by the Department for Work and Pensions. What
we are doing is restoring the original intention
of the payment agreed by the coalition Government,
and agreed by this Parliament after extensive
consultation.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Extensive consultation is
an interesting idea, because the court made
its decision last year, the Government did
not consult the Social Security Advisory Committee
and, at the last minute, sneaked out their
decision.
The court ruled that the payments should be
made because the people who were to benefit
from them were suffering “overwhelming psychological
distress”. Just a year ago, the then new
Work and Pensions Secretary said:
“I can tell the House that we will not be
going ahead with the changes to PIP that had
been put forward.”
The court has since made a ruling. The Prime
Minister’s colleague the hon. Member for
South Cambridgeshire (Heidi Allen) said:
“In my view, the courts are there for a
reason. If they have come up with this ruling,
which says that the criteria should be extended,
then I believe we have a duty to honour that.”
Is she not right?
>>The Prime Minister: First, on the issue
of these payments and those with mental health
conditions, the personal independence payment
is better for people with mental health conditions.
The figures show that two thirds of people
with mental health conditions who are claiming
personal independence payments and in receipt
of it are awarded the higher daily living
rate allowance, compared with less than a
quarter under the previous disability living
allowance arrangements.
This is the second time that the right hon.
Gentleman has suggested that somehow the change
was sneaked out. It was in a written ministerial
statement to Parliament. I might remind him
that week after week he talks to me about
the importance of Parliament; well, we accepted
the importance of Parliament and made the
statement to Parliament. He also referred
to the Social Security Advisory Committee,
and it can look at this matter. My right hon.
Friend the Work and Pensions Secretary called
the Chairman of the SSAC and spoke to him
about the regulations on the day they were
being introduced; he also called the Chairman
of the Select Committee on Work and Pensions
and spoke to him about the regulations that
were being introduced; and he called both
offices of the shadow Work and Pensions Secretary,
but there was no answer and they did not come
back to him for four days.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Calling—[Interruption.]
Calling the Chairs of two Committees and making
a written statement to the House does not
add up to scrutiny, and as I understand it
no call was made to the office of my hon.
Friend the Member for Oldham East and Saddleworth
(Debbie Abrahams), the shadow Secretary of
State.
The reality is that this is a shameful decision
that will affect people with dementia, those
suffering cognitive disorders due to a stroke,
military veterans with post-traumatic stress
disorder, and those with schizophrenia. Will
the Prime Minister look at the effects of
her decision to override what an independent
court has decided, and think again?
>>The Prime Minister: The issues and conditions
that the right hon. Gentleman raises are taken
into account when decisions are made about
personal independence payments. The court
said that the regulations were unclear; that
is why we are clarifying the regulations and
ensuring that they respect and reflect the
original intention that was agreed by this
Parliament.
If the right hon. Gentleman wants to talk
about the support being given to people with
disabilities, I say to him that this Government
are spending more than ever in support for
people with disability and health conditions,
and we are spending more than ever on people
with mental health conditions. What we are
doing with personal independence payments
is ensuring that those who are most in need
get most support.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The Government have overridden
an independent court decision, and they should
think long and hard about that. The Prime
Minister’s hon. Friend, the right hon. Member
for North East Bedfordshire (Alistair Burt),
said this week that the Government have to
“make it very clear that physical and mental
health has the same priority”.
In 2002, the Prime Minister made a speech
to the Conservative party conference. I remember
it very well; I was watching it on television.
She described her party as the “nasty party”
and said:
“Some Tories have tried to make political
capital by demonising minorities”.
This week, her policy chair suggested that
people with debilitating conditions were those
who were
“taking pills at home, who suffer from anxiety”
and were not “really disabled”. Is that
not proof that the “nasty party” is still
around?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
has rightly apologised for the comments that
he made, and I hope that the whole House will
accept his apology. The right hon. Gentleman
asks me about parity between mental health
conditions and physical conditions. It is
this Conservative Government who introduced
parity of esteem in dealing with mental health
in the national health service. How many years
were Labour in government and did nothing
about it? Thirteen years!
>>Jeremy Corbyn: It was a Labour amendment
to the Health and Social Care Bill that resulted
in parity of esteem being put on the face
of the Bill. I am surprised that the right
hon. Lady has forgotten that; she could have
taken this opportunity to thank the Labour
party for putting it forward. The Prime Minister
made a speech earlier this year supporting
parity of esteem for mental health, and I
am glad she did so. However, 40% of NHS mental
health trusts are having their budgets cut,
and there are 6,600 fewer mental health nurses
and 160,000 people with severe mental health
conditions who are about to lose out on support.
Can she not recognise that parity of esteem
means funding it properly and not overriding
court decisions that would benefit people
suffering from very difficult conditions?
We should reach out to them, not deny them
the support they need.
>>The Prime Minister: As I say, we are spending
more than ever on mental health—£11.4 billion
a year. More people each week are now receiving
treatment in relation to mental health than
previously. Is there more for us to do on
mental health? Yes, there is. I have said
that in this Chamber in answer to questions
that I have received—
>>Emily Thornberry (Islington South and Finsbury)
(Lab): Well, do it!
>>The Prime Minister: The shadow Foreign Secretary
shouts, “Well, do it” from her normal
sedentary position—[Interruption.] We are
doing it. That is why we are putting record
amounts of money into mental health. That
is why we are seeing more people being provided
with mental health treatment every week under
this Government. There is one thing that I
know: if we are going to be able to provide
that extra support for people with disabilities
and health conditions and provide treatment
for people with mental health conditions,
we need a strong economy that enables us to
pay for it. And the one thing we know about
Labour is that they would bankrupt Britain.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: That is rich, coming from
a Government who, by 2020, will have borrowed
more and increased the national debt by the
total borrowing of all Labour Governments.
The mental health charity Rethink has said:
“The Government has spoken forcefully about
the importance of parity esteem between physical
and mental health, yet when presented with
the chance to make this a reality...it has
passed on the opportunity”.
As a society, we are judged by how we treat
the most vulnerable. The respected mental
health charity Mind has said:
“This misguided legislation must be reversed”.
Will the Prime Minister look again at the
decision of the court and its consequences,
withdraw this nasty decision, accept the court’s
judgment and support those who are going through
a very difficult time in their lives? That
is how we will all be judged.
>>The Prime Minister: The way we are dealing
with disability benefits is to ensure that
payments are going to those who are most vulnerable.
What we are doing in relation to personal
independence payments is ensuring that the
agreement of this Parliament is being put
into practice. The right hon. Gentleman talks
about funding and he talks about borrowing.
I understand that today—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. We cannot have a constant
debate while the Prime Minister is answering
the question. The question has been put and
was heard, and the answer must be heard without
a constant hubbub in the background.
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
talks about accepting the court’s decision
and paying for that. When asked how Labour
would pay for the increase if it was put in
place, I understand that the Labour shadow
Health Secretary said today, “Err, we’ve
not outlined that yet.” That just sums up
the Labour party and the Labour party leadership.
After the result in Copeland last week, the
hon. Member for Lancaster and Fleetwood (Cat
Smith) summed up the by-election result by
saying that it was an “incredible result”
for the Labour party. I think that word describes
the right hon. Gentleman’s leadership: incredible.
>>Stephen Metcalfe (South Basildon and East
Thurrock) (Con): On Monday, I chaired a seminar
at the Royal Society looking at the priorities
for the science community as we start our
Brexit negotiations, and a report of the meeting
will be launched here in Parliament on 21
March. While I of course understand that the
Prime Minister may be too busy to attend,
will she meet me once the report is published
so that I can present to her in person the
collective concerns of the science community,
particularly those around collaboration and
people?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising that important issue, which he
is right to raise. We want the UK to be the
go-to place for innovators and investors across
the world, and we want to secure the best
possible outcomes for the UK research base
as we leave the European Union. Indeed, one
of the objectives that I set out for our negotiations
with the European Union relates to science
and research. We already are a leading destination
for science and innovation, and we would welcome
an agreement to continue to collaborate with
our European partners. I am interested in
what my hon. Friend has said, and I am sure
that that report will be looked at carefully
by my right hon. Friend the Secretary of State
for Exiting the European Union.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): We on the
SNP Benches join the Prime Minister and the
leader of the Labour Party in extending our
condolences to the family and friends of Sir
Gerald Kaufman. We also extend our best wishes
to the people of Wales on St David’s Day.
In Scottish questions just prior to PMQs today,
Ministers were unable to answer basic questions
about the Government’s plans for agriculture
and for fisheries. Those are important industries
for the rural economy and are devolved to
the Scottish Government and the Scottish Parliament.
With Brexit ending the role of Brussels in
those areas, will all decisions about agriculture
and fisheries be made at Holyrood—yes or
no?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
knows well that we are discussing with the
devolved Administrations the whole question
of the UK framework and devolution of issues
as they come back from Brussels. The overriding
aim for everything that we do when we make
those decisions is to ensure that we do not
damage the important single market of the
United Kingdom, a market which I remind the
right hon. Gentleman is more important to
Scotland than the European Union is.
>>Angus Robertson: That is a very interesting
answer because people in Scotland, including
those working in the agriculture and fisheries
sectors, were told during the Brexit referendum
that farming and fisheries powers would be
exercised fully by the Scottish Government
and the Scottish Parliament. Judging by the
Prime Minister’s answer, however, it seems
that that will not be true. Will the Prime
Minister confirm today—she has the opportunity—that
it is her intention to ensure that UK Ministers
will negotiate and regulate over large areas
that impact on Scottish fisheries and agriculture
post-Brexit?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
seems not to have understood this point, so
I will repeat it. We are in the process of
discussing with the devolved Administrations
the whole question of which of the powers
that currently reside in Brussels will be
returned and will remain at a UK level for
decisions and which powers will be further
devolved to the devolved Administrations.
That is the discussion that is taking place
at the moment. He asks about the Brexit negotiations
with the European Union, and it will be the
UK Government that will be negotiating with
the European Union, taking full account of
the interests and concerns of the devolved
Administrations and, indeed, of all the regions
of England.
>>Nigel Adams (Selby and Ainsty) (Con): Does
the Prime Minister agree that, when tickets
to a teenage cancer charity gig by Ed Sheeran
are being resold on the viagogo ticket website
for more than £1,000, with none of that money
going to the charity, and tickets to the hit
musical “Hamilton” are being touted for
upwards of £5,000 when viagogo knows only
too well that resold tickets are invalid for
entry, it is unfair and not indicative of
a market that works for everyone? What will
the Government do to ensure that genuine fans
are not fleeced by ticket touts and rogues?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising that important issue, which I
know he has been working on for some time.
He is absolutely right to identify circumstances
where websites are acting in that way and
causing those problems for people who genuinely
believe that they are able to buy tickets
for what they wish to attend. I understand
that he recently met my right hon. Friend
the Minister for Digital and Culture to discuss
the issue. As my hon. Friend will be aware,
the Consumer Rights Act 2015 introduced new
rules on ticketing and a review of online
ticket sales. The Department for Culture,
Media and Sport will shortly respond to the
independent report by Professor Michael Waterson
on this issue, but as a Government we are
looking at the general issue of where markets
are not working in the interest of consumers.
>>Mr Steve Reed (Croydon North) (Lab): I add
my condolences to those already expressed
about the former Father of the House, and
I welcome my new hon. Friend the Member for
Stoke-on-Trent Central (Gareth Snell) to his
place. Young black men who use mental health
services are more likely than other people
to be subject to detention, extreme forms
of medication and severe physical restraint,
and, in extreme cases, this has led to death,
including that of my constituent Seni Lewis.
Too many black people with mental ill health
are afraid to seek treatment from a service
they fear will not treat them fairly. Will
the Prime Minister meet me and some of the
affected families to discuss the need for
an inquiry into institutional racism in the
mental health service?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to welcome
the new hon. Member for Stoke-on-Trent Central
(Gareth Snell) to this House. It is precisely
because of concern about how various people
were being treated within our public services
that last year I introduced a racial audit
of the disparity of treatment within public
services. As Home Secretary, I saw this when
I looked at the way that people, particularly
black people with mental health issues, were
being dealt with by the police and in various
forms of detention. That is exactly the sort
of issue that we are looking at. I am very
happy for the hon. Member for Croydon North
(Mr Reed) to write to me with the details
of the particular issue that he set out.
>>Jo Churchill (Bury St Edmunds) (Con): Will
the Prime Minister join me in congratulating
my West Suffolk College, all its staff and,
in particular, its principal, Nikos Savvas,
on winning the prestigious teaching and learning
initiative award for the whole country at
last week’s Times Educational Supplement
further education awards by combining the
teaching of maths, art, religion and science?
I am sure the Prime Minister will agree that
that initiative drives forward inquisitive
minds and grows the skills that future generations
will need to succeed.
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to join
my hon. Friend in congratulating West Suffolk
College on being given that award for best
teaching and learning initiative for its MARS
initiative. The college has put in place a
really interesting initiative, and I congratulate
all its staff. This award is a sign of the
dedication of the staff and students at West
Suffolk College. All colleges across the country
should be aspiring to reach these standards,
and she is absolutely right that we need to
ensure that young people have not just a skillset
but an inquiring mind that enables them, as
they look forward to what may be different
careers throughout their life, to embrace
new skills and change.
>>Mary Glindon (North Tyneside) (Lab): My
constituent Joanne Good’s 16-year-old daughter,
Megan, tragically died after drinking half
a three-litre bottle of Frosty Jack’s cider,
which is 7.5% and, at under £4 a bottle,
contains 22 vodka-shot equivalents. Does the
Prime Minister accept that cheap, super-strength,
white cider is a health hazard and should
be banned or at the very least carry a much
higher duty per unit?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I am sure that
Members from across the whole House will want
to join me in offering our deepest sympathies
to the family of this 16-year-old constituent—former
constituent—of the hon. Lady. She raises
an important issue, which is why the Government
recognise the harm associated with the problem
consumption of alcohol. We have taken action
through the duty system, so that high-strength
ciders and beers are taxed more than equivalent
lower-strength products. We have also, of
course, taken action on the very cheap alcohol
by banning sales below duty plus VAT. But
another element is involved, too, which is
making sure that young people are aware of
the dangers and harms of alcohol misuse. Public
Health England and the NHS have run campaigns
offering advice and support to young people,
and they also work with charities and in schools
to help to raise that awareness. I think that
is an important part of this.
>>Bob Blackman (Harrow East) (Con): We are
rightly proud that young people can study
at our colleges and universities regardless
of race, creed or colour, yet this week Jewish
students are being subjected to intimidation,
fear and anti-Semitism as the result of the
so-called Israeli apartheid week. What action
can my right hon. Friend take to make sure
that chancellors and principals ensure that
anti-Semitism is not allowed to prosper on
campuses?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I want to assure
my hon. Friend that higher education institutions
have a responsibility to ensure that they
provide a safe and inclusive environment for
all students. We expect them to have robust
policies and procedures in place to comply
with the law, and to investigate and swiftly
address hate crime, including any anti-Semitic
incidents that are reported. I know that my
hon. Friend the Minister for Universities,
Science, Research and Innovation has recently
written to remind institutions of these expectations,
and he has also urged them to follow the Government’s
lead in adopting the International Holocaust
Remembrance Alliance definition of anti-Semitism.
>>Roger Mullin (Kirkcaldy and Cowdenbeath)
(SNP): There is a flaw in the legislative
reform order with which the Government are
seeking to create private fund limited partnerships,
which allows criminal-owned Scottish limited
partnerships to convert easily to these new
types of partnerships. Will the Prime Minister
step in and delay the LRO until such time
as the current Department for Business, Energy
and Industrial Strategy review on SLPs is
completed?
>>The Prime Minister: We have taken important
steps to tackle money laundering, terrorist
financing and other economic crimes; I oversaw
the establishment of the economic crime command
in the National Crime Agency. On the question
the hon. Gentleman raises on SLPs, I understand
that BEIS consulted last year on further transparency
requirements for SLPs and will be publishing
proposals soon, and that my right hon. Friend
the Business, Energy and Industrial Strategy
Secretary is gathering evidence which may
lead to further reform.
>>Andrew Bingham (High Peak) (Con): My right
hon. Friend will be aware of the concerns
about the new business rates. Although there
is a welcome from many of the businesses in
the High Peak that will be taken out of business
rates, there is a concern among those who
have seen an increase—in one case one of
as much as 85%. Can she give me an assurance,
and give those businesses an assurance, that
we will do all we can for these people, who
work incredibly hard to be the engine room
of our economy, as a rise of this size may
threaten their livelihoods?
>>The Prime Minister: As my hon. Friend will
know, business rates are based on property
value and it has been seven years since property
values were last looked at, so I think it
is absolutely right that we update them. But
of course, as I recognised last week, there
are different impacts on different businesses,
and it is important that we have already put
significant sums into transitional support
for businesses so that we help the companies
that are facing increased bills. As I said
in this House last week, I have asked my right
hon. Friends the Chancellor and the Communities
and Local Government Secretary to make sure
that the support that is provided is appropriate
and is in place for the hardest cases. I would
expect my right hon. Friend the Chancellor
to say more about this next week in the Budget.
>>Sarah Olney (Richmond Park) (LD): A recent
National Audit Office report exposed massive
Government overspend on new free school sites,
and the Department for Education estimates
that it will need to spend a further £2.5
billion on land for these schools. Schools
throughout my constituency are reporting chronic
levels of underfunding. Will the Prime Minister
please review the plans for new free schools
and provide existing schools with the investment
they need?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to say to
the hon. Lady that we have, of course, protected
the core schools budget in real terms. Yes,
we have had free schools—I understand that
she raises a concern about them—but we have
seen the programme of free schools and academies
continue under this Government to ensure that
we are creating more good school places throughout
the country. That is what we want to do and
that is what our policy will continue to do.
>>Glyn Davies (Montgomeryshire) (Con): I join
the Prime Minister in wishing Wales a happy
dydd Dewi Sant—St David’s day. The Secretary
of State for Wales has been working with colleagues
across Government to send out to the world
the message that Wales is one of the best
places in the United Kingdom to live, work,
visit and trade with. Does the Prime Minister
agree that Welsh interests must remain at
the heart of our United Kingdom? As we leave
the European Union, the future of the UK Union
has never been more important.
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for that question. He is absolutely right
to raise the importance of Wales. My right
hon. Friend the Wales Secretary is doing important
work to remind the world that Wales is one
of the best places in the UK to live, work
and trade with. In the forthcoming negotiations
we are committed to getting a deal that works
for all parts of the UK, including Wales.
The best way to achieve that is for the UK
Government and the devolved Administrations
to continue to work together. I am pleased
to say that I am going to be hosting a St
David’s day reception in Downing Street
tonight to celebrate everything that Wales
has to offer. I once again wish all Members
of this House dydd Gŵyl Dewi hapus.
>>Judith Cummins (Bradford South) (Lab): Congestion,
journey times and connectivity between Bradford
and Leeds are among the worst in the country.
Will the Prime Minister support the campaign
to ensure that Bradford is part of the High
Speed 3 network? Will she commit to delivering
the investments we so desperately need for
our West Yorkshire powerhouse?
>>The Prime Minister: I apologise to the hon.
Lady, but I missed the first part of her question.
I think she was talking about investment in
infrastructure in her area. [Interruption.]
HS3, right. The Government have obviously
already set out the commitments we have made
on infrastructure. As she will know, we believe
infrastructure plays an important part in
encouraging the growth of the economy and
ensuring that we see increased productivity
around the rest of the country. Over time,
we will of course be looking at further projects
that can do just that.
>>Victoria Prentis (Banbury) (Con): When I
was canvassing in Copeland recently, people
there wanted to talk about the future of their
local maternity unit; it was just like being
at home in Banbury. Rather than politicise
the NHS, would the Prime Minister agree to
a review of maternity services, encouraging
care that is not just safe but kind and close
to home?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend makes
an important point about local maternity services.
As I have said, I am looking forward to welcoming
the new Member for Copeland to this House
very shortly. During the recent campaign,
she made it very clear that she did not want
to see any downgrading of the West Cumberland
hospital services. She also did something
else. She put forward a powerful case for
what my hon. Friend the Member for Banbury
(Victoria Prentis) has just suggested: a review
to tackle the recruitment issues that affect
the maternity services up there. A professionally
led review seems very sensible, and I know
that the Health Minister is looking into it.
>>Alex Cunningham (Stockton North) (Lab):
A 19-year-old constituent of mine faces being
discharged by the Tees, Esk and Wear Valley
mental health trust for a second time because
the trust has neither the skills nor the cash
to provide the support he needs. What is the
Prime Minister’s message to him?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sorry, but I obviously
do not know the full details of the individual
case raised by the hon. Gentleman. We are
ensuring that more money is being—and will
continue to be—put into mental health conditions
over the year. I am sure that the Secretary
of State for Health will look into that case,
if the hon. Gentleman wants to write to him
about it.
>>Andrew Selous (South West Bedfordshire)
(Con): As a leader who wants to spread wealth
and opportunity as widely as possible, will
the Prime Minister ensure that we end the
practice of developers buying freehold land
on which they then sell new houses on a leasehold
basis? Many first time buyers on Help to Buy
feel that they are being ripped off by this
practice and look to the Government for help.
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for mentioning that issue, which he has raised
with me previously. I know he is concerned
about it and working on it. Our housing White
Paper clearly sets out that developers should
be building homes for people to live in. That
means that we will act to promote fairness
for the growing number of leaseholders, but
we will consult on a range of measures to
tackle unfair and unreasonable abuses of leasehold,
as the Housing Minister has said. Other than
in certain exceptional circumstances, I do
not see why new homes should not be built
and sold with the freehold interest at the
point of sale.
>>Sir Kevin Barron (Rother Valley) (Lab):
May I add my condolences to the family of
Gerald Kaufman, who was one of my friends
in this place? I received an email yesterday
from a local pharmacist who, since the Government
announcement in October last year, has had
to implement cost-cutting measures, including
to staff and services. This week he received
a notification of the payment for prescriptions
dispensed in December last year, and has had
a reduction of nearly £9,000, which represents
an 18.8% cut—well beyond the 4% that the
Under-Secretary of State for Health, the hon.
Member for Warrington South (David Mowat)—the
pharmacies Minister—spoke about in October.
Will the Government commit to revisit community
pharmacy funding as a matter of urgency?
>>The Prime Minister: We all recognise the
important service that pharmacies provide,
which is why spending on them has actually
risen in recent years. There has been an increase
of more than 18% in the number of pharmacies
over the past decade. The system needs to
reform so that NHS resources are spent efficiently
and effectively. Let us look at some of the
figures: two fifths of pharmacies are within
10 minutes’ walk of two or more other pharmacies;
the average pharmacy receives roughly £220,000
a year in NHS funding; and most pharmacies
receive the £25,000 establishment payment,
regardless of size or quality. We looked at
this concern when it was raised last summer,
and made changes to ensure that greater support
was available to pharmacies in particular
areas.
>>Mr Peter Bone (Wellingborough) (Con): One
of David Cameron’s greatest legacies was
his effort to fight human trafficking under
the Modern Slavery Act 2015. Last year, this
country looked after 800,000 children in Syria
or the surrounding countries for the same
investment as looking after 3,000 in this
country. By doing that, we help to defeat
human trafficking. Will the Prime Minister
confirm that we will continue with that policy?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to join
my hon. Friend in paying tribute to David
Cameron. I was pleased that he supported the
Modern Slavery Act when I proposed introducing
it. We are, indeed, committed to continuing
our policy in this area. I have set up, and
chair, a modern slavery taskforce at No. 10,
bringing together various parties to ensure
that we are doing what is necessary across
Government to break the criminal gangs, deal
with the perpetrators and provide the necessary
support for victims.
>>Mr Nigel Dodds (Belfast North) (DUP): May
I, on behalf of my hon. and right hon. Friends,
join the Prime Minister and the Leader of
the Opposition in expressing condolences to
the family of the late Father of the House?
He will be greatly missed. The Prime Minister
cannot fail to have noticed the recent intervention
in the Brexit debate by two former Prime Ministers;
I am sure they were very helpful. I am sure
that she will know what they and everybody
else mean by “hard Brexit” and by “soft
Brexit”, but we are all now wondering what
is meant by a “soft coup”, when
it might be triggered, and when, indeed, we
will know whether it has been triggered. Perhaps
the Prime Minister will elucidate on that
since she has been so helpful in many other
ways. Will she take the opportunity today,
however, to make it clear that, whatever former
Prime Ministers or Members of the unelected
upper House may say, the reality is that her
plan to trigger article 50 by the end of March
is now clearly on track?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank the right hon.
Gentleman for that question. It is, indeed,
my plan to trigger by the end of March, and
when I refer to that, I refer, of course,
to the triggering of article 50, rather than
attempting to trigger any coup, soft or otherwise,
that might take place. It is still our intention
to do that. It is important; the article 50
Bill, of course, does respond to the judgment
of the Supreme Court, but it also ensures
that we are responding to the voice of the
United Kingdom, when people voted to ensure
that we do leave the European Union, and that
is what we will do.
>>Rebecca Pow (Taunton Deane) (Con): Mr Speaker,
perhaps you, like many other hon. Members
here today, took a shower this morning—[Laughter.]
I am sure you were very careful to check whether
the shower gel contained microbeads. [Hon.
Members: “Ah!”]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. We must hear the thrust
of this fascinating question. Mrs Pow, let’s
hear it.
>>Rebecca Pow: Shower gel products containing
microbeads can result in 100,000 microbeads
or microplastics being washed down the drain
every time we use them—into the water system,
and then into the marine environment, damaging
these precious habitats. Would the Prime Minister
join me in welcoming the steps this Government
are taking to introduce a ban on microbeads
used in cosmetics and personal care products,
with the consultation ending just a few days
ago?
>>The Prime Minister: I think I should say
for clarity to Members of this House that
I am not in a position to know whether or
not you took a shower this morning, Mr Speaker.
My hon. Friend has raised a very important
point. It is completely unnecessary to add
plastics to products like face washes and
body scrub, where harmless alternatives can
be used. As she said at the end of her question,
our consultation to ban microbeads in cosmetics
and personal care products closed recently.
We are aiming to change legislation by October
2017, and we also ask for evidence of what
more can be done in future to prevent other
sources of plastic from entering the marine
environment, because we are committed to being
the first generation ever to leave the environment
in a better state than when it was inherited.
I am sure that, together, we can all work
to bring an end to these harmful plastics
clogging up our oceans.
>>Mr Speaker: I think both Philip and Sally
are very reassured by what the Prime Minister
has just said.
>>Mrs Madeleine Moon (Bridgend) (Lab): Along
the M4 corridor in south Wales, over 1,000
families woke up this morning deeply worried
about potential job losses at Ford in Bridgend.
Families in Ogmore and Bridgend are particularly
frightened—frightened that Ford is not going
to be able to bring new contracts into the
factory, with the uncertainty of Brexit ahead.
Can I have an assurance from the Prime Minister
that she will arrange for her Ministers to
meet Ford and Unite the union to see what
can be done to support Ford to ensure continuity
of engine production in the Bridgend plant?
>>The Prime Minister: Can I reassure the hon.
Lady that our automotive sector is one of
the most productive in the world? We want
to see it going from strength to strength.
That is why Ministers in this Government have
been engaging with various companies within
the automotive sector, including Ford and
other companies. Ford is an important investor
here; it has been established here for over
100 years. We now account for around a third
of Ford’s global engine production, and
Bridgend continues to be an important part
of that. We have had, as I said, dialogue
with Ford; we will continue to have a regular
dialogue with Ford about the ways in which
Government can help to make sure that this
success continues.