>>Yasmin Qureshi (Bolton South East) (Lab):
If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 22 February.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): This
morning I had meetings with ministerial colleagues
and others. In addition to my duties in this
House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Yasmin Qureshi: Yesterday, the campaign
group fighting cuts at West Cumberland hospital
was due to deliver a 30,000-strong petition
to Downing Street. Despite having a slot booked,
they were turned away at the gates and told,
“Today isn’t a good day. Come back after
Thursday.” How can the Prime Minister justify
this disgraceful dismissal of the people of
Copeland?
>>The Prime Minister: A petition was indeed
delivered to No. 10. The petition was accepted
by No. 10 Downing Street yesterday, so I suggest
to the hon. Lady that she considers what she
said in her question. I am aware of the issues
that have been raised around West Cumberland
hospital. I am aware of them because the very
good Conservative candidate in Copeland, Trudy
Harrison, has raised them with me. She has
made it very clear that she wants to see no
downgrading of services at West Cumberland
hospital. She has made that clear to me and
to Health Ministers.
>>Andrew Bingham (High Peak) (Con): I recently
met many of my local headteachers in the High
Peak, and they are concerned about the new
national funding formula. Can my right hon.
Friend assure me that when we decide on the
funding for our schools, we will look at unavoidable
costs, such as the national apprenticeship
levy, to ensure that our schools have the
money that they need to educate our children?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising this. The question of schools
funding, and the system we have for schools
funding, is important. I think the current
system is unfair. It is not transparent and
it is out of date. That has been the general
view for some time now. The problem is that
it cannot support the aspiration of all our
children to get a great education. We do,
indeed, want children to be able to get the
education that they deserve and that ensures
that they can go as far as their talents and
hard work take them. The Labour Government
did nothing to address the funding system.
We are looking at that funding system. It
is a consultation, and I am sure that the
comments and the issue my hon. Friend has
raised will be noted by the Secretary of State
for Education.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): When
hospitals are struggling to provide essential
care, why is the Prime Minister’s Government
cutting the number of beds in our national
health service?
>>The Prime Minister: Thanks to the medical
advances, to the use of technology and to
the quality of care, what we see on hospital
stays is actually that the average length
of time for staying in hospital has virtually
halved since the year 2000. Let us look at
Labour’s record on this issue. In the last
six years of the last Labour Government, 25,000
hospital beds were cut. But we do not even
need to go as far back as that. Let us just
look at Labour’s policy before the last
election, because before the last election,
the right hon. Member for Leigh (Andy Burnham),
a former Labour shadow Health Secretary, said
the following:
“what I’d cut…are hospital beds”.
Labour policy: cut hospital beds.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: In 2010, there was the highest
ever level of satisfaction with the national
health service, delivered by a Labour Government.
The British Medical Association—[Interruption.]
It’s doctors. The British Medical Association
tells us that 15,000 beds have been cut in
the past six years, the equivalent of 24 hospitals,
and as a result, we have longer waiting times
at A&E, record delayed discharges and more
people on waiting lists. The Prime Minister
claims the NHS is getting the money it needs,
so why is it that one in six A&amp;E units
in England are set for closure or downgrading?
>>The Prime Minister: I will tell the right
hon. Gentleman what is happening and what
has happened since 2010 in A&E: we see 1,500
more emergency care doctors—that includes
600 more A&E consultants—and we have got
2,400 more paramedics. We have more people
being seen in accident and emergency every
single week under this Government. He talks
about what the NHS needs: what the NHS needs
is more doctors—we are giving it more doctors;
what it needs is more funding—we are giving
it more funding. What it does not need is
a bankrupt economy, which is exactly what
Labour would give it.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I asked the Prime Minister
why one in six A&E units are currently set
for closure or downgrading; she did not answer.
One of the problems—she well knows this—is
the £4.6 billion cut to social care, which
has a knock-on effect. Her friend the Tory
chair of the Local Government Association,
Lord Porter, has said that
“extra council tax income will not bring
in anywhere near enough money to alleviate
the growing pressure on social care”.
Two weeks ago, we found out about the sweetheart
deal with Tory Surrey. When will the other
151 social services departments in England
get the same as the Surrey deal?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
refers to the questions he asked me about
Surrey County Council two weeks ago. Those
claims were utterly destroyed the same afternoon,
so rather than asking the same question, he
should stand up and apologise.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Far from my apologising,
it is the Prime Minister who ought to be reading
her correspondence and answering the letter
from 62 council leaders representing social
service authorities who want to know if they
are going to get the same deal as Surrey.
They are grappling with a crisis, which has
left over 1 million people not getting the
social care they need.
We opposed Tory cuts in the NHS which involved
scrapping nurses’ bursaries, because we
feared it would discourage people from entering
training. The Prime Minister’s Government
said that removing funding for nurses’ bursaries
would create an extra 10,000 training places
in this Parliament. Has this target been met?
>>The Prime Minister: There are 10,000 more
training places available for nurses in the
NHS. The right hon. Gentleman talks about
the amount of money being spent on the NHS.
It is this Conservative Government who are
putting the extra funding into the NHS. I
remind him that we are spending £1.3 billion
more on the NHS this year than Labour planned
to spend if it had won the election.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My questions were about social
services funding to pay for social care—no
answer. My questions were about the number
of training places for nurses being brought
in—no answer. In reality, 10,000 fewer places
have been filled because there are fewer applications.
A problem is building up for the future. In
addition, the Royal College of Midwives estimates
that there is a shortage of 3,500 midwives
in England, and the Royal College of Nursing
warns:
“The nursing workforce is in crisis and
if fewer nurses graduate in 2020 it will exacerbate
what is already an unsustainable situation”.
Will the Prime Minister at least commit herself
to reinstating the nurses’ bursary?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
asked me a question about nursing training
places, which I answered. If he does not like
the answer he gets, he cannot just carry on
asking the same question if I have answered
it previously. He talks about all these issues
in relation to what is happening in the NHS,
so let us look at what is happening in the
NHS: we have 1,800 more midwives in the NHS
since 2010; we have more people being seen
in accident and emergency since 2010; and
we have more operations taking place every
week in the NHS. Our NHS staff are working
hard. They are providing quality care for
patients up and down the country. What they
do not need is a Labour party policy that
leads to a bankrupt economy. Labour’s policy
is to spend money on everything, which means
bankrupting the economy and having no money
to spend on anything. That does not help doctors
and nurses, it does not help patients, it
does not help the NHS, and it does not help
ordinary working families up and down this
country.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Yes, let us look at the national
health service and let us thank all those
who work so hard in our national health service,
but also recognise the pressures they are
under. Today, a Marie Curie report finds that
nurses are so overstretched they cannot provide
the high-quality care needed for patients
at the very end of their lives. The lack of
care in the community prevents people from
having the dignity of dying at home. There
is a nursing shortage and something should
be done about it, such as reinstating the
nurses’ bursary.
The Prime Minister’s Government have put
the NHS and social care in a state of emergency.
Nine out of 10 NHS trusts are unsafe, 18,000
patients a week are waiting—[Interruption.]
Mr Speaker, I repeat the figure: 18,000 patients
a week are waiting on trolleys in hospital
corridors and 1.2 million often very dependent—[Interruption.]
It seems to me that some Members are not concerned
about the fact that there are 1.2 million
elderly people who are not getting the care
they need. The legacy of her Government will
blight our NHS for decades: fewer hospitals,
fewer A&E departments, fewer nurses and fewer
people getting the care they need. We need
a Government who will put the NHS first and
will invest in our NHS.
>>The Prime Minister: First, the right hon.
Gentleman should consider correcting the record,
because 54% of hospital trusts are considered
good or outstanding—quite different from
the figure he cited. Secondly, I will take
no lessons on the NHS from the party—[Interruption.]
Oh, the deputy leader of the Labour party
says we should take lessons on the NHS, but
I will not take any lessons from the party
that presided over the failure that happened
at Mid Staffs hospital. Labour says we should
learn lessons. I will tell the House who should
learn lessons: the Labour party, which still
fails to recognise that if you are going to
fund the NHS—we are putting money in, and
there are more doctors, more operations and
more nurses—you need a strong economy. We
now know, however, that Labour has a different
sort of phrase for its approach to these things.
Remember when it used to talk about “boom
and bust”? Now it is borrow and bankrupt.
[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. We must get through Back
Benchers’ questions and the Prime Minister’s
answers to them. I call Mr Michael Tomlinson.
>>Michael Tomlinson (Mid Dorset and North
Poole) (Con): Brendan Cox will meet today
with the Duchess of Cornwall to launch plans
to bring communities together over the weekend
of 17 and 18 June to mark the first anniversary
of our colleague Jo’s death. The aim of
this Great Get Together, as it has been called,
is for more than 10 million people across
the country to come together as communities
and neighbours for events such as street parties,
picnics and even bake offs. Will the Prime
Minister join me in agreeing that such events
and moments of national reflection and celebration
in our communities will be a fitting tribute
to Jo and will remind us all that, as she
herself said, we have far more things in common
than things that divide us?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an extremely important point, and I am very
happy to agree that what is becoming known
as the Great Get Together is a fitting and
important tribute to our late colleague Jo
Cox. I commend her husband, Brendan—I am
sure that everyone across the House would
wish to do so—for the work that he has done.
As my hon. Friend said, it is important to
remember that there is more that brings us
together than divides us, and this is an important
moment of national reflection and celebration
of the strength of our communities. As we
face the future together—these are momentous
times for this country—it is important that
we remember that being united makes us strong
and recognise the things that unite us, as
a country and a people, and the bonds we share
together. This is a very fitting tribute to
our late colleague.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): In recent
days, the Prime Minister has said that it
is a key personal commitment to transform
the way domestic violence is tackled. It is
hugely welcome that she has called for ideas
about how the treatment of victims could be
improved and more convictions against abusers
secured. Combatting violence against women
and preventing domestic violence is the aim
of the Istanbul convention, which the UK is
yet to ratify. Does she agree with Members
on both sides of the House that the convention
should be ratified as a priority?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
raises an important subject. As he says, I
take it particularly seriously—I worked
hard on it as Home Secretary and I continue
to do so as Prime Minister. There were still
an estimated 1.3 million female victims of
domestic abuse in the last year and more than
400,000 victims of sexual violence. He is
right that we signed up to the Istanbul convention,
and we are fully committed to ratifying it,
which was why we supported in principle the
private Member’s Bill of the hon. Member
for Banff and Buchan (Dr Whiteford) on Second
Reading and in Committee. In many ways, the
measures we have in place actually go further
than the convention, but I am clear that we
need to maintain momentum, which is why I
am setting up a ministerial working group
to look at the legislation and at how we can
provide good support to victims, and to consider
the possibility of a domestic violence Act.
>>Angus Robertson: This Friday, the House
will consider a Bill on the Istanbul convention.
We know that Ministers have been working hard
with my hon. Friend the Member for Banff and
Buchan (Dr Whiteford), who has cross-party
support for her Bill. Given the importance
of this issue and the Prime Minister’s personal
commitment, which she has outlined again today,
will she join me in encouraging Members to
support the Bill and discourage any attempts
to use parliamentary wrecking tactics to stop
it?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to join the
right hon. Gentleman in that. I know that
the Minister for Vulnerability, my hon. Friend
the Member for Truro and Falmouth (Sarah Newton),
has had a number of constructive discussions
with the hon. Member for Banff and Buchan.
The Government have tabled some mutually agreed
amendments, for which the Government will
vote this Friday. I hope that all my hon.
Friends who are present on Friday will support
these measures. This is an important Bill.
The Government have supported it, and I hope
it will be supported on both sides of the
House.
>>William Wragg (Hazel Grove) (Con): Residents
in the village of High Lane in my constituency
are concerned about the 4,000 homes proposed
under the Greater Manchester spatial framework,
which will more than double the size of the
village. What assurances can my right hon.
Friend give to my constituents that the green
belt is safe with this Government?
>>The Prime Minister: I am happy to give that
commitment to my hon. Friend. The Government
are very clear that the green belt must be
protected. We are very clear that boundaries
should be altered only when local authorities
have fully examined all other reasonable options.
If they do go down that route, they should
compensate by improving the quality or accessibility
of the remaining green-belt land so that it
can be enjoyed. I know about the particular
issue that my hon. Friend raises, and I believe
that the Greater Manchester spatial framework
led to quite a number of responses. There
was a lot of interest in that consultation,
which closed last month, and I am sure that
all those views will be taken into account.
>>Caroline Flint (Don Valley) (Lab): Last
week, the all-party group on children of alcoholics
launched a manifesto for change. Some 2.5
million children are growing up in the home
of a problem drinker—I did, too. These children
are twice as likely as others to have problems
at school, three times more likely to consider
suicide, and four times more likely to become
an alcoholic, yet today 138 local authorities
have no plan to support these children. Will
the Prime Minister work with the all-party
group to establish the first ever Government
strategy to tackle this hidden problem that
blights the lives of millions?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Lady
raises an important issue. I know that she
recently spoke very movingly about her own
experience. I am sure that Members on both
sides of the House recognise the devastating
impact that addiction can have on individuals
and their families, so this is an important
issue for her to raise. It is unacceptable
that children bear the brunt of their parents’
condition. The Government are committed to
working with MPs, health professionals and
those affected to reduce the harm of addiction
and to get people the support they need. We
shall look carefully at the proposals suggested
by the right hon. Lady.
>>Dr Julian Lewis (New Forest East) (Con):
If she will take steps to introduce legislative
proposals to provide legal protection to former
military personnel who served in Northern
Ireland at least equivalent to that offered
to former republican and loyalist paramilitaries.
>>The Prime Minister: As I have made clear,
I think it is absolutely appalling when people
try to make a business out of dragging our
brave troops through the courts. In the case
of Northern Ireland, 90% of deaths were caused
by terrorists, and it is essential that the
justice system reflects that. It would be
entirely wrong to treat terrorists more favourably
than soldiers or police officers. That is
why, as part of our work to bring forward
the Stormont House agreement Bill, we will
ensure that investigative bodies are under
a legal duty to be fair, balanced and proportionate
so that our veterans are not unfairly treated
or disproportionately investigated.
>>Dr Lewis: While I welcome that reply, it
does not go quite as far as I and many other
people would like. There is no prospect of
new credible evidence coming forward against
our veterans of the troubles up to 40 years
after the event, yet people are starting to
use the same techniques in Northern Ireland
against them as were used against veterans
of Iraq. Surely the answer has to be a statute
of limitations preventing the prosecution
of veterans to do with matters that occurred
prior to the date of the Belfast agreement.
>>The Prime Minister: As my right hon. Friend
knows, we are looking at this issue as part
of the Stormont House agreement. What we are
doing is ensuring that the investigative bodies
responsible for looking at deaths during the
troubles will operate in a fair, balanced
and proportionate manner. We want cases to
be considered in chronological order, and
we want these protections enshrined in legislation.
We are going to consult fully on these proposals,
because we want to make sure that we get this
right.
>>Gerald Jones (Merthyr Tydfil and Rhymney)
(Lab): When the new local housing allowance
cap for social tenants is introduced in 2019,
it will hit people on low incomes in my constituency
hard. In places such as Maidenhead, the allowance
will often exceed the average rent, but the
basic weekly allowance in Merthyr Tydfil is
£67, while the rent charged by Merthyr Valleys
Homes is £76, which is already one of the
lowest social housing rents in Wales. That
will mean that tenants, including many older
people, will be expected to find nearly £500
a year to put towards their rent. Will the
Prime Minister act now? Will she issue clear
guidance to exempt older people, at the very
least, from these crude cuts, and also to
ensure that the local housing allowance is
in line with local rents?
>>The Prime Minister: Local authorities have
a fund and can exercise discretion. There
will be some variation across the country,
and steps have been taken to ensure that particularly
vulnerable people are not affected in the
way that the hon. Gentleman suggests.
>>Dr Tania Mathias (Twickenham) (Con): The
lack of large-scale vaccine manufacturing
has been described as a national security
issue for our country, and it will take many
years to build that up. Will the Prime Minister
look into what more the Government can do
to address this highly critical health and
defence concern?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend is absolutely
right to raise the issue in that context.
The Government take it very seriously. The
ability to ensure that we can readily scale
up vaccine production in the event of a pandemic
is, as she says, vital to our national security.
As I am sure she will understand, the precise
details are necessarily confidential, but
I can assure her that we have provisions in
place to ensure that urgently needed vaccines
are available in the UK at short notice, including
in the event of a pandemic. As an added contingency,
we are funding a £10 million competition
to establish a world-leading centre for vaccine
manufacturing. However, that is only part
of the picture, because we are in a strong
position: we have one of the most comprehensive
and successful vaccination programmes in the
world, backed up by £300 million in this
year alone.
>>Kerry McCarthy (Bristol East) (Lab): Last
night Bristol City Council set its budget.
Very difficult decisions were made more difficult
by the abject failure of the previous Mayor
to get a grip on the council’s finances.
It has taken a Labour Mayor to face up to
the challenge, but Government cuts are making
his task almost impossible, and devolution
simply means asking us to do more with less.
We did our bit last night in setting the budget;
will the Prime Minister now meet the Mayor
of Bristol to discuss the fairer funding deal
that the people of Bristol deserve?
>>The Prime Minister: I understand that my
right hon. Friend the Communities Secretary
has indeed had such a meeting to discuss the
issue that the hon. Lady has raised.
>>Chris Davies (Brecon and Radnorshire) (Con):
Seventeen years ago, my constituents Sue and
Glyn Jones received a phone call that no parent
should ever have to take. The caller told
them that their daughter Kirsty, who was backpacking
in Thailand, had been brutally murdered. The
Thai authorities are due to close their investigation
of Kirsty’s murder soon but, as yet, her
case remains unsolved, her killer remains
free, and her parents have neither justice
nor closure. May I ask my right hon. Friend
to press the Thai authorities to use recently
improved DNA techniques to bring the killer
to justice, to endeavour to provide more support
for families who have lost loved ones abroad
and, finally, to ensure that Kirsty’s personal
effects are, at last, returned home to her
parents from Thailand?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure that the whole
House will join me in offering condolences
to the Jones family and in recognising the
terrible trauma that they have been through
as a result of the killing of their daughter.
As I am sure that my hon. Friend appreciates,
it is not for the British Government to interfere
with police investigations that take place
in another country, but I understand that
the Foreign Office has been providing support
and remains ready to do so. Our embassy in
Bangkok will continue to raise these issues
with the Thai Government, and I am sure that
the Foreign Office will keep my hon. Friend
updated on any developments.
>>Phil Wilson (Sedgefield) (Lab): In the Prime
Minister’s Lancaster House speech, she said
of a future trade agreement with the EU:“no
deal for Britain is better than a bad deal
for Britain.”In the spirit of consistency,
will that rule also apply to any future trade
negotiations with the United States of America,
where President Trump has said that America
comes first?
>>The Prime Minister: I assure the hon. Gentleman
that, as I have said consistently, we will
be ensuring that when we negotiate trade deals
with whichever countries around the world,
they will be good deals for the UK.
>>Crispin Blunt (Reigate) (Con): In the Marriage
(Same Sex Couples) Act 2013, we took the power,
subject to a consultation and the laying of
an order, to give humanists in England and
Wales the opportunity to celebrate marriages
as they do in Scotland. We have had the consultation,
with 90% approval, and there has even now
been reference to the Law Commission, which
has concluded. Will my right hon. Friend now
give her attention to laying this order and
giving humanists in England and Wales the
same rights and freedoms as they enjoy very
successfully in Scotland?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend has been
following this issue closely over recent years.
I think he recognises that this is an important
and complex area of law, and we want to make
sure that proposals are considered properly.
That is why the Ministry of Justice is carefully
examining the differences in treatment that
already exist within marriage law, alongside
the humanist proposals, so that the differences
can be minimised. I am sure that my hon. Friend
will agree that it is both right and fair
to approach this in that way.
>>Nic Dakin (Scunthorpe) (Lab): My constituent
Kevin’s chances of survival from pancreatic
cancer were no better than his mother’s,
who died of that disease 40 years earlier.
This disease is soon to become the fourth
biggest cancer killer in the UK. Will the
Prime Minister join MPs on both sides of this
House to champion a significant increase in
spending on pancreatic cancer research which,
sadly, currently lags behind that on other
cancers?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
a very important point that is obviously of
particular relevance in the case of the constituent
to whom he refers. As he says, pancreatic
cancer is one of those cancers that it is
very difficult to deal with and treat. There
has been a lot of attention over the years
on certain cancers, such as breast cancer
increasingly, as well as bowel cancer and
prostate cancer, but it is important that
the appropriate attention is given to cancers
that are proving more difficult to deal with,
such as pancreatic cancer.
>>Neil Parish (Tiverton and Honiton) (Con):
In February 2008, Mr Barry Pring, the brother
of one of my constituents, was unlawfully
killed in Ukraine. Mr Pring’s Ukrainian
wife is clearly implicated in his death. Earlier
this year, our coroner in Devon ruled that
Mr Pring was tricked into standing on a carriageway
before being run down by a car that had stolen
licence plates and no lights—death was immediate.
However, every time an investigating officer
makes progress with the case in Ukraine, they
are replaced. This has happened 10 times and
the case has stalled. May I implore my right
hon. Friend to raise this case with the Ukrainian
Prime Minister so that we can get justice
and closure for Barry’s mother and brother
and the Pring family?
>>The Prime Minister: I am sure that the whole
House will join me in offering condolences
to Barry’s family following his death in
2008. I understand that my hon. Friend has
discussed this case with my right hon. Friend
the Foreign Secretary. As I said in reply
to an earlier question, it is not for the
British Government to interfere in the legal
processes of another country, but the Foreign
Office has been regularly raising this case
with the Ukrainian authorities and will continue
to do so. It is my understanding that UK police
have assisted the investigation on a number
of occasions and all information from the
UK coroner’s inquest will be passed on.
I am sure that the Foreign Office will keep
my hon. Friend updated on any developments.
>>Gavin Newlands (Paisley and Renfrewshire
North) (SNP): Tens of thousands of disabled
people on the Motability scheme have had their
cars removed by this Government. In November,
the Minister for Disabled People, Health and
Work said that they will be looking at allowing
personal independence payment claimants to
keep their cars pending appeal. Next week,
my constituent Margaret Gibson will lose her
car, which she regards as a lifeline, despite
a pending appeal and two decades of receiving
higher rate disability living allowance. Will
the Prime Minister update the House on the
progress of this review to help Margaret and
thousands like her?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
an issue about the way in which these assessments
are made and the implications of the decisions
taken. He referred, I think, to a review in
relation to PIP payments and the Motability
element of that. If I may, I will write to
him with further details.
>>Derek Thomas (St Ives) (Con): It was a year
ago this week that the Edward Hain community
hospital was temporarily closed due to fire
safety concerns. There are now no community
beds in the towns of St Ives, Penzance and
St Just, or in the rural areas in between.
GPs, residents and local campaigners agree
with me that this valued community hospital
needs to be reopened as an urgent priority.
Will my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister
apply pressure to NHS Property Services and
to Cornwall’s NHS managers to find a way
of getting that building work done and reopening
those community beds?
>>The Prime Minister: This is obviously a
concern for my hon. Friend’s constituents—he
is right to raise it. I am sure that he recognises
that the first priority must be to ensure
that patients are treated in a safe and secure
environment, and I understand that the local
clinical commissioning group and the NHS have
been working closely to ensure that community
hospital facilities in Cornwall are fit to
deliver that expectation. I think that a review
has already been undertaken into the repairs
and improvements needed to bring the Edward
Hain community hospital up to a safe standard,
and the CCG will be looking at the infrastructure
and facilities that it needs, once a final
local plan has been agreed. Obviously my right
hon. Friend the Health Secretary has heard
my hon. Friend’s representations.
>>Caroline Lucas (Brighton, Pavilion) (Green):
The Government’s business rates hike could
devastate the local economy in my constituency.
Brighton pier is facing a 17% increase, the
World’s End pub a 123% increase, and Blanch
House hotel a 400% increase. Does the Prime
Minister recognise that Brighton will be disproportionately
affected? Will she urgently set up a discretionary
fund to support small and micro-businesses,
and agree to a full review of the whole system?
>>The Prime Minister: If we just stand back,
we can see that business rates are based on
the rental values of properties. Those values
change over time—they can go up and down—and
it is right that business rates change to
recognise that. That is the principle of fairness
that underpins the business rates system.
However, we also want to support businesses
and we recognise that, for some, business
rates will go up when the revaluations take
place. That is why we have put significant
funding in place for transitional relief.
I recognise that there has been particular
concern that some small businesses will be
adversely affected as the result of this revaluation,
and that is why I have asked the Chancellor
and the Communities Secretary to ensure that
there is appropriate relief in those hardest
cases.
>>Sir Julian Brazier (Canterbury) (Con): My
right hon. Friend gave a sympathetic answer
to my right hon. Friend the Member for New
Forest East (Dr Lewis) and I know that she
has taken particular interest in the matter
that he raised. May I put it to her that,
for many of us, there is something profoundly
wrong with a criminal justice system that
can pursue veterans who have risked their
lives for this country 40 years on, long after
there is any possibility of new evidence,
while it is at the same time capable of paying
out £1 million to a terror suspect?
>>The Prime Minister: In relation to the issue
in Northern Ireland, the legacy bodies were
part of the Stormont House agreement and we
are working to deliver on that agreement.
As I said in reply to my right hon. Friend
the Member for New Forest East (Dr Lewis),
the overwhelming majority of our armed forces
in Northern Ireland served with great distinction
and we owe them a huge debt of gratitude.
The situation at the moment is that cases
are being pursued against officers who served
in Northern Ireland, and we want to see the
legacy body set up under the Stormont House
agreement taking a proportionate, fair and
balanced approach. As I said earlier, we recognise
that the majority of individuals who suffered
did so at the hands of terrorists.
>>Andy Burnham (Leigh) (Lab): On the steps
of Downing Street, the Prime Minister pledged
to end the “burning injustice” of so few
working-class boys going to university. Will
she tell me how cutting every single secondary
school in Leigh, Wigan, Rochdale, Trafford
and Manchester through her new schools funding
formula will do anything other than make that
injustice even worse?
>>The Prime Minister: I want to ensure, through
the education system that we provide, that
there is a good school place for every child.
I am pleased to say that under Conservatives
in government, we have seen 1.8 million more
children in good or outstanding schools. We
are looking at the funding formula for schools
and listening to the comments that have been
made, but everyone across the House will recognise
that it has been said for some time now that
the existing formula is not transparent or
fair. We are looking at a new formula, but
I can assure the right hon. Gentleman that
our education policy is about ensuring that
every child has the opportunity to go as far
as their talents and their hard work enable
them to go.
>>Paul Scully (Sutton and Cheam) (Con): Mr
Speaker, you saw at first hand what a cup
run means to a town and a club such as Sutton.
With AFC Wimbledon out of the picture, I wonder
whether my right hon. Friend will join me
in congratulating Sutton United on such a
spirited performance on Monday, and in wishing
Lincoln City well for keeping the non-league
spirit alive in the next round of the FA cup.
Finally—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. The hon. Gentleman must
be heard.
>>Paul Scully: Finally, will my right hon.
Friend join me in congratulating and thanking
Arsenal for their generosity in allowing Sutton
to keep a little extra slice of the FA cup
pie?
>>The Prime Minister: If I may say so, that
was a neat reference to pie at the end of
the question. I am happy to congratulate Sutton
on their extremely good run in the FA cup.
It makes a huge difference to a local area
when its football club is able to progress
to that extent, to be up there with the big
boys, and to do as well as Sutton did. I am
also happy to congratulate Lincoln City—I
see that my hon. Friend the Member for Lincoln
is sitting next to my hon. Friend the Member
for Sutton and Cheam (Paul Scully)—on their
success. We wish them well for the future.
>>Mr Speaker: Finally, I call Michelle Thomson.
>>Michelle Thomson (Edinburgh West) (Ind):
The UK Green Investment Bank, which is co-located
in Edinburgh, is being sold, and recent newspaper
reports suggest that the contract could be
concluded soon. That is happening despite
the UK’s stated focus on research and development,
and the fact that no realistic guarantees
have yet been given as to the continuation
of a proper headquarters and board based in
Edinburgh. Will the Prime Minister commit
to looking again at why a sale at this time
is not in the best interests of Edinburgh,
the green agenda or UK taxpayers?
>>The Prime Minister: Before I respond to
the hon. Lady’s question, I am afraid that
I owe a couple of apologies. I am sorry for
mixing up my hon. Friends the Members for
Stroud (Neil Carmichael) and for Lincoln (Karl
MᶜCartney). I was obviously getting carried
away with the football fever that my hon.
Friend the Member for Sutton and Cheam introduced
into the Chamber.
The hon. Member for Edinburgh West (Michelle
Thomson) mentioned the Green Investment Bank.
If I may, I will write to her with a response
to her question.
>>Mr Speaker: I think it is fair to say that
in dealing with the matter the Prime Minister
has deployed a very straight bat.