>> Huw Merriman (Bexhill and Battle) (Con):
If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 15 March.
>> The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May):
I am sure that Members will want to join me
in wishing people across the UK and around
the world a happy St Patrick’s day this
coming Friday. This morning, I had meetings
with ministerial colleagues and others. In
addition to my duties in this House, I shall
have further such meetings later today.
>> Huw Merriman:
With my Irish blood, may I also wish people
a happy St Patrick’s day?
I welcome the Government’s announcement
that we will abide by the letter of our manifesto
and also the spirit. Does the Prime Minister
agree that, as we move towards balancing the
books, we must ensure that we have a fair
and sustainable tax system?
>> The Prime Minister:
I thank my hon. Friend for his question. We
made a commitment not to raise tax, and we
put our commitment into the tax lock. The
measures that we put forward in the Budget
last week were consistent with those locks.
As a number of my parliamentary colleagues
have been pointing out in recent days—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. This is intolerable. [Interruption.]
I take no view on the matter, but I do take
a view on the importance of hearing the questions
and the answers.
>> The Prime Minister:
As a number of my parliamentary colleagues
have been pointing out in recent days, the
trend towards greater self-employment does
create a structural issue in the tax base
on which we will have to act. We want to ensure
that we maintain, as they have said, fairness
in the tax system. We will await the report
from Matthew Taylor on the future of employment;
consider the Government’s overall approach
to employment status and rights to tax and
entitlements; and bring forward further proposals,
but we will not bring forward increases to
national insurance contributions later in
this Parliament.
>> Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab):
First, may I wish everyone in my constituency,
in Ireland and all around the world a very
happy St Patrick’s day on the 17th?
We have just heard that the Prime Minister
is about to drop the national insurance hike
announced only a week ago. It seems to me
that the Government are in a bit of chaos
here with a Budget that unravels in seven
days, a Conservative manifesto with a pensive
Prime Minister on the front page saying that
there would be no increase, and a week ago
an increase being announced. If they are to
drop the increase, as they are indicating,
the Prime Minister should thank the Federation
of Small Businesses and all those who have
pointed out both how unfair the increase would
be and how big business evades an awful lot
of national insurance through bogus self-employment.
>> The Prime Minister:
I do not think the right hon. Gentleman listened
to the answer I gave to my hon. Friend the
Member for Bexhill and Battle (Huw Merriman).
I normally stand at this Dispatch Box and
say I will not take any lectures from the
right hon. Gentleman, but when it comes to
lectures on chaos he would be the first person
I turned to.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
I think the Prime Minister should offer an
apology for the chaos that her Government
have caused during the past week and the stress
they have caused to the 4.8 million self-employed
people in this country. Will she offer that
apology? Her hon. Friend the Under-Secretary
of State for Wales did so a week ago; it is
time she joined him. This measure, if carried
through, will create a black hole in the budget.
What is she going to do to fill that black
hole?
>> The Prime Minister:
If the right hon. Gentleman is so concerned
about balancing the books, why is it Labour
party policy to borrow half a trillion pounds
and bankrupt Britain?
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Given that this Government propose to borrow
more between now and 2020 than the entire
borrowing of all Labour Governments put together,
we do not need lectures from them on that.
I hope that in his statement later today the
Chancellor will address the question of injustice
to many people who are forced into bogus self-employment
by unscrupulous companies, many of which force
their workers to become self-employed and
thereby avoid employer’s national insurance
contributions. It is a grossly unfair system
where those in self-employment pay some national
insurance, but employers do not, and benefit
from it. That is a gross injustice that must
be addressed.
>> The Prime Minister:
The right hon. Gentleman obviously has not
noticed that one of the first things I did
when I became Prime Minister was commission
Matthew Taylor of the RSA to conduct a review
of the employment market and employment rights
and status, precisely because we recognised
that the employment market is changing. He
talks about the self-employed, so let us look
at what we have done for the self-employed.
Our increase in the personal allowance means
that they now keep more of their earnings.
They will have access to both tax-free childcare
and 30 hours of free childcare a week, just
like employees, and now they have access to
the new state pension, worth over £1,800
more a year. What we know is that the Labour
party’s policies would bankrupt Britain
and put firms out of business and people out
of jobs.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
We have a Government U-turn, no apology, and
a Budget that falls most heavily on those
with the least broad shoulders, with cuts
to schools, cuts to social care and cuts to
support for people with disabilities. That
is the agenda of the right hon. Lady’s Government,
and everybody knows it.
>> The Prime Minister:
I do not think the right hon. Gentleman has
got the hang of this. He is supposed to ask
me a question when he stands up—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. Let us hear the answer.
>> The Prime Minister:
The right hon. Gentleman talks about schools.
What have we done? We have protected the core
schools budget and introduced the pupil premium.
This Budget delivers money for more than 100
new schools, ensuring good school places for
every child. This Budget delivers on skills
for young people; we want them to be equipped
for the jobs of the future. The Budget delivers
£500 million for technical education. We
also recognise the pressure on social care.
This Budget delivers £2 billion more funding
for social care—funding that would not be
available with Labour’s economic policies.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
It would be a very good idea if the Prime
Minister listened to headteachers all over
the country, who are desperately trying to
work out how to balance the books in their
schools, but are losing teachers, losing teaching
assistants and losing support for their children
because school budgets are being cut. She
knows that. We all know that. Everybody out
there knows that. They also know that, according
to figures from the Institute for Fiscal Studies,
average working families will be £1,400 worse
off as a result of her Budget that was produced
last week. What is she doing to help the worst
off and poorest in our society, rather than
continuing to cut local government and schools
expenditure, and to underfund social care?
>> The Prime Minister:
I will tell the right hon. Gentleman what
we have delivered for the low paid. We have
frozen VAT and fuel duty, and every basic
rate taxpayer has had a tax cut worth £1,000.
We have taken more than 3 million people out
of paying income tax altogether. That is what
we have done for the low paid. On schools,
1.8 million more children are now in good
or outstanding schools. I want a good school
place for every child. We have done it with
free schools and academies, and with our changes
to education—all opposed by the Labour party.
Now it wants to oppose our giving every child
a good school place. What do we know about
the Labour party’s policies? Well, the former
shadow Chancellor, the hon. Member for Nottingham
East (Chris Leslie) said that Labour’s policies
would mean doubling national insurance, doubling
VAT and doubling council tax. That would not
help the low paid or ordinary working families.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
The difference is that we want a good school
and a good place for every child in every
school in every community. Selective education—the
reintroduction of grammar schools—does not
achieve that. We want a staircase for all,
not a ladder for the few, which is what Conservative
policies actually are. The Prime Minister
has also not addressed the unfairness of a
Budget that cuts tax at the top end, continues
to reduce corporation tax and encourages bogus
self-employment. She has to address the issues
of injustice and inequality in our society,
and of a Government who are dedicated to widening
the gap, not helping the hard-up or those
who are working as self-employed, trying to
make ends meet and not getting access to any
benefits at the same time.
>> The Prime Minister:
Inequality has gone down under this Government.
The Budget shows that the top 1% of earners
will actually contribute 27% in terms of the
income that they are providing. Let me address
the issue of schools. The problem with what
the right hon. Gentleman says is that the
Labour party has opposed, and continues to
oppose, every single education policy brought
forward by this Government, delivering more
good school places for children. The Labour
party’s approach is that parents shall take
what they are given, good or bad. We believe
in listening to parents.
Let us look ahead to what the right hon. Gentleman’s
policies would produce for this country: half
a trillion pounds of borrowing—£500 billion
more borrowing under the Labour party—more
taxes, more spending and more borrowing. It
would be a bankrupt Britain that would not
give money for public services or help ordinary
working families. It is the Conservative party
that is helping ordinary working families.
It is the Labour party that is failing to
address the needs of the people of this country.
We are delivering. He is just sitting there
or going on protest marches.
>> Jeremy Quin (Horsham) (Con):
As the facts change, I change my question.
May I congratulate my right hon. Friend on
proposing the most radical reform of
technical education in a generation and delivering
fair funding for all our schools? However,
may I ask her, as part of the consultation,
to ensure a minimum level of appropriate funding
for all schools?
>> The Prime Minister:
I thank my hon. Friend, because he has raised
an important point. One of the issues we have
addressed in the Budget is putting more money
into skills training—into further education
and technical education—for young people.
I think that one of the most important things
we can do is equip young people for their
futures, and for the jobs of the future, so
that they can get on in life. We are investing
an extra half a billion pounds a year, as
I said earlier, in England’s technical education
system to do this.
My hon. Friend referred to the issue of a
minimum funding level. My right hon. Friend
the Education Secretary confirmed last month
that the Department for Education has heard
representations on this issue. It is considering
these issues, but the funding formula is a
complex issue that has needed addressing for
some time, and we will be looking at it carefully.
>> Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP):
We once had a Prime Minister who said,
“The lady’s not for turning.”
My goodness, is it not welcome that the Prime
Minister has today admitted that she is for
turning, with her screeching, embarrassing
U-turn on national insurance contributions?
Only days remain until the Prime Minister
is going to invoke article 50 on leaving the
European Union. Last July, she promised to
secure a UK-wide approach—an agreement between
the devolved Administrations of Scotland,
Wales and Northern Ireland and the UK Government—before
triggering article 50, so when will the Prime
Minister announce the details of the agreement?
>> The Prime Minister:
As I said to the right hon. Gentleman yesterday,
and to others asking me questions on the timetable
yesterday, we will trigger article 50 by the
end of March. There will be an opportunity
for further discussions with the devolved
Administrations over that period. On the issue
of membership of the European Union, and his
view on Scotland not being a member of the
United Kingdom, I say this to him: he is comparing
membership of an organisation that we have
been a member of for 40 years with our country.
We have been one country for over 300 years;
we have fought together, we have worked together,
we have achieved together, and constitutional
game-playing must not be allowed to break
the deep bonds of our shared history and our
future together.
>> Angus Robertson:
The Prime Minister can wag her finger as much
as she likes; last year, she made a promise:
she promised an agreement. I asked her about
it yesterday; she did not answer. I have asked
her about it now; she has not answered. When
will she reach an agreement—not discussions—with
the Scottish Government before triggering
article 50? She has another opportunity. [Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. I recognise the passions—[Interruption.]
Mr Wishart, calm yourself, man. I am perfectly
capable of doing this without your beneficent
assistance. The right hon. Member for Moray
(Angus Robertson) will be heard, however long
it takes. [Interruption.] Yes, he will; he
will continue, however long it takes. Carry
on, Mr Robertson.
>> Angus Robertson:
The Prime Minister promised an agreement;
there is not an agreement. When will there
be an agreement? Does she not understand that
if she does not secure an agreement before
triggering article 50—if she is not prepared
to negotiate on behalf of the Scottish Government
and secure membership of the single European
market—people in Scotland will have a referendum,
and we will have our say?
>> The Prime Minister:
We have been in discussions with the Scottish
Government and with the other devolved Administrations
about the interests that they have as we prepare,
as the United Kingdom Government, to negotiate
a deal on behalf of the whole of the United
Kingdom—a deal that will be a good deal
for not just England, Wales and Northern Ireland,
but the people of Scotland as well. As we
go forward in negotiating that deal, I think
the right hon. Gentleman should remember this:
Scotland will be leaving the European Union,
either as a member of the United Kingdom or
if it were independent, as it is very clear
from the Barroso document that it would not
be a member of the European Union. What we
need now is to unite, come together as a country,
and ensure that we can get the best deal for
the whole of the United Kingdom.
>> Mr Andrew Turner (Isle of Wight) (Con):
This Government are working with local enterprise
partnerships, councils and other partners
to grow the economy, but despite being in
the prosperous south-east, the Isle of Wight
is 339th out of 379 in the UK competitiveness
index. Will my right hon. Friend ensure that
more growth funding is targeted at rural areas
such as the island, with its many small and
microbusinesses, to deliver a country that
works for all?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend speaks well on behalf of his
constituents, and he is right to do that.
I know that he has consistently put forward
the unique characteristics of the Isle of
Wight. We have already been able to support
the island’s economy through the local growth
deal for the Solent—that is £183 million—and
the Solent local enterprise partnership has
been supporting the Isle of Wight rural small
and medium-sized enterprise programme; my
hon. Friend particularly referred to rural
funding. I want to make sure that we make
the best of the diverse strengths of all Britain’s
cities, regions and islands. I am sure that
on the island, the business community and
the council will work together to create the
best possible conditions for growth and competitiveness
in the future.
>> Stephen Doughty (Cardiff South and Penarth)
(Lab/Co-op):
Our two single markets are the backbone of
our economy, yet the Prime Minister wants
to rip us away from one, and the Scottish
National party wants to break up the other.
Is the risky and reckless approach she is
taking to Brexit really a price worth paying
to foster the break-up of Britain?
>> The Prime Minister:
The hon. Gentleman is wrong when he says that
I want to rip the United Kingdom away from
the single market. What we want to do—[Interruption.]
I am sorry to say to hon. Members on the Labour
Benches that this is the same answer that
I have given consistently in this House. We
want to ensure that we get a good free trade
agreement that gives us the maximum possible
access to the single market, to enable us
to trade with the single market and operate
within the single market.
>> Mrs Theresa Villiers (Chipping Barnet)
(Con):
I welcome the support on business rates being
given by the Budget to local high streets,
which are so crucially valued in places such
as my constituency of Barnet. Does the Prime
Minister agree that we can give more help
to small businesses if we secure the international
agreement we need to ensure that all big businesses
pay their taxes?
>> The Prime Minister
This is a very important issue, and one on
which I think this Government have a record
of which we can be proud, but of course there
is more to do. Since 2010, through the work
we have done on tackling tax evasion, avoidance
and non-compliance, we have secured an additional
£140 billion in compliance yield. Internationally,
we have driven the global agenda. We have
now got 100 countries signed up to the automatic
exchange of financial account information,
and we have pushed G7 and G20 partners to
establish registers of beneficial ownership,
but my right hon. Friend is right: there is
more to do. We will continue to crack down
on big companies not paying their tax. I want
to see an economy that works for everyone,
and that means that big companies should be
paying their tax as well as everybody else.
>> Mike Weir (Angus) (SNP):
In answer to my right hon. Friend the Member
for Moray (Angus Robertson), the Prime Minister
called for respect, but that is a two-way
street. Where is her Government’s respect
for the Scottish Government’s compromise
proposal, which has just been ignored in these
negotiations?
>> The Prime Minister:
The compromise proposal has not been ignored;
it has been discussed by Ministers with Ministers
from the Scottish Government. There are many
areas within that proposal on which we agree,
as I have said before, such as on ensuring
our security from crime and terrorism, and
maintaining and protecting workers’ rights.
>> Will Quince (Colchester) (Con):
Colchester hospital’s A and E department
has excellent staff, but suffers from poor
layout and patient flow. Does the Prime Minister
agree with me that the £100 million set out
for triage in the Budget last week will enable
hospitals such as mine to address this issue
and improve patient outcomes?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is right to recognise, and
we should all recognise, the hard work and
dedication of our excellent staff throughout
the NHS. What we are seeing in the NHS is
that A and Es are treating more people than
ever before. We are spending half a trillion
pounds on the NHS in England during this Parliament,
and the NHS is going to see an increase in
its funding of £10 billion in real terms,
but there is sometimes an issue, as my hon.
Friend says, about the configuration of A
and E and enabling changes to take place to
help the flow, and to help in dealing with
potential patients as they come in. That is
why my right hon. Friend the Chancellor announced
last week £425 million in new capital investment
in the NHS, which includes £100 million to
help manage the demand on A&amp;E services,
enabling hospitals to make changes to ensure
people are treated in the most appropriate
way possible.
>> Nick Thomas-Symonds (Torfaen) (Lab):
Over 200 staff at the Cwmbran pension centre
in my constituency face an uncertain future,
as they have been told they have to relocate
to other areas over the next few years. Does
the Prime Minister realise the impact this
has on staff and the local economy, and will
she meet me and representatives of the workforce
to see what can be done to save Cwmbran pension
centre?
>> The Prime Minister:
I recognise the concern that the hon. Gentleman
has raised for staff at that particular pension
office in—
>> Nick Thomas-Symonds:
Cwmbran.
>> The Prime Minister:
Cwmbran. I recognise this is an issue. I am
sure it is an issue that the Secretary of
State for Work and Pensions will look at very
closely, but of course the Government are
looking to ensure that we both use our resources
effectively, but also provide the proper and
appropriate service for the recipients of
those particular benefits.
>> Victoria Atkins (Louth and Horncastle)
(Con):
Last weekend, thousands of people from across
Lincolnshire came to the Revesby races in
my constituency to enjoy the racing and the
delicious local food, including award-winning
Lincolnshire sausages. As the Government prepare
to strike new international trade deals, will
my right hon. Friend ensure that the high
standards we expect of our food producers
and farmers will be met and maintained in
these deals, and will this Government continue
to back British farming?
>> The Prime Minister:
I can assure my hon. Friend that we will certainly
do that. I remember, when I visited her prior
to the general election in 2015, sampling
some of the excellent Lincolnshire sausages
that come from her constituency. We have an
opportunity to build a new future for our
food and farming industry when we leave the
European Union. We will maintain the UK’s
high standards of food safety and of animal
welfare; that will be a priority for us. Any
trade deals we enter into will need to be
right for consumers, for businesses and for
farmers, and will need to ensure our food
safety and environmental protection, and of
course the animal welfare standards I have
just referred to. We recognise the need for
certainty for businesses. We have already
provided guarantees on support for farmers
up to 2020, and I can assure her that we will
continue to back British farmers.
>> Callum McCaig (Aberdeen South) (SNP):
The UK has one of the worst performing currencies
in the world, and it has a trade deficit of
£133 billion and a national debt approaching
£1.7 trillion. May I ask the Prime Minister:
does she really believe that the UK could
afford to be an independent country?
>> The Prime Minister:
If he wants—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. There is too much noise in the Chamber.
Hon. Members on the SNP Benches are very over-excited
individuals. I want to hear the Prime Minister’s
reply. Let us hear the reply.
>> The Prime Minister:
If the hon. Member for Aberdeen South (Callum
McCaig) wants to talk about figures in relation
to the UK economy, it is the world’s sixth
largest economy, and this Government have
reduced the deficit by two thirds. If he would
care to look at the employment figures we
see today, employment is at a record high
and unemployment has not been lower since
1975.
>> Tim Loughton (East Worthing and Shoreham)
(Con):
Today is the Ides of March—and, yet again,
Brutus opposite missed badly—so will the
Prime Minister take the opportunity to stick
the knife into the ridiculous Court of Justice
of the European Union, which ruled yesterday
that employers can ban their staff from wearing
signs of religious or political belief, and
reiterate that reasonable freedom of expression
should never be snuffed out by insidious political
correctness?
>> The Prime Minister:
We have, as my hon. Friend knows, a strong
tradition in this country of freedom of expression.
It is the right of all women to choose how
they dress and we do not intend to legislate
on this issue. He raised the broader issue
of symbols, but this case came up particularly
in relation to the wearing of the veil. There
will be times when it is right to ask for
a veil to be removed, such as at border security
or, perhaps, in court. Individual institutions
can make their own policies, but it is not
for Government to tell women what they can
and cannot wear. We want to continue that
strong tradition of freedom of expression.
>> Ms Tasmina Ahmed-Sheikh (Ochil and South
Perthshire) (SNP):
Our First Minister was elected with the largest
vote in Scottish parliamentary history, on
a manifesto that stated that the Scottish
Parliament—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The question will be heard.
>> Ms Ahmed-Sheikh:
Thank you, Mr Speaker. I will start again.
Our First Minister was elected with the largest
vote in Scottish parliamentary history, on
a manifesto pledge that the Scottish Parliament
should have the right to hold an independence
referendum
“if there is a significant and material
change in the circumstances…such as Scotland
being taken out of the EU against our will.”
My question to the Prime Minister is simple:
does she agree that Governments should stick
to their manifesto promises? If so, she cannot
object to the First Minister sticking to hers.
>> The Prime Minister:
I of course recognise that a vote took place
for the Scottish Parliament, and that the
First Minister was returned as the First Minister
of a minority Government, but I refer the
hon. Lady to two other votes that took place.
In September 2014, the Scottish people were
given the opportunity to vote on whether or
not they wished to remain in the United Kingdom.
They chose that Scotland should remain part
of the United Kingdom. That was described
by the right hon. Member for Gordon (Alex
Salmond) as a “once in a generation” vote.
The other vote to take note of was on 23 June
last year, when the people of the United Kingdom
voted to leave the European Union, and that
is what we are going to do.
>> Geoffrey Clifton-Brown (The Cotswolds)
(Con):
With 80% of small and medium-sized enterprises
reluctant to export, does my right hon. Friend
agree that the prospect of Brexit gives those
firms—particularly those from Scotland—a
golden opportunity to use the great British
entrepreneurial spirit to go out into the
world and succeed?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right. Small
businesses and entrepreneurs are essential
to an economy that is working for everyone.
The opportunity that comes from Brexit is
to see those firms go out and export across
the world, and to do those trade deals that
will be of benefit to them, to their communities
and to our economy. We want to encourage more
businesses to go out there and export. That
is exactly what my right hon. Friend the Secretary
of State for International Trade is doing.
This is an important part of building a stronger,
fairer Britain for the future.
>> Hannah Bardell (Livingston) (SNP):
Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs employs
more than 1,000 vital staff in my Livingston
constituency. Despite widespread criticism
from the National Audit Office and the Public
Accounts Committee, and despite Livingston
having the most engaged and productive staff,
the Prime Minister’s Government are determined
to move jobs from Livingston to Edinburgh.
Staff do not want to move there and rental
costs will be higher. To compound that, last
week Ethicon announced that 400 jobs are set
to go at its Livingston site. Will the Prime
Minister therefore change her mind on HMRC
jobs in Livingston, and meet me to ensure
that public sector jobs that are vital to
Livingston stay in Livingston?
>> The Prime Minister:
HMRC is indeed relocating from 170 outdated
offices to 13 large, modern regional centres.
The new centres will be equipped with the
digital infrastructure and facilities that
are needed to build a more highly skilled
and flexible workforce, to enable the modernisation
of ways of working, make tax collection more
efficient and effective, and bring significant
improvements to HMRC’s customer services.
>> Dr Caroline Johnson (Sleaford and North
Hykeham) (Con):
The people of Sleaford and North Hykeham voted
strongly in favour of Brexit, and I was very
proud to be here in the House on Monday to
vote in support of the European Union (Notification
of Withdrawal) Bill. Will my right hon. Friend
the Prime Minister confirm that she shares
my commitment to a Brexit that works in the
best interests of everyone in our country?
>> The Prime Minister:
I have to say—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The hon. Member for Perth and North
Perthshire (Pete Wishart) was shouting from
beyond the Bar, which is very disorderly.
On top of that, a few moments ago he was gesticulating
in a most eccentric manner. I am becoming
concerned about the hon. Gentleman, who must
now calm himself.
>> The Prime Minister:
Thank you, Mr Speaker. My hon. Friend the
Member for Sleaford and North Hykeham (Dr
Johnson) is absolutely right. As she says,
her constituency voted overwhelmingly to leave
the European Union. The point is that the
people of the United Kingdom voted by a majority
to leave the European Union. As we do that,
we will ensure that the deal we achieve in
our negotiations is the right deal for the
whole of the United Kingdom—for people in
England, Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland.
>> Yvette Cooper (Normanton, Pontefract and
Castleford) (Lab):
The Prime Minister has just made a £2 billion
Budget U-turn in the space of a week. Last
year, the Government made a £4 billion U-turn
in the space of five days. Is that why they
want to abolish spring Budgets—because they
just keep ripping them up?
>> The Prime Minister:
I welcome the measures in the spring Budget
to improve school places for children, and
to ensure that we put money—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. The hon. Member for Lichfield (Michael
Fabricant) is another very eccentric fellow
shouting very loudly. You must not shout down
your own Prime Minister! Let us hear the Prime
Minister.
>> The Prime Minister:
Thank you, Mr Speaker. I welcome the measures
in the spring Budget to ensure we put money
into schools, skills and social care. I would
have thought the right hon. Member for Normanton,
Pontefract and Castleford (Yvette Cooper)
would have accepted that putting money into
schools, skills and social care is good for
this country.
>> Rebecca Pow (Taunton Deane) (Con):
Will the Prime Minister join me in welcoming
the news today that Sergeant Blackman’s
murder conviction has been downgraded to manslaughter,
in part thanks to the release of previously
unheard evidence? That is fantastic news for
his wife Claire, who lives in my constituency
and who has campaigned so unstintingly. My
hon. Friend the Member for South Dorset (Richard
Drax), who I believe is returning from chambers,
proved a very worthy advocate in this case,
and I commend his hard work. Does the Prime
Minister agree that, within the correct legal
framework, those who defend our peace and
protect our world from evil should be treated
with fairness and understanding and given
the adequate resources, including mental health
support, that they deserve?
>> The Prime Minister:
Of course we respect the court’s decision.
The Ministry of Defence will be looking very
closely at the judgment. I assure the House
that the Ministry of Defence has co-operated
fully at each stage of Sergeant Blackman’s
case. It will continue to provide support
to the family, as it has done since the charges
were first brought. I would just say, on the
general point, that our Royal Marines have
a worldwide reputation as one of the world’s
elite fighting forces. They make an incredible
contribution to our country and we should
pay tribute to them all.
>> Stephen Twigg (Liverpool, West Derby) (Lab/Co-op):
The Disasters Emergency Committee has launched
its east Africa crisis appeal. In the context
of that crisis, does the Prime Minister share
my concern that President Trump is considering
major cuts to spending by the US on aid? Will
the Government take every opportunity to press
the Americans to remain fully part of the
global humanitarian system?
>> The Prime Minister:
I assure the hon. Gentleman that we recognise
the severity and urgency of the crisis taking
place in east Africa. More than 20 million
people face the risk of dying from starvation
because of war and drought. Again, it is this
country that is leading the way in delivering
life-saving support. We have announced that
we will match, pound for pound, the first
£5 million donated by the public to the Disasters
Emergency Committee’s new east Africa crisis
appeal, to which he referred. I assure him
that we take every opportunity to ensure that
countries around the world recognise the importance
of international aid, and of supporting countries
when we see terrible disasters such as this
famine coming into being. The UK’s record,
and what we do, enable us to say to others
that they should do more.
>> Henry Smith (Crawley) (Con):
It is my honour to chair the all-party parliamentary
group on blood cancer. Today we launched an
inquiry into greater awareness of the condition
and the patient experience. I seek assurances
from my right hon. Friend that the additional
£10 billion going into the NHS in this Parliament
will in some way be spent on ensuring that
we tackle this third-biggest cancer killer.
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is right to raise this subject.
Many people have not heard much about this
particular cancer, and are probably not much
aware of it as an issue. I can assure him
about what the NHS is doing. Over the last
few years, we have seen a significant improvement
in cancer survival rates. We have seen an
increase in the number of people being referred
on because of potential cancer cases, and
an increase in the number of people being
treated for cancer. This is a record on which
we want to build.