>>Helen Jones (Warrington North) (Lab): If
she will list her official engagements for
Wednesday 25 January.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): As
the response from the whole House showed,
we all indeed welcome the Speaker of the Burmese
Parliament and his colleagues to see our deliberations
today.
I am sure that the whole House will join me
in sending our thoughts to the friends and
family of the police officer who was shot
in Belfast over the weekend. The Police Service
of Northern Ireland does a superb job in keeping
us safe and secure, and has our fullest support.
This morning, I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others, and in addition to
my duties in this House I shall have further
such meetings later today. Later this week,
I will travel to the United States for talks
with President Trump.
>>Helen Jones: I join the Prime Minister in
sending good wishes to the police officer
who was shot in Belfast.
They are the best drivers of social mobility,
and 99% of them are rated good or outstanding,
while 65% of their places are in the most
deprived areas of this country, so why is
the Prime Minister introducing cuts that threaten
the very existence of maintained nursery schools?
Is it not true that when it comes to social
mobility, her actions speak far louder than
her words?
>>The Prime Minister: I want to ensure, and
this Government want to ensure, good-quality
education at every age and every stage for
children in this country. That is why we are
looking at improving the number of good school
places. The hon. Lady talks about my record
speaking louder than words, so let me point
out that I was very proud as chairman of an
education authority in London in the 1990s
to introduce nursery school places for every
three and four-year-old whose parent wanted
them.
>>Chris Philp (Croydon South) (Con): The Prime
Minister laid out a clear and bold plan for
Brexit in her speech last week. Hon. Members
quite rightly want an opportunity to scrutinise
the plan. Does the Prime Minister agree that
the best way of facilitating that scrutiny
would be a Government White Paper laying out
our vision for a global Britain based on free
trade in goods and services that will be to
the benefit of us and other European countries?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
the question of parliamentary scrutiny. I
have made clear, as have senior Ministers,
that we will ensure that Parliament has every
opportunity to carry out such scrutiny as
we go through this process. I set out that
bold plan for a global Britain last week.
I recognise that there is an appetite in the
House to see it set out in a White Paper—I
have heard my hon. Friend’s question, and
my right hon. Friend the Member for Broxtowe
(Anna Soubry) asked a question in the same
vein last week—and I can confirm that our
plan will be set out in a White Paper published
for the House.
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): I
join the Prime Minister in expressing the
condolences of, I am sure, the whole House
to the family of the police officer who lost
his life over the weekend in Northern Ireland.
The Prime Minister has wasted 80 days between
the original judgment and the appeal. She
has finally admitted today, after pressure
from all sides, that there will be a White
Paper. May we know when that White Paper will
be available to us, and why it is taking so
long for us to get it?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
asked for debates. I made very clear that
there would always be debates in the House,
and there have been and will continue to be.
He asked for votes. There have been votes
in the House; the House voted overwhelmingly
for the Government to trigger article 50 before
the end of March this year. He asked for a
plan. As we heard from my hon. Friend the
Member for Croydon South (Chris Philp), I
have set out a clear plan for a bold future
for Britain. He and others asked for a White
Paper, and I have made clear that there will
be a White Paper.
What I am also clear about is that the right
hon. Gentleman always asks about process—about
the means to an end. The Government and I
are focusing on the outcomes. We are focusing
on a truly global Britain, building a stronger
future for this country, the right deal for
Britain, and Britain out of the European Union.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: My question was not complicated.
I simply asked when the White Paper would
come out. Will it be published before or at
the same time as the Bill that is apparently
about to be published?
Last week I asked the Prime Minister repeatedly
to clarify whether her Government were prepared
to pay to secure tariff-free access to the
single European market. She repeatedly refused
to answer the question, so I will ask her
again. Are her Government ruling out paying
a fee for tariff-free access to the single
market or the bespoke customs union to which
she also referred in her speech?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
has mentioned the issue of timing. There are
actually two separate issues. The House has
voted overwhelmingly that article 50 should
be triggered before the end of March 2017.
Following the Supreme Court judgment, a Bill
will be provided for the House, and there
will be proper debates on it in the Chamber
and in another place. There is then the separate
question of the publication of the plan that
I have set out, a bold vision for Britain
for the future. I will do that in the White
Paper. The right hon. Gentleman knows that
one of our objectives is the best possible
free trade with the European Union, and that
is what we will be out there negotiating for.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Some of this is very worrying
for many Members, but, more important, it
is worrying for many other people. For example,
the chief executive of Nissan was given assurances
by the Prime Minister’s Business Secretary
about future trade arrangements with Europe,
but now says that Nissan will
“have to re-evaluate the situation”
in relation to its investments in Britain.
The Prime Minister is threatening the EU that
unless it gives in to her demands she will
turn Britain into a bargain basement tax haven
off the coast of Europe. Labour Members are
very well aware of the consequences that that
would have—the damage that it would do to
jobs and living standards, and to our public
services. Is the Prime Minister now going
to rule out the bargain basement threat that
she made in her speech at Lancaster House?
>>The Prime Minister: I expect us to get a
good deal for trading relationships with the
European Union, but I am also clear that this
Government will not sign up to a bad deal
for the United Kingdom. As for the threats
that the right hon. Gentleman claims might
happen—he often uses those phrases and talks
about workers’ rights—perhaps he should
listen to his former colleague in this House,
the Mayor of London, Sadiq Khan, who today
said,
“to give credit to the Government…I don’t
think they want to weaken workers’ rights”,
and goes on to say,
“I’ve seen no evidence from the conversations
I’ve had with senior members of the Government
that that’s their aspiration or their intention
or something they want to do. Which is good.”
As usual with Labour, the right hand is not
talking to the far-left.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The evidence of what the
Tory party and this Government really think
about workers’ rights was there for all
to see yesterday: a private Member’s Bill
under the ten-minute rule by a Tory MP to
tear up parts of the International Labour
Organisation convention, talking down the
Bill of my hon. Friend the Member for Great
Grimsby (Melanie Onn) to protect European
workers’ rights that have been obtained
in this country. That is the real agenda of
the Tory party.
What the Prime Minister is doing is petulantly
aiming a threat at our public services with
her threats about a bargain basement Britain.
Is her priority our struggling NHS, those
denied social care, and children having their
school funding cut, or is it once again further
cuts in big business taxation to make the
rich even better off?
>>The Prime Minister: I simply remind the
right hon. Gentleman that I have been very
clear that this Government will protect workers’
rights; indeed, we have a review of modern
employment law to ensure all employment legislation
is keeping up with the modern labour market.
One of the objectives I set out in my plan
for our negotiating objectives was to protect
workers’ rights.
The right hon. Gentleman talks about threats
to public services. I will tell him what the
threat to public services would be: a Labour
Government borrowing £500 million extra.
That would destroy our economy and mean no
funding for our public services.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The threat to workers’
rights is there every day: 6 million people
earning less than the living wage; and many
people—nearly 1 million—on zero-hours
contracts with no protection being offered
by this Government. What they are doing is
offering once again the bargain basement alternative.
Will the Prime Minister also take this opportunity
today to congratulate the 100,000 people who
marched in Britain last weekend to highlight
women’s rights after President Trump’s
inauguration, and to express their concerns
about his misogyny? Many have concerns that
in the Prime Minister’s forthcoming meeting
with President Trump she will be prepared
to offer up for sacrifice the opportunity
for American companies to come in and take
over parts of our NHS or our public services.
Will she assure the House that in any trade
deal none of those things will be offered
up as a bargaining chip?
>>The Prime Minister: I again point out to
the right hon. Gentleman that it is this Government
who have introduced the national living wage
and this Government who have made changes
to zero-hours contracts.
On the issue of my visit to the United States
of America, I am pleased that I am able to
meet President Trump so early in his Administration.
That is a sign of the strength of the special
relationship between the United Kingdom and
the United States of America—a special relationship
on which he and I intend to build. But I also
say to the Leader of the Opposition that I
am not afraid to speak frankly to a President
of the United States; I am able to do that
because we have that special relationship—a
special relationship that the right hon. Gentleman
would never have with the United States.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: We would never allow Britain
to be sold off on the cheap. How confident
is the Prime Minister of getting a good deal
for “global Britain” from a President
who says he wants to put America first, buy
American and build a wall between his country
and Mexico?
Article 50 was not about a court judgment
against the Government. What it signified
was the bad judgment of this Government: the
bad judgment of prioritising corporate tax
cuts over investment in national health and
social care; the bad judgment of threatening
European partners while offering a blank cheque
to President Trump; and the bad judgment of
wanting to turn Britain into a bargain basement
tax haven. So will the Prime Minister offer
some clarity and certainty and withdraw the
threats to destroy the social structure of
this country by turning us into the bargain
basement she clearly threatens?
>>The Prime Minister: We will be out around
the world with the EU, America and other countries
negotiating good free trade deals for this
country that will bring prosperity to this
country. The right hon. Gentleman wants to
talk about Brexit, but I have to say to him
that he is the leader of his party and he
cannot even agree with his shadow Chancellor
about Brexit. The shadow Chancellor cannot
agree with the shadow Brexit Secretary, the
shadow Brexit secretary disagrees with the
shadow Home Secretary, and the shadow Home
Secretary has to ring up the leader and tell
him to change his mind. He talks about us
standing up for Britain; they cannot speak
for themselves and they will never speak for
Britain.
>>David Warburton (Somerton and Frome) (Con):
On 27 December, another young woman lost her
life driving through the west country on the
A303. In the past decade, more than 1,000
people have been killed or injured on that
road. For 40 years, Governments have promised
to dual the lethal parts of the road where
two lanes become three or three lanes become
two, with no central reservation. The queues
on the road are also legendary. I know that
the Government are committed to an upgrade,
but will the Prime Minister assure us that
the proposed tunnel beneath Stonehenge will
not hold up essential work elsewhere, and
that we will soon see cones on the road and
spades in the ground?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important issue, and he is absolutely right
to do that. I can assure him that we are working
generally to improve the safety of our roads.
He refers specifically to the issue of the
A303 and to the tragic incident that happened
on 27 December. We have committed to creating
a dual carriageway on the A303 from the M3
to the M5. I understand that Highways England
has recently launched a consultation into
the route under Stonehenge, and my hon. Friend
will want to look closely at that issue. This
is all part of our £2 billion investment
in road improvements that will improve connections
in the south-west, but I can assure him that
we have road safety at the forefront of our
mind.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): May I begin
by wishing everybody a happy Burns day, and
by extending congratulations to The Scotsman
newspaper, which is celebrating its bicentenary
today?
Yesterday, the Government lost in the Supreme
Court, and today we have had a welcome U-turn
on a White Paper on Brexit. In the spirit
of progress for Parliament, and in advance
of her meeting President Trump, will the Prime
Minister tell Parliament what she wants to
achieve in a UK-US trade deal?
>>The Prime Minister: First, I join the right
hon. Gentleman in wishing a happy Burns day
to everybody and in recognising the bicentenary
of The Scotsman. I am sure everybody in the
House will join me in that. He asks what we
want to achieve in our arrangements with the
United States. It is very simple: we want
to achieve an arrangement that ensures that
the interests of the United Kingdom are put
first, and that is what I will be doing. We
want to see trade arrangements with the United
States, and with other parts of the world,
that can increase our trade and bring prosperity
and growth to the United Kingdom. Then, my
aim for this Government is to ensure that
the economy works for everyone in every part
of the United Kingdom.
>>Angus Robertson: The European Union, which
we are still part of, has among the highest
food safety standards anywhere in the world,
and we are proud on our continent to have
public national health systems. The United
States, on the other hand, is keen to have
health systems that are fully open to private
competition and it wants to export genetically
modified organisms, beef raised using growth
hormones and chicken meat washed with chlorinated
water. Will the Prime Minister tell President
Trump that she is not prepared to lower our
food and safety standards or to open our health
systems up for privatisation? Or does she
believe that that is a price worth paying
for a UK-US trade deal?
>>The Prime Minister: We will be looking for
a UK-US trade deal that improves trade between
our two countries, that will bring prosperity
and growth to this country and that will ensure
that we can bring jobs to this country as
well. I can assure the right hon. Gentleman
that, in doing that, we will put UK interests
and UK values first.
>>Kevin Hollinrake (Thirsk and Malton) (Con):
Historic per capita spending in our regions,
including Yorkshire, when compared with London
is up to 40% lower for our local authorities,
up to 50% lower for our schools and up to
60% lower for our transport projects. Does
the Prime Minister agree that, if we want
to build a country that works for everyone,
we need a fair funding deal that works for
everyone?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the issues
that my hon. Friend has raised, and I can
assure him that our commitment in relation
to the northern parts of England, including
Yorkshire, is absolutely clear. We want to
back business growth right across the north,
and we are backing the northern powerhouse
to help the great cities and towns of the
north to pool their strengths and take on
the world. Yorkshire local enterprise partnerships
have received an additional £156 million
in Government funding this week, and we are
spending a record £13 billion on transport
across the north. As a result, there are more
people in work in Yorkshire and the Humber
than ever before, and the employment rate
is at a record high. That is good news for
people in the region and good news for our
economy as a whole.
>>Dr Philippa Whitford (Central Ayrshire)
(SNP): The European Medicines Agency provides
a single drug licensing system for 500 million
people and results in the UK having drugs
licensed six to 12 months ahead of countries
like Canada and Australia. Yesterday, the
Health Secretary stated that the UK will not
be in the EMA, so can the Prime Minister confirm
this and explain how she will prevent delayed
drug access for UK patients?
>>The Prime Minister: There are a number of
organisations that we are part of as members
of the European Union. As part of the work
that we are doing to look at the United Kingdom’s
future after we leave the European Union,
we are looking at the arrangements we can
put in place in relation to those issues.
The pharmaceutical industry in this country
is a very important part of our economy, and
the ability of people to access these new
drugs is also important. I assure the hon.
Lady that we are looking seriously at this
and will ensure that we have the arrangements
that we need.
>>Kit Malthouse (North West Hampshire) (Con):
Too few British entrepreneurs are connecting
with the capital they need to start and grow.
As part of her industrial strategy, which
will be looking at access to capital, will
the Prime Minister order a review of the enterprise
investment scheme and the seed enterprise
investment scheme in the hope that they can
be simplified, helping to create the large
pools of buccaneering capital that British
industry needs?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important issue. He has long been a champion
of entrepreneurship in this country, and I
can tell him that in the industrial strategy
we are committed to providing the best environment
for business. The Treasury has established
a patient capital review, for example, with
a panel chaired by Sir Damon Buffini to look
at the barriers that exist to long-term investment.
We are also increasing investment in venture
capital by the British Business Bank by £400
million, and that will unlock £1 billion
of new finance. The Treasury is going to be
publishing a consultation in the spring examining
these issues, and I am sure my hon. Friend
will wish to contribute and respond to that.
>>Lilian Greenwood (Nottingham South) (Lab):
Four-and-a-half years ago, my constituents
Chris and Lydia Leek were on a family holiday
on the Greek island of Zante when their son,
Jamie, was hit and killed by a speeding motorbike—it
was his ninth birthday. The rider was convicted
but has appealed against his sentence and,
to date, remains a free man. Will the Prime
Minister agree to meet Chris and Lydia to
discuss how they can finally secure justice
for Jamie?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to look
at the tragic case that the hon. Lady describes.
Our thoughts must be with Chris and Lydia
at the terrible loss they experienced. As
to the issue of what is happening in terms
of the Greek criminal justice system, of course
that is a matter for the Greek authorities,
but I will look seriously at this case and
see if there is anything that the Foreign
Office can do.
>>Mr Andrew Tyrie (Chichester) (Con): President
Trump has repeatedly said that he will bring
back torture as an instrument of policy. When
she sees him on Friday, will the Prime Minister
make it clear that in no circumstances will
she permit Britain to be dragged into facilitating
that torture, as we were after 11 September?
>>The Prime Minister: I assure my right hon.
Friend that our position on torture is clear:
we do not sanction torture and do not get
involved in it. That will continue to be our
position.
>>Andy Slaughter (Hammersmith) (Lab): Seventy
per cent. of my constituents voted remain,
15% are citizens of other EU countries, and
almost all do not trust the Prime Minister’s
Government to negotiate a deal that secures
the future prosperity of London and the UK.
Will she give this House a veto on the deal
that she does, or will she put the deal to
a referendum of the British people?
>>The Prime Minister: People voted differently
across the country. Parts of the country voted
to remain and parts of the country voted to
leave. What we do now is unite behind the
result of the vote that took place. We come
together as a country, we go out there, we
make a success of this, and we ensure that
we build a truly global Britain that will
bring jobs to the hon. Gentleman’s constituency
and for his constituents.
>>Iain Stewart (Milton Keynes South) (Con):
This week, Milton Keynes celebrates its 50th
birthday. [Hon. Members: “Hear, hear.”]
We have been the most successful of new cities
and have one of the highest rates of economic
growth. Does the Prime Minister agree that
Milton Keynes has a great future and will
be central to delivering this Government’s
ambitions?
>>The Prime Minister: I join my hon. Friend
in marking Milton Keynes’ 50th birthday.
I understand that he has secured a Westminster
Hall debate on the subject later today, so
I congratulate him on that. Milton Keynes
is a great example of what can be achieved
with a clear plan and strong local leadership.
We are providing additional funding for the
east-west rail project, which he supported
through his chairing of the east-west rail
all-party parliamentary group, and the Oxford
to Cambridge expressway road scheme. We will
see a country that works for everyone. Milton
Keynes has had a great 50 years, but I am
sure that it will have a great future as well.
>>Kelvin Hopkins (Luton North) (Lab): Last
week, a freight train from China arrived in
Barking after using the channel tunnel, demonstrating
the massive potential of rail freight. However,
continental rail wagons and lorry trailers
on trains cannot be accommodated on Britain’s
historic rail network because its loading
gauge is too small. Will the Prime Minister
therefore consider giving positive support
to the GB freight route scheme, which will
provide a large-gauge freight line linking
all the nations and regions of Britain both
to each other and to Europe and Asia? It would
take 5 million lorry journeys off Britain’s
roads every year.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman raises
the difference in gauges on railways here
and on the continent, which has obviously
been an issue for some considerable time.
We want to encourage rail freight, we have
been encouraging it, and we will continue
to do so.
>>Rebecca Pow (Taunton Deane) (Con): The Ministry
of Cake in Taunton, a company with a turnover
of £30 million, has recently been bought
by a French company called Mademoiselle Desserts.
The Ministry of Cake trades across Europe
and into China. Does the Prime Minister agree
that that demonstrates confidence in our economy—in
that a European company has bought into it—that
we can unlock global trade and that the south-west
is a terrific place to do business?
>>The Prime Minister: I absolutely agree with
my hon. Friend. The investment of a French
company into the company in her constituency
shows people’s confidence in the future
of our economy, the fundamental strengths
of our economy and that we can unlock global
trade. Of course, the south-west is a very
good place to do business.
>>Peter Grant (Glenrothes) (SNP): Robert Burns
once spoke that whatever damages society,
or any least part of it, “this is my measure
of iniquity.”Does the Prime Minister agree
that that description applies perfectly to
the detained fast track system, recently found
to be illegal by British courts, under which
10,000 asylum seekers were denied a fair trial,
some of whom were probably illegally deported
to face death and torture?
>>The Prime Minister: The issue of the detained
fast track system in the asylum system is
one that I obviously looked at when I was
Home Secretary, and we made a number of changes
to how we operated it. However, it is built
on a simple principle: if somebody’s case
for asylum is such that they are almost certain
to be refused that asylum, we want to ensure
that they can be removed from the country
as quickly as possible, hence the detained
fast track system.
>>David Morris (Morecambe and Lunesdale) (Con):
Will my right hon. Friend the Prime Minister
assist in efforts to get an enterprise zone
in my constituency of Morecambe and Lunesdale
as part of the industrial strategy? It turns
out that the Labour council and county council
are talking about an enterprise zone-esque
project in the area but have not applied for
any funding whatsoever. Will she please assist
me in this endeavour?
>>The Prime Minister: I know what a champion
for Morecambe and Lunesdale my hon. Friend
is and has been as a Member of Parliament,
and I am sure that the Chancellor and the
Business Secretary will look at the issue
he has raised. I should also say how sad it
is that Labour councils are not willing to
put forward proposals to increase the prosperity
and economic growth in their areas.
>>Patrick Grady (Glasgow North) (SNP): When
she will next meet the First Minister of Scotland.
>>The Prime Minister: I will meet the First
Minister and leaders of the devolved Administrations
at the Joint Ministerial Committee on Monday,
but of course we regularly engage with the
Scottish Government on a wide range of issues.
>>Patrick Grady: When the Prime Minister does
eventually meet the First Minister, will the
Prime Minister confirm whether she supports
the principle in the Scotland Act that whatever
is not reserved is devolved? Will she be able
to tell the First Minister what powers will
come to the Scottish Parliament in the event
of Brexit? Will she confirm that the great
repeal Bill will not be the great power grab?
>>The Prime Minister: I have been very clear,
and this was echoed yesterday by my right
hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Exiting
the European Union, that no powers that are
currently devolved are suddenly going to be
taken back to the United Kingdom Government.
We will be looking at and discussing with
the devolved Administrations how we deal with
those powers that are currently in Brussels
when they come back to the United Kingdom.
We want to ensure that those powers are dealt
with so that we can maintain the important
single market of the United Kingdom.
>>Oliver Dowden (Hertsmere) (Con): It is currently
an offence to assault a police officer, immigration
officer or prison officer, but it is not a
specific offence to assault an NHS worker,
whether they are a doctor, nurse or paramedic.
Does the Prime Minister agree that we should
consider extending a specific offence to cover
such people, to make it absolutely clear that
the public will not tolerate violence towards
our hard-working members of the NHS?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important point. Of course, we condemn
assaults on anybody and any violence that
takes place. The Secretary of State for Health
has heard the case that my hon. Friend has
put and will be happy to look into that issue.
>>Chris Bryant (Rhondda) (Lab): When the Prime
Minister introduces a UK agricultural policy
because we have left the common agricultural
policy, will the Duke of Westminster still
receive £407,000 a year, will the Duke of
Northumberland still receive £475,000 a year,
and will the Earl of Iveagh still receive
£915,000 a year from the British taxpayer?
>>Mr Speaker: The hon. Gentleman seems to
know a lot about these ducal matters; it is
most interesting. I am fascinated by the reply,
so let’s hear it.
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman is
right that one of the tasks we will have when
we leave the European Union is to decide what
support is provided to agriculture as a result
of our being outside the common agricultural
policy. I assure him that we are taking the
interests of all parts of the United Kingdom
into account when we look at that system and
what it should be in future.
>>Mr Speaker: Ah, yes, a Hampshire knight.
>>Sir Gerald Howarth: Last weekend, my right
hon. Friend the Secretary of State for Defence
made a welcome visit to Ukraine, where he
said that freedom and democracy are not tradeable
commodities. As we mark the 25th anniversary
of relations between our two Parliaments,
may I invite my right hon. Friend the Prime
Minister to declare the continuing support
of the United Kingdom for the maintenance
of an independent sovereign state in Ukraine,
which has been subjected to the most outrageous
annexation of part of its property by Russia?
>>The Prime Minister: I am very happy to join
my hon. Friend in confirming our commitment
to the independent sovereign state of Ukraine.
The Foreign Secretary has been doing a lot
of work with other Foreign Ministers on this
issue. We provide significant support to Ukraine,
and I hope to be able to meet President Poroshenko
soon and talk about the support we provide.
>>Mr Pat McFadden (Wolverhampton South East)
(Lab): In her speech last week, the Prime
Minister said that Parliament would get a
vote on the final deal between the UK and
the European Union. Will she set out for the
House what would happen if Parliament said
no to the terms of that deal? In those circumstances,
would she negotiate an alternative deal, or
would her no deal option mean our falling
back on World Trade Organisation rules, which
would mean 10% tariffs on cars, 20% tariffs
on food and drink, and a host of other barriers
to trade, investment and prosperity in the
UK?
>>The Prime Minister: As I also said in my
speech last week, I expect that we will be
able to negotiate a good trade deal with the
European Union, because it will be in our
interests and the interests of the European
Union to do so. There will be a vote on the
deal for this Parliament. If this Parliament
is not willing to accept a deal that has been
decided on and agreed by the United Kingdom
Government with the European Union, then,
as I have said, we will have to fall back
on other arrangements.
>>Graham Evans (Weaver Vale) (Con): It was
a great pleasure to welcome my right hon.
Friend the Prime Minister and her Cabinet
to Sci-Tech Daresbury earlier this week. I
welcome the Government’s industrial strategy,
which will bring high-skill, high-wage jobs
that will help close the north-south divide.
The message is that Britain is open for business.
>>The Prime Minister: I and the whole Cabinet
were very pleased to be able to visit Daresbury.
I was pleased to sit down and meet small businesses
on that particular site and to hear their
support for what the Government are doing
in the industrial strategy. We should be very
clear that Britain is open for business. We
will be out there trading around the world.
We will be a global leader in free trade,
bringing jobs, economic growth and prosperity
to every part of this country.
>>Ian Blackford (Ross, Skye and Lochaber)
(SNP): We are all aware of the hundreds of
thousands of women around the world who marched
on behalf of women’s rights last weekend.
In this House, we have been lobbied by members
of the Women Against State Pension Inequality.
Many MPs have lodged petitions asking the
Government to act. Can the Prime Minister
tell us how many MPs have lodged such petitions?
>>The Prime Minister: I think the number of
petitions presented in this Parliament is
a matter for the House authorities. The hon.
Gentleman also knows that the Government have
already taken action in relation to the issue
of women’s pensions by reducing the changes
that will be experienced by women and putting
extra money into that.
>>Mr John Baron (Basildon and Billericay)
(Con): Following her excellent EU speech last
week, will the Prime Minister consider unilaterally
guaranteeing the rights of EU citizens living
and working in the UK? Not only is that the
decent thing to do, but, by taking the moral
high ground, it will be a source of strength
going forward in the negotiations. We can
always return to the issue of non-reciprocation
by the EU, if necessary, later in those negotiations.
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the concern
that my hon. Friend has raised, but my position
remains the same as it always has been. I
expect, intend and want to be able to guarantee
the rights of EU citizens living here in the
United Kingdom, but, as the British Prime
Minister, it is only right that I should give
consideration to the rights of UK citizens
living elsewhere in what will be the remaining
27 member states of the EU. That is why I
want that reciprocal arrangement, but, as
I said in my speech last week, I remain open
to this being an issue that we negotiate at
a very early stage in the negotiations. There
are a good number of other European member
states that want that too. Some do not, but
I am hoping to settle this at an early stage.
>>Dr Lisa Cameron (East Kilbride, Strathaven
and Lesmahagow) (SNP): As chair of the all-party
parliamentary group on disability, we recently
compiled an important inquiry report into
the Government’s pledge to halve the disability
employment gap. Research shows that that pledge
will not be met for 50 years. To date, no
Minister has met the APPG to discuss the report.
Will the Prime Minister place people with
disability at the heart of policy and ensure
that her Ministers engage with the APPG and
its recommendations?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Lady raises
an important issue about disabled people in
the workplace. It is one of which we are aware.
Of course, as we see unemployment going down,
the ratios do change to an extent. The Secretary
of State for Work and Pensions is looking
very seriously at how we can ensure that there
are more disabled people in the workplace.
I am sure that he will see the requests that
she has made in relation to the APPG.
>>Mr David Burrowes (Enfield, Southgate) (Con):
May I welcome the Prime Minister’s meeting
with the President of Turkey on Saturday,
when we can show our solidarity in the fight
against terrorism and deepen our trading relationship?
Will she also seek support for a united and
independent Cyprus, free from Turkish troops?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend
for raising that matter. There are important
issues that I will be discussing with President
Erdoğan and with the Prime Minister of Turkey
when I meet them on Saturday. On Cyprus, I
am hopeful that the talks will continue and
that we will come to a solution—we are closer
to a solution now than we have been before.
I have already spoken to Prime Minister Tsipras
and to President Erdoğan about the need to
ensure that we are creative in the thinking
and in the finding of a solution. I had a
further telephone call with Nicos Anastasiades
over the weekend about this very issue. We
stand ready as a guarantor to play our part
in ensuring that we see a successful conclusion
of these talks and the reunification of Cyprus
that people have been working towards for
some time.
>>Mr Nigel Dodds (Belfast North) (DUP): I
join the Prime Minister in wishing a speedy
recovery to the police officer who was shot
and injured in my constituency in north Belfast
on Sunday night. Thankfully, he was not killed—but
of course that was not the terrorists’ intention.
It is clear that the political instability
brought about by Sinn Féin’s collapse of
the Assembly is not in anyone’s interests
in Northern Ireland. It is also clear that
it is Sinn Féin’s intention to try to rewrite
the history of the past. Will the Prime Minister
make it very clear that the one-sided legal
persecution of police officers and soldiers
who did so much to bring peace to Northern
Ireland will not be allowed to continue?
>>The Prime Minister: As the right hon. Gentleman
indicates, political stability in Northern
Ireland has been hard earned over some considerable
time, and none of us wants to see that thrown
away. He raised the issue of the current situation
with a number of investigations by the Police
Service of Northern Ireland into former soldiers
and their activities in Northern Ireland.
It is absolutely right that we recognise that
the majority of people who lost their life
did so as a result of terrorist activity,
and it is important that that terrorist activity
is looked into. That is why one of the issues
that my right hon. Friend the Secretary of
State for Northern Ireland is looking at is
the legacy question and how the issue of investigation
on all sides can take place in future.
>>Maggie Throup (Erewash) (Con): Social care
provided by Labour-led Derbyshire County Council
is failing miserably, with serious errors
in process leading to shameful consequences
for some of the most vulnerable people in
my constituency. It is clearly not about funding,
as the council sits on reserves of about £233
million. Will my right hon. Friend instigate
an urgent review of social care practice at
the county council, because the people of
Derbyshire deserve better?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend makes
an important point. The success of social
care is not wholly about funding. It is about
practice on the ground, which is why we have
made it clear that it is important to see
integration between social and health care
at a local level, and local authorities should
play their part in delivering that. This is
an issue that needs to be addressed for the
longer term as well. It has been ducked by
Governments for too long in this country,
which is why this Government are determined
to introduce a sustainable programme for social
care in future.
[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: The right hon. Gentleman never
knew he was quite that popular.
>>Edward Miliband (Doncaster North) (Lab):
I was going to say, Mr Speaker, that it brings
back memories.
As the first foreign leader to meet President
Trump, the Prime Minister carries a huge responsibility
on behalf not just of this country but of
the whole international community in the tone
that she sets. Can I ask her to reassure us
that she will say to the President that he
must abide by, and not withdraw from, the
Paris climate change treaty? In case it is
helpful, can she offer the services of UK
scientists to convince the President that
climate change is not a hoax invented by the
Chinese?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise the role
that the right hon. Gentleman has played in
looking at the issue of climate change, and
I hope that he recognises the commitment that
the Government have shown to this issue, with
the legislation that we have introduced and
the changes that we have brought about in
the energy sector and the use of different
forms of energy. The Obama Administration
signed up to the Paris climate change agreement,
and we have now done so. I would hope that
all parties would continue to ensure that
that climate change agreement is put into
practice.