>>Chris Law (Dundee West) (SNP): If she will
list her official engagements for Wednesday
11 January.
>>The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May): This
morning, I had meetings with ministerial colleagues
and others. In addition to my duties in this
House, I shall have further such meetings
later today.
>>Chris Law: A very happy new year to you,
Mr Speaker, and I would like to extend that
to everyone in this House.
It has been more than six months since the
European referendum. Embarrassingly for the
Prime Minister, the Scottish Government are
the only Administration on these islands to
have published a plan on what to do next.
Has she read it yet? When will she be publishing
her own plan?
>>The Prime Minister: I join the hon. Gentleman
in wishing everybody in the House, not only
Members, but all the staff of the House, a
very happy new year.
As I said to the Liaison Committee when I
appeared in front of it before Christmas,
I will, in a matter of weeks, be setting out
some more details of our proposals on this
issue. I would like just to remind him, when
he talks about the Scottish Government’s
plan, that of course it is his party, the
Scottish nationalist party, that wants to
leave the United Kingdom and therefore leave
the European Union.
>>Mark Menzies (Fylde) (Con): Westinghouse’s
Springfields site in my constituency employs
more than 1,200 people in highly skilled jobs
manufacturing nuclear fuel, which generates
15% of the UK’s electricity. Does my right
hon. Friend agree that the nuclear industry
is of crucial importance to the north-west
economy? Will she continue to support the
construction of a new generation of nuclear
power stations to guarantee jobs in the region?
>>The Prime Minister: I certainly agree with
my hon. Friend that new nuclear does have
a crucial role to play in securing our future
energy needs, especially as we are looking
to move to a low-carbon society. The industrial
strategy that the Government will be setting
out will have a strong emphasis on the role
of regions in supporting economic growth and
ensuring that the economy works for everyone.
Like him, I very much welcome the proposals
from NuGen and Toshiba to develop a new nuclear
power station at Moorside in Cumbria. The
Department for Business, Energy and Industrial
Strategy continues to work closely with NuGen
and other developers as they bring their proposals
forward.
>>Mr Speaker: I call Jeremy Corbyn.
[Hon. Members: “Hear, hear!”]
>>Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab): Thank
you, Mr Speaker. It is nice to get such a
warm welcome, and may I wish all Members,
as well as all members of staff in the House,
a happy new year?
I hope the whole House will join me—I am
sure it will—in paying tribute to 22- year-old
Lance Corporal Scott Hetherington, who died
in a “non-combat” incident in Iraq last
Monday. I am sure the whole House will also
join in sending its heartfelt condolences
to the family and friends of seven-year-old
Katie Rough, who tragically died in York earlier
this week. I think it is right that we send
condolences to her family.
Last week, 485 people in England spent more
than 12 hours on trolleys in hospital corridors.
The Red Cross described this as a “humanitarian
crisis”. I called on the Prime Minister
to come to Parliament on Monday, but she did
not—she sent the Health Secretary. But does
she agree with him that the best way to solve
the crisis of the four-hour wait is to fiddle
the figures so that people are not seen to
be waiting so long on trolleys in NHS hospitals?
>>The Prime Minister: First, may I join the
right hon. Gentleman in sending our condolences
to the family of Lance Corporal Hetherington,
who, as he said, died in a non-combat incident
in Iraq? From everything I have seen and read
about Lance Corporal Hetherington, he was
a very fine young man. He delighted in being
in the armed forces, and we are proud that
such a fine young man was in our armed forces.
I also join the right hon. Gentleman in expressing
condolences to the family and friends of little
Katie, who died so tragically.
The right hon. Gentleman talks about the pressures
on the NHS, and we acknowledge that there
are pressures on the National Health Service.
There are always extra pressures on the NHS
during the winter but, of course, we have
at the moment those added pressures of the
ageing population and the growing complex
needs of the population. He also refers to
the British Red Cross’s term, “humanitarian
crisis.” I have to say to him that I think
we have all seen humanitarian crises around
the world, and to use that description of
a National Health Service that last year saw
2.5 million more people treated in accident
and emergency than six years ago was irresponsible
and overblown.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Some 1.8 million people had
to wait longer than four hours in A&amp;E
departments last year. The Prime Minister
might not like what the Red Cross said, but
on the same day the British Medical Association
said that
“conditions in hospitals across the country
are reaching a dangerous level.”
The Royal College of Nursing has said that
NHS conditions are the worst ever. The Royal
College of Physicians has told the Prime Minister
that the NHS is
“under-funded, under-doctored and overstretched.”
If she will not listen to the Red Cross, who
will she listen to?
>>The Prime Minister: I have said to the right
hon. Gentleman that I of course acknowledge
that there are pressures on the National Health
Service. The Government have put extra funding
into the National Health Service. The fact
is that we are seeing more people being treated
in our NHS: 2,500 more people are treated
within four hours every day in the National
Health Service because of the Government putting
in extra funding and because of the hard work
of medical professionals in our National Health
Service. It is not just a question of targets
for the health service, although we continue
to have a commitment to the four-hour target,
as the Health Secretary has made clear. It
is a question of making sure that people are
provided with the appropriate care for them,
and the best possible care for them in their
circumstances.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: The right hon. Lady seems
to be in some degree of denial about this.
She will not listen to professional organisations
that have spent their whole lifetimes doing
their best for the NHS, but will she listen
to Sian, who works for the NHS? She has a
22-month old nephew. He went into hospital,
but there was no bed. He was treated on two
plastic chairs pushed together with a blanket.
Sian says that
“one of the nurses told my sister that it’s
always like this nowadays”.
She says to us all:
“Surely we should strive to do better than
this.”
Do the Prime Minister and the Health Secretary
think that is an acceptable way to treat a
22-month-old child in need of help?
>>The Prime Minister: I accept that there
have been a small number of incidents in which
unacceptable practices have taken place. We
do not want those things to happen, but what
matters is how you deal with them, which is
why it is so important that the NHS looks
into the issues when unacceptable incidents
have taken place and learns lessons from them.
I come back to the point that I was making
earlier: the right hon. Gentleman talks about
the hard-working healthcare professionals,
like Sian, in the National Health Service,
and indeed we should be grateful for all those
who are working in the NHS, but on the Tuesday
after Christmas we saw the busiest day ever
in the National Health Service, and over the
few weeks around Christmas we saw the day
on which more people were treated in accident
and emergency within four hours than ever
before. That is the reality of our National
Health Service.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: We all thank NHS staff and
we all praise NHS staff, but the Prime Minister’s
Government are proposing, through sustainability
and transformation, to cut one third of the
beds in all of our hospitals in the very near
future. On Monday, she spoke about mental
health and doing more to help people, particularly
young people, with those conditions, which
I welcome, except that last night the BBC
revealed that, over five years, there had
been an 89% increase in young people with
mental health issues having to go to A&E
departments. Does she not agree that the £1.25
billion committed to child and adolescent
mental health in 2015 should have been ring-fenced
rather than used as a resource to be raided
to plug other holes in other budgets in the
NHS?
>>The Prime Minister: If we look at what is
happening with mental health treatment in
the national health service, we see 1,400
more people every day accessing mental health
services. When I spoke about this issue on
Monday, I said that there is of course more
for us to do—this is not a problem that
will be resolved overnight. I have set out
ways in which we will see an improvement in
the services in relation to mental health,
but it is about the appropriate care for the
individual. As I mentioned earlier, that is
not just about accident and emergency. When
I was in Aldershot on Monday, I spoke to service
users with mental health problems who said
that they did not want to go to A&E. The provision
of alternative services has meant that the
A&E locally has seen its numbers stabilising
rather than going up. It is about the appropriate
care for the individual. We want to see that
good practice spread across the whole country.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: Nobody wants people with
mental health conditions to go to A&E departments—the
A&E departments do not want them to go there.
Under this Government, there are 6,000 fewer
nurses and 400 fewer doctors working in mental
health. It is obvious that these people will
go somewhere to try to get help when they
are in a desperate situation. Our NHS is under
huge pressure. Much of that is caused by cuts
to social care, which the Royal College of
Physicians says
“are pushing more people into our hospitals
and trapping them there for longer.”
Will the Prime Minister do what my hon. Friend
the Member for Leicester South (Jonathan Ashworth)
has called for and bring forward now the extra
£700 million allocated in 2019 and put it
into social care so that we do not have this
problem of people staying too long in hospital
when they should be cared for by a social
care system?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
asked me those questions in the last PMQs
before Christmas. [Interruption.] He may find
it difficult to believe that somebody will
say the same thing that they said a few weeks
ago, but we have put extra money into social
care. In the medium term, we are ensuring
that best practice is spread across the country.
He talks about delayed discharges. Some local
authorities, which work with their health
service locally, have virtually no delayed
discharges. Some 50%—half of the delayed
discharges—are in only 24 local authority
areas. What does that tell us? It tells us
that it is about not just funding, but best
practice. If he comes back to me and talks
to me about funding again, he should think
on this: we can only fund social care and
the NHS if we have a strong economy, and we
will only have that with the Conservatives.
>>Jeremy Corbyn: I am sorry to have to bring
the Prime Minister back to the subject of
social care, which I raised before Christmas.
The reason I did so, and will continue to
do so, is that she has not addressed the problem.
The Government have cut £4.6 billion from
the social care budget. The King’s Fund
says that there is a social care funding gap
of almost £2 billion this year.
Earlier this week, the Prime Minister said
that she wanted to create a “shared society”.
Well, we certainly have that: more people
sharing hospital corridors on trolleys; more
people sharing waiting areas in A&amp;E departments;
and more people sharing in the anxiety created
by this Government. Our NHS is in crisis,
but the Prime Minister is in denial. May I
suggest to her that, on the economic question,
she should cancel the corporate tax cuts,
and spend the money where it is needed—on
people in desperate need in social care and
in our hospitals?
>>The Prime Minister: The right hon. Gentleman
talks about a crisis. I suggest he listens
to the right hon. Member for Don Valley (Caroline
Flint), a former Labour Health Minister, who
said that, with Labour,
“It’s always about ‘crisis...the NHS
is on its knees’… We’ve got to be a
bit more grown up about this.”
And he talks to me about restoring the cuts
in corporation tax. The Labour party has already
spent that money eight times. The last thing
the NHS needs is a cheque from Labour that
bounces. The only way that we can ensure that
we have funding for the national health service
is with a strong economy. Yesterday, the right
hon. Gentleman proved that he is not only
incompetent, but that he would destroy our
economy, and that would devastate our national
health service.
>>Mrs Maria Miller (Basingstoke) (Con): Cyber-bullying,
sexting and revenge pornography are part of
British teenage life today; so is a rapid
increase in mental health problems among our
teenagers. How is the Prime Minister helping
to tackle the pressures that teenagers face
in Britain today?
>>The Prime Minister: My right hon. Friend
raises an important point. One of the things
I spoke about, when I spoke about mental health
on Monday, was trying to ensure that we can
provide some better training for staff and
teachers in schools to identify the early
stages of mental health problems for young
people, so that those problems can be addressed.
Something like half of all mental health problems
start before the age of 14, so this is a real
issue that we need to address. We are going
to look at how we can provide that training.
We will also review the mental health services
provided for young people to ensure that we
can identify what is working and make sure
that good practice is spread across the country.
>>Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP): May I begin
with a tribute to Father George Thompson,
who died shortly before Christmas? He led
a remarkable life as a teacher, as a priest
and as the Scottish National party Member
of Parliament for Galloway. We extend our
sympathies to his family.
All of us in this House and across these islands
care about the peace process and about the
democratic institutions in Northern Ireland,
so may I wish the Prime Minister well and
the Taoiseach, the Northern Ireland Secretary
and the political parties all the best in
trying to resolve the serious political difficulties
there? Will the Prime Minister tell us what
the consequences will be if no agreement can
be found?
>>The Prime Minister: First, may I join the
right hon. Gentleman in offering condolences
to the family and friends of the Rev. George
Thompson, who, as he says, was the MP for
Galloway between 1974 and 1979 and, I believe,
was the first former MP in modern times to
be ordained a Roman Catholic priest.
On the issue that the right hon. Gentleman
raises about the political situation in Northern
Ireland, we are obviously treating this with
the utmost seriousness. As he will know, my
right hon. Friend the Northern Ireland Secretary
made a statement in the House earlier this
week on this issue. He has spoken to the First
Minister and the former Deputy First Minister,
and he is urging all parties to work together
to find a way forward. I have also spoken
to the Taoiseach about this issue, so we are
putting every effort into this. The legislation
says that if, within seven days, we do not
have a nomination for a Deputy First Minister,
the matter would go to an election.
>>Angus Robertson: The Prime Minister has
indicated that she wants to take the views
of the elected representatives and the devolved
institutions on Brexit seriously. So it stands
to reason then that if there is no Northern
Ireland Assembly and no Northern Ireland Executive
for much of the time before the March timetable
that she has set for invoking article 50,
she will be unable to consult properly, to
discuss fully and to find agreement on the
complex issues during this period. In these
circumstances, will the Prime Minister postpone
invoking article 50—[Interruption]—or
will she just plough on regardless?
>>The Prime Minister: As the right hon. Gentleman
says, we want to ensure that we do hear the
views from all parts of the United Kingdom.
That is why we have established the JMC European
committee specifically to take views, and
the JMC plenary, which is also obviously meeting
more frequently than previously. I am clear
that, first of all, we want to try to ensure
that, within this period of seven days, we
can find a resolution to the political situation
in Northern Ireland, so that we can to see
the Assembly Government continuing. But I
am also clear that, in the discussions that
we have, it will be possible—it is still
the case that Ministers are in place and that,
obviously, there are executives in place—that
we are still able to take the views of the
Northern Ireland people.
>>Michael Fabricant (Lichfield) (Con): What
recent assessment she has made of the (a)
performance of the economy and (b) adequacy
of provision of public services in Staffordshire;
and if she will make a statement.
>>The Prime Minister: The fundamentals of
the UK’s economy are strong, including in
Staffordshire and the west midlands. Employment
in Staffordshire has risen by over 20,000
since 2010. We have protected schools and
police budgets. We see more doctors and more
nurses in the Burton hospitals trust. Of course,
we are going further than this in the west
midlands by giving new powers to the west
midlands with the devolution deal and with
the election of a directly elected Mayor.
I have to say that I think Andy Street, with
his business and local experience, would be
a very good Mayor for the west midlands.
>>Michael Fabricant: I thank my right hon.
Friend the Prime Minister for that answer.
Unemployment in my constituency—my beautiful
Lichfield constituency—is around 0.7%, and
that is fantastic, but I want it even lower.
I found out that 24% of my constituents work
in the area of the West Midlands Combined
Authority, so can I press my right hon. Friend
just a little further about what she thinks
is needed in the West Midlands Combined Authority
to improve employment still more?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my hon. Friend,
and, of course, I have had the advantage of
having visited his beautiful constituency.
But in relation to the midlands, we have a
very strong ambition to make the midlands
an engine for growth in the UK. That is why
we have plans for the midlands engine that
demonstrate that, when we say we are going
to build an economy that works for everyone,
we actually mean it. In the autumn statement,
my right hon. Friend the Chancellor confirmed
things such as the £5 million for a Birmingham
rail hub and a £250 million midlands engine
investment fund, and we will shortly be publishing
a strategy for the midlands engine. But I
repeat the point that I made: for the west
midlands, having the devolution deal, having
the Mayor and having the right person elected
as Mayor, who I think will be Andy Street,
is absolutely crucial.
>>Ian Murray (Edinburgh South) (Lab): Happy
new year, Mr Speaker. Sir Ivan Rogers, in
his resignation letter, said that people may
have to deliver messages to the Government
that Ministers may find disagreeable. So here
is a message that the Prime Minister may find
disagreeable: her lack of priority for the
single market is putting jobs in Scotland
and the economy at risk. That means her Government
are as big a threat to the Union as the SNP.
Her Government are not worthy of the trust
of Scots, let alone their blind trust, so
will the Prime Minister take this opportunity
to apologise for threatening the Union and
give a solemn promise to every single person
in this country that they will not be a penny
worse off after a Tory Brexit?
>>The Prime Minister: The hon. Gentleman will
be very well aware that I want to see the
best possible trade deal for the United Kingdom
with the EU and the best possible deal for
trading with and operating within the single
European market. When we enter the negotiations,
obviously, that is one of the issues that
I have said that I want to see, and we will
be out there and be delivering on it. Unlike
the sort of downplaying that the hon. Gentleman
does about the approach that we are taking,
I have to say that it is this Government that
is ambitious for the opportunities that are
available to this country once we leave the
European Union.
>>Antoinette Sandbach (Eddisbury) (Con): Cheshire
schools in areas of rurality and areas of
high deprivation will receive some of the
lowest per-pupil funding rates in the country
under the new proposed funding formula. Does
the Prime Minister agree that these discrepancies
must be addressed to ensure that Eddisbury
pupils get the best possible start in life?
>>The Prime Minister: I think everybody recognises
that the way that schools have been funded
in the past has been unfair and many pupils
have been missing out. That is why I think
it is right for us to look at bringing forward
a new fair funding formula, making sure that
funding is attached to children’s needs.
Of course we recognise the particular issues
of rural areas in this, and that is why, within
the fair funding formula, additional funding
for such schools has been included. But, of
course, the Department for Education has this
out for consultation at the moment, and I
would urge my hon. Friend to make her representations
as part of that consultation.
>>Tracy Brabin (Batley and Spen) (Lab): Dewsbury
hospital A&amp;E is set for a downgrade this
year. Over Christmas, I had constituents who
were waiting 20 hours for a bed in a facility
that might not even exist next year. Will
the Prime Minister please face reality and
act now to stop this vital A&E service from
disappearing?
>>The Prime Minister: What the hon. Lady is
referring to, of course, is the plans that
are being put forward at local level to consider—[Interruption.]
>>Mr Speaker: Order. There is far too much
noise. I must say to the hon. Member for Dewsbury
(Paula Sherriff) that if she were behaving
like this in another public place she would
probably be subject to an antisocial behaviour
order.
>>The Prime Minister: I return to the point,
Mr Speaker. Decisions about services in the
local area are rightly taken by the local
national health service, because we believe
that it is local clinicians, and also local
patients and leaders, who know what is best
for their areas. So it is about trying to
tailor the services to provide the best possible
services for the needs of local people, modernising
the care and facilities, and making services
appropriate to the local area. This trust
has an extensive improvement plan to ensure
that both hospitals within it can care for
patients attending accident and emergency
in as timely a way as possible.
>>Richard Fuller (Bedford) (Con): Next Thursday
evening, I will host the first session of
the Bedford community business school, free
of charge and open to all, with 250 local
people sharing a passion for entrepreneurship
and learning tips about business from national
and local business leaders. Will my right
hon. Friend ensure that her forthcoming industrial
strategy has at its heart the passion and
the interest of Britain’s small business
leaders and entrepreneurs?
>>The Prime Minister: I can absolutely give
my hon. Friend that commitment. What is important
is that the industrial strategy will be looking
to the economy of the future—what sort of
economy we want in this country. Crucial to
that will be the growth that is generated
by entrepreneurs and by small businesses—by
the very passion that he has spoken about.
We want to see an environment in which those
who can grow can emerge and develop to provide
future jobs for people and contribute to the
strength of our economy. That is what the
industrial strategy is about; I absolutely
agree with my hon. Friend.
>>Norman Lamb (North Norfolk) (LD): The Prime
Minister, I am sure, will understand, despite
the reassurances, that there are genuine and
really serious concerns among staff across
the NHS and the care system, and patients
and their families, about the pressure that
they are under. For that reason, MPs from
her own party, from the Labour party and from
my party have come together to call for the
Government to establish an NHS and care convention
to engage with the public, so that we can
come up with a long-term settlement for the
NHS and care. Would the Prime Minister be
prepared to meet us to discuss it, so that
she can hear our case?
>>The Prime Minister: I recognise, obviously,
the interest and the attention that the right
hon. Gentleman has given to these issues—of
course, he is a former Health Minister—and
I would be happy to meet him and others, as
he suggests.
>>Edward Argar (Charnwood) (Con): There can
be nothing as distressing for a parent as
the death of their child, particularly where
that child has been murdered. That is what
happened to the two ladies, one of them a
constituent of mine, who set up Justice After
Acquittal, successfully campaigning for voluntary
national standards of support by the Crown
Prosecution Service and by the police for
the families of murder victims following an
acquittal. Those standards are due to be launched
here next Tuesday. Will the Prime Minister
join me in paying tribute to the determination
and energy with which they have campaigned
for their cause, and will she continue to
ensure, as she always has done, that the voices
of the victims of crime and their families
are always listened to?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
a very important point. I am very happy to
join him in paying tribute to these two campaigners.
Indeed, I am sure that the whole House would
want to pay tribute to the work that they
are doing. As he says, I remain committed
to ensuring that the voices of victims are
heard. That is what I did when I was Home
Secretary, if we look at issues such as introducing
new measures to tackle modern slavery, strengthening
the Independent Police Complaints Commission
and legislating in relation to police complaints
and discipline systems to strengthen public
confidence in policing, and a number of other
actions that I took. I am very pleased to
say that my right hon. Friend the current
Home Secretary is taking that same passion
to ensuring that the voices of the victims
of crime are heard and is taking that forward.
>>Joanna Cherry (Edinburgh South West) (SNP):
Across the United Kingdom, many banks are
accelerating their closure of local branches,
with adverse effects on vulnerable and older
people and adverse effects on the high street.
The Royal Bank of Scotland is closing down
branches across Scotland, including those
at Juniper Green and Chesser in my constituency.
Local convenience stores are taking the strain
of processing bills and often face exorbitant
bank charges for the privilege of doing so.
Will the Prime Minister meet me to discuss
how we can realise a situation where banking
across the UK services customers and the real
economy?
>>The Prime Minister: The issue of bank branches
and, indeed, of the accessibility of bank
services is one that is for individual banks
themselves to take and consider, and of course
there are many ways in which people are now
accessing bank services other than by going
physically into an actual bank branch, but
I will certainly look at the issue that the
hon. and learned Lady has raised.
>>Dr James Davies (Vale of Clwyd) (Con): Building
a country that works for everyone means doing
even more to tackle the economic and social
deprivation that has come to afflict pockets
of seaside towns such as Rhyl in my constituency.
Will my right hon. Friend therefore support
Growth Track 360, a locally developed plan
to invest in rail infrastructure to help unlock
the true potential of the north Wales and
Mersey-Dee economic region as an integral
part of the northern powerhouse, connected
to the rest of the country via
the proposed HS2 hub at Crewe?
>>The Prime Minister: I welcome the establishment
of the north Wales and Mersey-Dee rail taskforce
and the work that it is doing. The plan that
my hon. Friend mentions sets out an ambitious
programme of improvements for the area, and
I am sure it will be prioritising the most
promising options. I can say to him that the
Department for Transport will continue to
work closely with the taskforce and with the
Welsh Government to consider what can be jointly
accomplished.
>>Alan Brown (Kilmarnock and Loudoun) (SNP):
As Pensions Minister, Steve Webb misled the
public about the value of the single-rate
pension. He also gave us the Pensions Act
2011. He was rightly booted out by the voters,
yet is now deemed suitable for a knighthood.
Does the Prime Minister not understand that,
unless this Government take action to help
the struggling WASPI women, that knighthood
will be the final insult to these women?
>>The Prime Minister: Action has been taken
on the issue in relation to women’s pensions.
The Government took action to ensure that
the number of people who were affected and
the period for which they were affected would
be reduced, and money was put in to ensure
that that was possible. If the hon. Gentleman
looks at the new structure that is being put
in place for pensions, he will see that women
will actually be some of the greater beneficiaries
of the new structure.
>>Chris White (Warwick and Leamington) (Con):
I welcome the fact that the Prime Minister
has raised awareness of the importance of
child mental health this week, not least because
65% of young people requiring mental health
support in south Warwickshire last year had
to wait over 12 weeks before starting treatment.
Will my right hon. Friend outline how the
new proposals will improve our support network
for such vulnerable young people?
>>The Prime Minister: My hon. Friend raises
an important issue, which was of course alluded
to earlier in this session of Prime Minister’s
questions. We are investing more in mental
health than ever before—we are spending
a record £11.4 billion a year—and it was
of course the Conservative-led Government
that introduced parity of esteem between mental
and physical health, but as I said earlier,
there is more for us to do in ensuring that
appropriate care is available for people.
I cited an example earlier of where I saw
excellent work being done to provide care
and support for people in the community, which
was relieving pressure on accident and emergency,
but also ensuring that people were getting
the best possible care for them, and that
is obviously what we want to see.
>>John Woodcock (Barrow and Furness) (Lab/Co-op):
The strained accident and emergency provision
in my constituency is under review, and the
community further up the Cumbrian coast risks
losing 24-hour access to accident and emergency
and to consultant-led maternity from its local
hospital. I understand that the Prime Minister
will say that these decisions are to be made
locally, but will she at least say that she
can understand the anxiety of expectant mums
who face a 40-mile journey on difficult roads,
which are often blocked, if they have a difficult
birth?
>>The Prime Minister: The problems that are
facing the health service in Cumbria are widely
recognised, and I do understand the concerns
of local people about the services that will
be available for them. We have put robust
national support in place to address some
of the long-standing challenges in Cumbria,
and we are developing a lasting plan to deliver
the high-quality, sustainable services that
patients rightly expect.
The hon. Gentleman is right that these specific
decisions are being taken locally, and no
final decisions have been taken. I recognise
the concern that he has raised previously,
particularly about services at West Cumberland
hospital. There will be considerable involvement
in taking those decisions, but as I say, we
do recognise the local concerns about some
of the long-standing challenges for health
service provision in Cumbria.
>>Dr Caroline Johnson (Sleaford and North
Hykeham) (Con): I know from my career in medicine
that the men and women of our East Midlands
ambulance service do a brave and sterling
job for the people of Sleaford and North Hykeham
and others, saving people’s lives every
day. East Midlands ambulance service responded
to a total of 11,662 999 calls over the Christmas
bank holiday weekend alone, 2,500 of which
were in Lincolnshire. Will the Prime Minister
join me in paying tribute to their dedication,
particularly over the busy winter period,
and tell the House what more the Government
can do to support our ambulance services and
improve response times in rural areas such
as Sleaford and North Hykeham?
>>The Prime Minister: May I thank my hon.
Friend for her question, and also for bringing
her personal experience as a medical professional
to this issue? I am very happy to join her
in paying tribute to the men and women of
the ambulance service for the dedication and
commitment that they show. She asks what the
Government have been doing. We recognise that
ambulance services are very busy, which is
why we see over 2,000 more paramedics now
compared with 2010, and we are increasing
paramedic training places by over 60% this
year. Also, the Department of Health, NHS
Employers and ambulance unions have agreed
changes to the compensation for paramedics,
potentially giving them a pay increase of
up to £14,000 as they progress. We recognise
the excellent work that they do.
>>Gavin Robinson (Belfast East) (DUP): May
I commend the Prime Minister for her considered
statement last night and, indeed, for the
words that she has given this afternoon? She
knows our commitment to the institutions in
Northern Ireland, but would she agree that
nothing can be, or should be, gained from
threatening the peace process, the progress
that we have made or the institutions that
we have fought so hard to sustain in Northern
Ireland?
>>The Prime Minister: The progress that has
been made in Northern Ireland has been hard
won, and we must all recognise that we do
not want to put that progress in jeopardy.
That is why it is so important for the Government,
and for all parties, to work as hard as we
can to see a resolution to this issue, so
that we can see a return to the power-sharing
institutions and ensure that the hard-won
progress can be continued.
>>Nicky Morgan (Loughborough) (Con): I warmly
welcome what my right hon. Friend said about
children’s mental health earlier this week,
but may I draw her attention to another burning
injustice? My constituent Paula Edwards has
been battling cancer for four years. She is
recovering from an operation and has taken
28 weeks off work. She is still employed and
is on half pay, yet her working tax credits
have been stopped, which means that she is
worrying about how to make ends meet rather
than focusing on her recovery. Will my right
hon. Friend ask the Treasury to look at this,
perhaps in the course of Budget preparations?
>>The Prime Minister: I thank my right hon.
Friend for her comments about the mental health
announcements that I have made. I am sorry
to hear of the particular difficulties that
her constituent is experiencing and the distress
that they have caused her. Of course, working
tax credits provide support for low-income
families in work and are designed to incentivise
people to increase their working hours. With
the new universal credit system, we will obviously
have a system of benefits with single, streamlined
payments that encourages work, but I am sure
the Financial Secretary to the Treasury would
be happy to look at the individual case that
my right hon. Friend has raised and the issue
that she has set out.