>> Danny Kinahan (South Antrim) (UUP):
If she will list her official engagements
for Wednesday 29 March.
>> The Prime Minister (Mrs Theresa May)
I would like to update the House on last week’s
terrorist attack. Since my statement on Thursday,
the names of those who died have been released.
They were Aysha Frade, Kurt Cochran, Leslie
Rhodes and, of course, PC Keith Palmer. I
am sure that Members of all parties will join
me in offering our deepest condolences to
their friends and families. The police and
security services’ investigation continues;
two people have been arrested and remain in
custody.
This morning I had meetings with ministerial
colleagues and others, and in addition to
my duties in this House, I shall have further
such meetings later today.
>> Danny Kinahan:
I echo those sentiments and congratulate the
Prime Minister on all the good work done last
week and since that time.
I also congratulate the Prime Minister and
the Government on triggering article 50 today.
I know that this is a momentous action for
the whole of the United Kingdom. Although
I, in common with the right hon. Lady, campaigned
to stay in, we recognise that the people have
spoken, and we offer the Ulster Unionist party’s
full support in ensuring that the negotiations
deliver the best for the whole of the United
Kingdom, and particularly for Northern Ireland.
I ask the Prime Minister to confirm that,
in the extremely improbable event that a border
poll should take place regarding the future
of Northern Ireland within the United Kingdom
during her premiership, her Government would
fully support any official remain campaign,
just as the Government have done in regard
of the EU and indeed Scotland.
>> The Prime Minister:
The hon. Gentleman is absolutely right that
today we give effect to the democratic decision
of the people of the United Kingdom, who voted
for us to leave the European Union. It was
a call to make the United Kingdom a country
that works for everyone, not just the privileged
few. We are, of course, fully committed within
that to ensuring that the unique interests
of Northern Ireland are protected and advanced
as we establish our negotiating position.
Our position has always been clear—that
we strongly support the Belfast agreement,
including the principle of consent that Northern
Ireland’s constitutional position is a matter
for the people of Northern Ireland to determine.
As our manifesto made clear, we have a preference
for Northern Ireland to remain part of the
United Kingdom, and we will never be neutral
in expressing our support for that, because
I believe fundamentally in the strength of
our Union.
>> Mr Ranil Jayawardena (North East Hampshire)
(Con):
Pupils and parents deserve good schools and
real choice in education, including schools
that are focused unashamedly on academic rigour.
Will my right hon. Friend tell us when the
Government will open applications for the
new wave of free schools, and will she confirm
that they will be genuinely free to be run
as they wish, serving the local community
and creating schools that work for everyone?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right. I believe
that schools should be free to be run as best
suits them. We are putting autonomy and freedom
in the hands of strong leaders and outstanding
teachers so that they can deliver an excellent
education. We want to get out of the way of
outstanding education providers so that they
can set up the types of schools that parents
want. That is why we have set out our new
plans to remove the ban on new grammar schools
and the restrictions on new faith schools.
It is a complex area, but we expect to announce
the detail of the next wave of free school
applications following the publication of
our schools White Paper.
>> Jeremy Corbyn (Islington North) (Lab):
I want to begin by paying tribute, as the
Prime Minister did, to the emergency services
across the country, and especially to all
those who responded to the Westminster attack
last Wednesday and those who turned out to
help the victims of the New Ferry explosion
last Saturday. Our thoughts remain with the
injured and those who have lost loved ones,
and we especially thank the police for their
ongoing investigations. Will the Prime Minister
assure us that the police will be given all
the necessary support and resources to take
them through this very difficult period of
investigating what happened last Wednesday?
>> The Prime Minister:
I join the right hon. Gentleman in praising
the work of our emergency services, who, as
he has pointed out, have to deal with a wide
range of incidents. Our focus in the House
has most recently been on the attack that
took place last Wednesday, but we should never
forget that, day in and day out, our emergency
services are working on our behalf and often
putting themselves in danger as a result of
the work that they do.
I can assure the right hon. Gentleman that
I have, of course, been keeping in touch with
both the security services and the Metropolitan
police—as has my right hon. Friend the Home
Secretary—about the current investigation
of the attack last week, and about future
security arrangements. I can also assure him
that they have the resources that they need
in order to carry out their vital work.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Of course we all pay tribute to the police
for the work that they do, but there are some
problems. Between 2015 and 2018 there will
be a real-terms cut of £330 million in central
Government funding for police forces. Can
the Prime Minister assure the House that police
forces all over the country have the necessary
resources with which to do the job?
>> The Prime Minister:
I remind the right hon. Gentleman that we
have protected the police budget in the comprehensive
spending review. I also remind him that the
former shadow Home Secretary, his colleague
the right hon. Member for Leigh (Andy Burnham),
said during the 2015 Labour party conference
that
“savings can be found. The Police say 5
per cent to 10 per cent over the Parliament
is just about do-able.”
We did not accept that. We have actually protected
the police budget. I have been speaking to
police forces, as has my right hon. Friend
the Home Secretary, and they are very clear
about the fact that they have the resources
that they need for the work that they are
doing.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
A survey undertaken recently by the Police
Federation reveals that 55% of serving police
officers say that their morale is low because
of how their funding has been treated. Frontline
policing is vital to tackling crime and terrorism,
but there are 20,000 fewer police officers
and 12,000 fewer officers on the frontline
than there were in 2010. I ask the Prime Minister
again: will she think again about the cuts
in policing, and will she guarantee that policing
on the frontline will be protected so that
every community can be assured that it has
the police officers it needs?
>> The Prime Minister:
As I said to the right hon. Gentleman, we
have protected police budgets, including the
precept that the police are able to raise
locally. But let us just think about what
has happened since 2010. Since then, crimes
that are traditionally measured by the independent
crime survey have fallen by a third, to a
record low. That is due to the work of hard-working
police officers up and down the country, and
they have been backed by this Government.
Yes, we have made them more accountable through
directly elected police and crime commissioners,
and yes, there has been reform of policing—including
reform of the Police Federation, which was
very necessary—but we have ensured that
they have the resources to do their job, and
we now see crime at a record low.
>> Victoria Atkins (Louth and Horncastle)
(Con):
The Royal Air Force is preparing to fly Typhoons
from RAF Coningsby in my constituency to Romania
to support our NATO allies on the border with
Russia. That is happening as President Putin
is locking up his political opponents and
crushing calls for democracy. Will my right
hon. Friend confirm that, as we leave the
European Union, the United Kingdom will continue
to lead NATO in defending that vital border,
and will she pay tribute to the members of
the armed forces who safeguard our democracy
at home and abroad?
>> The Prime Minister:
I am very happy to join my hon. Friend in
paying tribute to the men and women of our
armed forces. They are the best in the world.
They work tirelessly to keep us safe, and
we owe them every gratitude for doing so.
I can also assure her that our commitment
to collective defence and security through
NATO is as strong as ever. We will meet our
NATO pledge to spend 2% of GDP on defence
in every year of this decade, and we plan
to spend £178 billion on the equipment plan
to 2025.
My hon. Friend referred to the work being
done by the Royal Air Force in relation to
Romania. With NATO, we are deploying a battalion
to Estonia and a reconnaissance squadron to
Poland, and I think that shows our very clear
commitment to our collective security and
defence.
>> Angus Robertson (Moray) (SNP):
We associate ourselves with the condolences
given by the Prime Minister and the leader
of the Labour party and their praise for the
emergency and security services during and
in the wake of the appalling terrorist atrocity
last week.
Last year, the Prime Minister promised that
before she triggered article 50 on leaving
the European Union she would secure a UK-wide
approach—an agreement—with the Governments
of—[Interruption.] Last year, the Prime
Minister did make that promise: she promised
that there would be an agreement with the
Governments of Scotland, Wales and Northern
Ireland before she triggered article 50. The
Prime Minister has now triggered article 50,
and she has done so without an agreement;
there is no agreement. Why has she broken
her promise and broken her word?
>> The Prime Minister:
I have been very clear throughout, since the
first visit that I made as Prime Minister
to Edinburgh last July, that we were going
to work with the devolved Administrations
and that we would develop a UK-wide approach,
but that it would be a UK approach that was
taken into the negotiations and that it would
be the United Kingdom Government who took
forward that position—and I would simply
remind the right hon. Gentleman that Scotland
is part of the United Kingdom.
>> Angus Robertson:
People viewing will note that the Prime Minister
did not deny that she said she would seek
a UK-wide approach and agreement with the
Governments of Scotland, Wales and Northern
Ireland, and there is no agreement.
The Scottish Government were elected with
a higher percentage of the vote—a bigger
electoral mandate—than the UK Government.
Yesterday the Scottish Parliament voted by
69 to 59 that people in Scotland should have
a choice about their future. After the negotiations
on the European Union are concluded, there
will be a period for democratic approval of
the outcome. That choice will be exercised
in this Parliament, in the European Parliament
and in 27 member states of the European Union.
Given that everybody else will have a choice
at that time, will the people of Scotland
have a choice about their future?
>> The Prime Minister:
I say to the right hon. Gentleman that we
are taking forward the views of the United
Kingdom into the negotiations with the European
Union on the United Kingdom exiting the European
Union. The Scottish nationalist party consistently
talks—[Hon. Members: “National.”]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. Ms Cherry, this is very unseemly heckling.
You are a distinguished QC; you would not
behave like that in the Scottish courts—you
would be chucked out.
The Prime Minister:
The SNP consistently talks about independence
as the only subject it wishes to talk about.
What I say to the right hon. Gentleman and
his colleagues is this: now is not the time
to be talking about a second independence
referendum. On today of all days we should
be coming together as a United Kingdom to
get the best deal for Britain.
>> Julian Sturdy (York Outer) (Con):
Improving vocational and technical education
is vital in closing our productivity gap,
so can the Prime Minister assure me that vocational
education will enjoy equal status with academic
education, so that as we leave the EU our
young people can be equipped to build the
high-skilled economy of the future?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend raises a very important issue.
It is essential for young people that we give
vocational and technical education the right
esteem and focus, because that is essential
in addressing our productivity gap. We want
to deliver a world-leading technical education
system and create two genuine options for
young people that are equal in esteem. At
the Budget my right hon. Friend the Chancellor
announced a significant package of investment
to implement the most ambitious post-16 reforms
since the introduction of A-levels 70 years
ago. We are going to be investing an extra
half a billion pounds a year in England’s
technical education system and introducing
maintenance loans to support those studying
high-level technical qualifications at prestigious
institutes of technology and national colleges.
>> Bill Esterson (Sefton Central) (Lab):
The Treasury Committee says that for many
small companies, having to fill in a tax return
every three months will mean facing disaster,
and the Federation of Small Businesses says
that the extra annual cost is likely to be
at least £2,700 a year—yet another burden
on business from this Government. The Prime
Minister got it wrong on national insurance;
is she going to backtrack on tax returns as
well?
>> The Prime Minister:
Perhaps the hon. Gentleman should have listened
to the announcement that my right hon. Friend
the Chancellor made in the Budget, when he
indicated that he would delay the introduction
of the change for a year for the smallest
businesses below the VAT threshold. It is
right that Her Majesty’s Revenue and Customs
tries to move to a greater digitisation of
how it operates, enabling it to provide a
better service to those who are completing
their forms. We should always remember that
aspect of what is being proposed.
>> David Mackintosh (Northampton South) (Con):
I welcome the additional money that the Government
have given for adult social care, but it is
important that we also look at long-term solutions.
As part of the long-term review, will the
Prime Minister look at some of the cases in
my constituency, and at the issues with how
the system works for Northamptonshire County
Council and Northampton general hospital?
>> The Prime Minister:
I am grateful for my hon. Friend’s welcome
for the extra money—the £2 billion that
was announced by my right hon. Friend the
Chancellor in the Budget—that is going into
social care. That shows that we have recognised
the pressures and demands on social care,
but it is also important that we ensure that
best practice is delivered across the whole
country. It is not just about money, so we
are also trying to find a long-term, sustainable
solution that will help local authorities
to learn from each other to raise standards
across the whole system. We will bring forward
proposals in a Green Paper later this year
to put the state-funded system on a more secure
and sustainable footing.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
As Home Secretary, the Prime Minister clearly
did not protect police budgets. Last week,
she told me four times:
“We have protected the schools budget.”—[Official
Report, 22 March 2017; Vol. 623, c. 854-855.]
Does she still stand by that statement?
>> The Prime Minister:
We have protected schools’ budgets, and
we are putting record funding into schools.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
Today, the Public Accounts Committee says
of the Department for Education:
“The Department does not seem to understand
the pressures that schools are already under.”
It goes on to say that “Funding per pupil
is reducing in real terms”,
and that school budgets will be cut by £3
billion—equivalent to 8%—by 2020. Is the
Public Accounts Committee wrong?
>> The Prime Minister:
What we will see over the course of this Parliament
is £230 billion going into our schools, but
what matters is the quality of education in
schools. An additional 1.8 million children
are in good or outstanding schools, and this
Government’s policy is to ensure that every
child gets a good school place.
>> Jeremy Corbyn:
The daily experience of many parents who have
children in school is that they receive letters
asking for money. One parent, Elizabeth, wrote
to me to say that she has received a letter
from her daughter’s school asking for a
monthly donation to top up the reduced funds
that it is receiving. This Government’s
cuts to schools are betraying a generation
of our children. If the Prime Minister is
right, the parents are wrong, the teachers
are wrong, the Institute for Fiscal Studies
is wrong, the National Audit Office is wrong,
and the Education Policy Institute is wrong.
Now the Public Accounts Committee, which includes
eight Conservative Members, is also wrong.
Which organisation does back the Prime Minister’s
view on education spending in our schools?
>> The Prime Minister:
As I have just said to the right hon. Gentleman,
we said that we would protect school funding,
and we have; there is a real-terms protection
for the schools budget. We said that we would
protect the money following children into
schools, and we have; the schools budget reaches
£42 billion, as pupil numbers rise, in 2019-20.
But I also have to say to him that it is about
the quality of education that children are
receiving, with 1.8 million more children
in good or outstanding schools than there
were under the Labour Government.
Time and again, the right hon. Gentleman stands
up at Prime Minister’s questions and asks
questions that would lead to more spending.
Let us look at what he has said recently:
on 11 January, more spending; on 8 February,
more spending; on 22 February, more spending;
on 1 and 8 March, more spending; and on 15
and 22 March, more spending. Barely a PMQs
goes by that he does not call for more public
spending. When it comes to spending money
that it does not have, Labour simply cannot
help itself. It is the same old Labour: spend
today and give somebody else the bill tomorrow.
Well, we will not do that to the next generation.
>> Bill Wiggin (North Herefordshire) (Con):
If she will introduce an award in recognition
of the contribution made by munitions workers
in the first and second world wars.
>> The Prime Minister:
I am sure everyone in the House will want
to join me in paying tribute to the thousands
who worked in munitions factories in both
world wars, often in very dangerous conditions.
They produced vital equipment for the armed
forces that helped us to victory. I am sure
my hon. Friend will recognise that, for practical
reasons, it is not possible to pursue individual
awards, but the Department for Business, Energy
and Industrial Strategy would be happy to
work with him to look at further ways of recognising
the collective effort of former munitions
workers.
>> Bill Wiggin:
I thank my right hon. Friend for that answer.
These ladies found that the chemicals in the
shells turned their skin yellow, and they
were nicknamed canary girls. I know my right
hon. Friend is exceptionally busy at the moment,
but could she find just a few moments in her
diary to meet me and some of these canary
girls to recognise their service?
>> The Prime Minister:
I would be very happy to meet some canary
girls. As I said, their work was vital to
the war effort. Their work was, in one sense,
absolutely routine, but in another sense,
it was extremely dangerous, and we should
recognise their efforts.
>> Carolyn Harris (Swansea East) (Lab):
The Prime Minister will be aware that the
Welsh Labour Government have established a
children’s funeral fund. Many independent
and leading funeral providers, such as The
Co-operative and Dignity, have also indicated
that there will be no charges for children’s
and young people’s funerals. I know that
she is a compassionate woman, and I know that
she understands the importance of a children’s
funeral fund, so will she agree to work with
me to further establish this fund, to bring
some comfort to bereaved parents in their
darkest hour?
>> The Prime Minister:
I pay tribute to the hon. Lady, who has campaigned
tirelessly on this issue. Obviously, she is
not just a passionate campaigner, but has
on many occasions spoken movingly in this
House about her own experience, which she
is bringing to bear on this issue. I welcome
the decision that has been taken by the Co-op
to waive funeral fees, and I recognise the
actions of the Welsh Government. Of course
there is some financial support available,
but we are looking at the issue and the problems
faced by parents. We are looking at what more
can be done through cross-Government work,
and I will ask the Minister for the Cabinet
Office, who is leading on that work, to meet
with her to talk about the idea.
>> David T. C. Davies (Monmouth) (Con):
As the Prime Minister will know, the Budget
gave an extra £200 million to the Welsh Labour
Government in order to provide business rates
relief. Does she agree with me and the leader
of Monmouthshire County Council, Peter Fox
OBE, that Welsh Labour must now commit to
spending that money on supporting Welsh businesses
and giving them the same level of support
that is being provided in England by this
Conservative Government?
>> The Prime Minister:
My hon. Friend is absolutely right. As he
says, at the Budget, my right hon. Friend
the Chancellor announced a £200 million boost
for the Welsh Government’s budget. They
will be able to use that money to support
their own priorities, but the people of Wales
will be able to send a very clear signal about
those priorities by voting for Conservative
councillors, like Peter Fox, on 4 May. It
is the UK Government’s actions to support
ordinary working families throughout the country
that will ensure that Wales benefits from
an economy that works for everyone.
>> Tulip Siddiq (Hampstead and Kilburn) (Lab):
During the EU referendum campaign, the now
Foreign Secretary urged people to“take back
control of huge sums of money”—£350 million
a week—“and spend it on our priorities”,Such
as the NHS. The Prime Minister will trigger
article 50 today. Can she confirm precisely
when she wants to fulfil the promise made
by her Cabinet colleague, who is sitting on
the Front Bench and smirking at the British
public?
>> The Prime Minister:
I am very happy—[Interruption.]
>> Mr Speaker:
Order. Boris is sitting perfectly comfortably,
and there is an air of repose about the fellow,
to which we are accustomed. Let us hear from
the Prime Minister.
>> The Prime Minister:
I am very happy to tell the hon. Lady that,
of course, when this country leaves the European
Union, we will have control of our budgets
and we will decide how that money is spent.
>> William Wragg (Hazel Grove) (Con):
With modification, schools in my constituency
welcome the national funding formula. Given
the Leader of the Opposition’s contribution,
I hope that the next part of my question does
not land me on the naughty step. Given that
Stockport schools and other f40 schools have
been at the bottom of the funding pile for
years and therefore have less scope for efficiencies,
will my right hon. Friend consider providing
more immediate support to them?
>> The Prime Minister:
As my hon. Friend is saying, we are aiming
to end the postcode lottery of schools funding,
and as I said, schools funding is now at a
record high. On the minimum funding level,
as I have said before, the Department for
Education has heard representations on the
issue on this national funding formula and
will, of course, be considering those. This
was a consultation, and there have been a
lot of responses to it, but it is an historic
and complex reform. There has been general
agreement for many years that reform is needed.
We want to get this right, which is why we
are carefully considering the representations.
>> Alex Salmond (Gordon) (SNP):
After nine months of this Prime Minister’s
approach to Brexit, Northern Ireland is deadlocked,
the Welsh are alienated, Scotland is going
for a referendum, the English are split down
the middle, and Brexit MPs are walking out
of Commons Committees because they do not
like home truths. Has the Prime Minister considered,
in terms of invoking article 50, that “now
is not the time”?
>> The Prime Minister:
What the UK Government are doing in invoking
article 50 is putting into practice the democratic
vote of the British people on 23 June last
year in a referendum. There was a referendum
in 2014 in Scotland, when the Scottish people
voted to remain part of the United Kingdom.
I suggest the right hon. Gentleman and his
colleagues put that into practice.
>> Matt Warman (Boston and Skegness) (Con):
Three quarters of my constituents voted to
leave the European Union. Does the Prime Minister
agree that triggering article 50 marks a watershed
moment, not only in this country’s control
of immigration and our sovereignty, but in
listening to the views of people who were
forgotten for far too long?
>> The Prime Minister:
I absolutely agree with my hon. Friend; in
invoking article 50, we are not just putting
into practice the views of the British people
as set out in that referendum on 23 June last
year. Crucially, that was not just a vote
about leaving the EU; it was a vote about
changing this country for the future. This
Government have a clear plan for Britain that
will change this country, and that will see
us with a more global outlook, a stronger
economy, a fairer society and a more united
nation.
>> Marion Fellows (Motherwell and Wishaw)
(SNP):
The people expect the Prime Minister to follow
her party’s manifesto, and to abide by a
majority vote of this Parliament, so why does
she say that the First Minister of Scotland
should do the opposite?
>> The Prime Minister:
What I say is that as we face this historic
moment of invoking article 50 and setting
in process the negotiations for the future
of this country and its relationship with
the European Union, now is the time to pull
together and not try to hang apart.
>> Derek Thomas (St Ives) (Con):
On Friday, thousands of people up and down
this country will be raising funds for and
awareness of brain tumour research. Many of
them will know someone, or have had a family
member, who has had a brain tumour or is suffering
from one, yet brain tumour research receives
only about 1% of all cancer research funding,
despite this being the biggest cancer killer
of children and adults under 40. Will the
Prime Minister join me in commending all these
people raising awareness and funds, and see
what more we can do to increase funding for
brain tumour research?
>> The Prime Minister:
This is a very important area, and the UK
has a good record of research on brain tumours.
My hon. Friend is absolutely right that the
people who are raising funds for this important
cause should be commended. As he said, many
of them will have had personal experience
of brain tumours, in one way or another. It
is important that we recognise that there
are many killers out there that often do not
receive the publicity and support that other
causes get. We should recognise their importance
and commend those who are raising funds.
>> Mr John Spellar (Warley) (Lab):
As we enter the world of article 50, will
the Prime Minister say what she is doing to
ensure that national and local government
prioritise the buying of British goods and
services? I have to say that her record on
police vehicles when she was Home Secretary
does not give us much cause for optimism.
>> The Prime Minister:
We have, as a Government, been encouraging
the procurement of British goods and services.
The right hon. Gentleman asks what we can
do for local authorities; if people around
the country want local authorities that take
their best interests to heart, they should
vote Conservative.
>> Paul Scully (Sutton and Cheam) (Con):
I congratulate my right hon. Friend the Prime
Minister on invoking article 50 today. Does
she agree that this needs to be the end of
the phoney war—the end of the posturing
we have heard from Members on the Opposition
Benches—and that we must now focus on the
detail for every industry, sector and community,
so that we get a bespoke deal that we can
all get behind?
>> The Prime Minister:
I absolutely agree with my hon. Friend. Now
is the time for us to come together, and to
be united across the House and across the
country to ensure that we work for the best
possible deal for the United Kingdom, and
the best possible future for us all.
>> Mr Nigel Dodds (Belfast North) (DUP):
The Prime Minister has rightly emphasised
her determination to deliver for all the constituent
parts of the United Kingdom on this historic
day. While others are content to moan and
whine, we want to see that delivery, and we
are confident that she will make it happen.
In Northern Ireland, some have walked away
from their responsibilities with regard to
devolution, but we want to see devolution
up and running, and to have a functioning
Northern Ireland Government, and we have set
no preconditions in the way of that. If others
continue to stay away from devolution and
walk away, will the Prime Minister pledge
to work ever more closely with those of us
in this House to defend and protect the interests
of Northern Ireland?
>> The Prime Minister:
We all want to work together to ensure that
we protect the best interests of Northern
Ireland. As the right hon. Gentleman just
said, ensuring that we have strong devolved
government in Northern Ireland is important
for the future. It is important, so that we
can build on the significant progress that
has been made in recent years for the people
of Northern Ireland. I urge all parties to
come to the talks with a view to finding a
way through, so that Northern Ireland can
once again be restored to devolved government.
>> James Berry (Kingston and Surbiton) (Con):
Does the Prime Minister agree that social
media companies need to take action now to
remove extremist and hate materials from their
platforms proactively, and to foot the bill
for the police, who are currently doing those
companies’ dirty work at the taxpayer’s
expense?
>> The Prime Minister:
The whole question of working with the companies
to ensure that extremist material is removed
as quickly as possible is not new; that work
has been going on for a number of years. Through
the counter terrorism internet referral unit,
we have a process that enables the police
to take material down. Some 250,000 pieces
of material have been taken down from the
internet since February 2010, and there has
been a significant increase in that activity
in the past couple of years or so. My right
hon. Friend the Home Secretary will meet the
companies later this week to talk to them
about this important issue. We do not want
to see extremist material on the internet,
and we want to see companies taking action
to remove material that encourages hate and
division.
>> Alison McGovern (Wirral South) (Lab):
Late on Saturday night, a massive explosion
devastated New Ferry in my constituency. We
are thinking of all those who are hurt. It
is a miracle that more people were not injured.
The community now faces significant dereliction.
Will the Prime Minister join me in thanking
all those who looked after my community over
the weekend and in recent days? Will she arrange
for me a meeting with the Secretary of State
for Communities and Local Government, so that
we can discuss how the Government can help
us to rebuild New Ferry?
>> The Prime Minister:
I am very happy to do both of those things.
First, I commend and thank all those in the
emergency services and others who worked so
hard to support the hon. Lady’s local community
when the devastating explosion took place.
That work will continue; it did not happen
just over the weekend. Support will be given
to the community into the future. I am very
happy to ask the Secretary of State for Communities
and Local Government to meet her and discuss
how that community can be rebuilt and can
overcome the impact of this explosion.